<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//Samba-Team//DTD DocBook V4.2-Based Variant V1.0//EN" "http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<refentry id="smbmount.8">

<refmeta>
	<refentrytitle>smbmount</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
</refmeta>


<refnamediv>
	<refname>smbmount</refname>
	<refpurpose>mount an smbfs filesystem</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
	<cmdsynopsis>
		<command>smbmount</command>
		<arg choice="req">service</arg>
		<arg choice="req">mount-point</arg>
		<arg choice="opt">-o options</arg>
	</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsect1>
	<title>DESCRIPTION</title>

	<para><command>smbmount</command> mounts a Linux SMB filesystem. It 
	is usually invoked as <command>mount.smbfs</command> by
	the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>mount</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry> command when using the 
	"-t smbfs" option. This command only works in Linux, and the kernel must
	support the smbfs filesystem.</para>

	<para>WARNING: <command>smbmount</command> is deprecated and not
	maintained any longer. <command>mount.cifs</command> (mount -t cifs)
	should be used instead of <command>smbmount</command>.</para>

	<para>Options to <command>smbmount</command> are specified as a comma-separated
	list of key=value pairs. It is possible to send options other
	than those listed here, assuming that smbfs supports them. If
	you get mount failures, check your kernel log for errors on
	unknown options.</para>

	<para><command>smbmount</command> is a daemon. After mounting it keeps running until
	the mounted smbfs is umounted. It will log things that happen
	when in daemon mode using the "machine name" smbmount, so
	typically this output will end up in <filename>log.smbmount</filename>. The <command>
	smbmount</command> process may also be called mount.smbfs.</para>

	<note><para> <command>smbmount</command> 
	calls <citerefentry><refentrytitle>smbmnt</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry> to do the actual mount. You 
	must make sure that <command>smbmnt</command> is in the path so 
	that it can be found. </para></note>
	
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>OPTIONS</title>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
		<term>username=&lt;arg&gt;</term>
		<listitem><para>
		specifies the username to connect as. If this is not given, then the environment variable <envar> USER</envar>
		is used. This option can also take the form "user%password" or "user/workgroup" or "user/workgroup%password"
		to allow the password and workgroup to be specified as part of the username.
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>password=&lt;arg&gt;</term>
		<listitem><para>
		specifies the SMB password. If this option is not given then the environment 
		variable <literal>PASSWD</literal> is used. If it can find no password 
		<command>smbmount</command> will prompt for a password, unless the guest option is given.
		</para>

		<para>
		Note that passwords which contain the argument delimiter character (i.e. a comma ',') will failed to be parsed
		correctly on the command line.  However, the same password defined in the PASSWD environment variable or a
		credentials file (see below) will be read correctly.
		</para>
		</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>credentials=&lt;filename&gt;</term>
		<listitem><para>specifies a file that contains a username and/or password. 
The format of the file is:
<programlisting>
username=value
password=value
</programlisting></para>

		<para>This is preferred over having passwords in plaintext in a
		shared file, such as <filename>/etc/fstab</filename>. Be sure to protect any
		credentials file properly.
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>krb</term>
		<listitem><para>Use kerberos (Active Directory). </para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>netbiosname=&lt;arg&gt;</term>
		<listitem><para>sets the source NetBIOS name. It defaults 
		to the local hostname. </para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>uid=&lt;arg&gt;</term>
		<listitem><para>sets the uid that will own all files on
		the mounted filesystem.
		It may be specified as either a username or a numeric uid.
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		
		
		<varlistentry>
		<term>gid=&lt;arg&gt;</term>
		<listitem><para>sets the gid that will own all files on
		the mounted filesystem.
		It may be specified as either a groupname or a numeric 
		gid. </para></listitem>		
		</varlistentry>
		
		
		<varlistentry>
		<term>port=&lt;arg&gt;</term>
		<listitem><para>sets the remote SMB port number. The default 
		is 445, fallback is 139. </para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		
		
		<varlistentry>
		<term>fmask=&lt;arg&gt;</term>
		<listitem><para>sets the file mask. This determines the 
		permissions that remote files have in the local filesystem. 
		This is not a umask, but the actual permissions for the files.
		The default is based on the current umask. </para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		

		<varlistentry>
		<term>dmask=&lt;arg&gt;</term>
		<listitem><para>Sets the directory mask. This determines the 
		permissions that remote directories have in the local filesystem. 
		This is not a umask, but the actual permissions for the directories.
		The default is based on the current umask. </para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		
		
		<varlistentry>
		<term>debug=&lt;arg&gt;</term>
		<listitem><para>Sets the debug level. This is useful for 
		tracking down SMB connection problems. A suggested value to
		start with is 4. If set too high there will be a lot of
		output, possibly hiding the useful output.</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		
		
		<varlistentry>
		<term>ip=&lt;arg&gt;</term>
		<listitem><para>Sets the destination host or IP address.
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>



		<varlistentry>
		<term>workgroup=&lt;arg&gt;</term>
		<listitem><para>Sets the workgroup on the destination </para>
		</listitem>
		</varlistentry>


		<varlistentry>
		<term>sockopt=&lt;arg&gt;</term>
		<listitem><para>Sets the TCP socket options. See the <ulink
		url="smb.conf.5.html#SOCKETOPTIONS"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>smb.conf</refentrytitle>
		<manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry></ulink> <parameter>socket options</parameter> option.
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>


		<varlistentry>
		<term>scope=&lt;arg&gt;</term>
		<listitem><para>Sets the NetBIOS scope </para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>guest</term>
		<listitem><para>Don't prompt for a password </para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>ro</term>
		<listitem><para>mount read-only </para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>rw</term><listitem><para>mount read-write </para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>iocharset=&lt;arg&gt;</term>
		<listitem><para>
		sets the charset used by the Linux side for codepage
		to charset translations (NLS). Argument should be the
		name of a charset, like iso8859-1. (Note: only kernel
		2.4.0 or later)
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>codepage=&lt;arg&gt;</term>
		<listitem><para>
		sets the codepage the server uses. See the iocharset
		option. Example value cp850. (Note: only kernel 2.4.0
		or later)
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>ttl=&lt;arg&gt;</term>
		<listitem><para>
		sets how long a directory listing is cached in milliseconds
		(also affects visibility of file size and date
		changes). A higher value means that changes on the
		server take longer to be noticed but it can give
		better performance on large directories, especially
		over long distances. Default is 1000ms but something
		like 10000ms (10 seconds) is probably more reasonable
		in many cases.
		(Note: only kernel 2.4.2 or later)
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

	</variablelist>


</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>ENVIRONMENT VARIABLES</title>

	<para>The variable <envar>USER</envar> may contain the username of the
	person using the client.  This information is used only if the
	protocol level is high enough to support session-level
	passwords. The variable can be used to set both username and
	password by using the format username%password.</para>

	<para>The variable <envar>PASSWD</envar> may contain the password of the
	person using the client.  This information is used only if the
	protocol level is high enough to support session-level
	passwords.</para>

	<para>The variable <envar>PASSWD_FILE</envar> may contain the pathname
	of a file to read the password from. A single line of input is
	read and used as the password.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>OTHER COMMANDS</title>

	<para>
	File systems that have been mounted using the <command>smbmount</command>
	can be unmounted using the <command>smbumount</command> or the UNIX system
	<command>umount</command> command.
	</para>

</refsect1>


<refsect1>
	<title>BUGS</title>

	<para>Passwords and other options containing , can not be handled.
	For passwords an alternative way of passing them is in a credentials
	file or in the PASSWD environment.</para>

	<para>The credentials file does not handle usernames or passwords with
	leading space.</para>

	<para>One smbfs bug is important enough to mention here, even if it
	is a bit misplaced:</para>

	<itemizedlist>

	<listitem><para>Mounts sometimes stop working. This is usually
	caused by smbmount terminating. Since smbfs needs smbmount to
	reconnect when the server disconnects, the mount will eventually go
	dead. An umount/mount normally fixes this. At least 2 ways to
	trigger this bug are known.</para></listitem>

	</itemizedlist>

	<para>Note that the typical response to a bug report is suggestion
	to try the latest version first. So please try doing that first,
	and always include which versions you use of relevant software
	when reporting bugs (minimum: samba, kernel, distribution)</para>

</refsect1>


<refsect1>
	<title>SEE ALSO</title>

	<para>Documentation/filesystems/smbfs.txt in the linux kernel
	source tree may contain additional options and information.</para>

	<para>FreeBSD also has a smbfs, but it is not related to smbmount</para>

	<para>For Solaris, HP-UX and others you may want to look at <citerefentry><refentrytitle>smbsh</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> or at other solutions, such as 
	Sharity or perhaps replacing the SMB server with a NFS server.</para>

</refsect1>


<refsect1>
	<title>AUTHOR</title>
	
	<para>Volker Lendecke, Andrew Tridgell, Michael H. Warfield 
	and others.</para>
	
	<para>The current maintainer of smbfs and the userspace
	tools <command>smbmount</command>, <command>smbumount</command>,
	and <command>smbmnt</command> is <ulink 
	url="mailto:urban@teststation.com">Urban Widmark</ulink>.
	The <ulink url="mailto:samba@samba.org">SAMBA Mailing list</ulink>
	is the preferred place to ask questions regarding these programs.
	</para>
	
	<para>The conversion of this manpage for Samba 2.2 was performed 
	by Gerald Carter. The conversion to DocBook XML 4.2 for Samba 3.0
	was done by Alexander Bokovoy.</para>
</refsect1>

</refentry>
