<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//Samba-Team//DTD DocBook V4.2-Based Variant V1.0//EN" "http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<preface lang="en-US">
<title>About the Cover Artwork</title>

	<para>
	The cover artwork of this book continues the freedom theme of the first
	edition of <quote>Samba-3 by Example</quote>. The history of civilization
	demonstrates the fragile nature of freedom. It can be lost in a moment,
	and once lost, the cost of recovering liberty can be incredible. The last
	edition cover featured Alfred the Great who liberated England from the
	constant assault of Vikings and Norsemen. Events in England that
	finally liberated the common people came about in small steps, but
	the result should not be under-estimated. Today, as always, freedom and
	liberty are seldom appreciated until they are lost. If we can not quantify
	what is the value of freedom, we shall be little motivated to protect it.
	</para>

	<para>
	<emphasis>Samba-3 by Example Cover Artwork:</emphasis> The British houses
	of parliament are a symbol of the Westminster system of government. This form
	of government permits the people to govern themselves at the lowest level, yet
	it provides for courts of appeal that are designed to protect freedom and to
	hold back all forces of tyranny. The clock is a pertinent symbol of the
	importance of time and place.
	</para>

	<para>
	The information technology industry is being challenged by the imposition of
	new laws, hostile litigation, and the imposition of significant constraint 
	of practice that threatens to remove the freedom to develop and deploy open 
	source software solutions. Samba is a software solution that epitomizes freedom
	of choice in network interoperability for Microsoft Windows clients.
	</para>

	<para>
	I hope you will take the time needed to deploy it well, and that you may realize
	the greatest benefits that may be obtained. You are free to use it in ways never
	considered, but in doing so there may be some obstacles. Every obstacle that is
	overcome adds to the freedom you can enjoy. Use Samba well, and it will serve
	you well.
	</para>

</preface>
