<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Samba-Team//DTD DocBook V4.2-Based Variant V1.0//EN" "http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<chapter id="Other-Clients">
<chapterinfo>
	&author.jelmer;
	&author.jht;
	&author.danshearer;
	<author>&person.jmcd;<contrib>OS/2</contrib></author>
	<pubdate>5 Mar 2001</pubdate>
</chapterinfo>

<title>Samba and Other CIFS Clients</title>

<para>This chapter contains client-specific information.</para>

<sect1>
<title>Macintosh Clients</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>DAVE</primary></indexterm>
Yes. <ulink url="http://www.thursby.com/">Thursby</ulink> has a CIFS client/server called <ulink
url="http://www.thursby.com/products/dave.html">DAVE</ulink>.  They test it against Windows 95, Windows
NT/200x/XP, and Samba for compatibility issues. At the time of this writing, DAVE was at version 5.1. Please
refer to Thursby's Web site for more information regarding this product.
</para>

<para> 
<indexterm><primary>Netatalk</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>CAP</primary></indexterm>
Alternatives include two free implementations of AppleTalk for several kinds of UNIX machines and several more
commercial ones.  These products allow you to run file services and print services natively to Macintosh
users, with no additional support required on the Macintosh. The two free implementations are <ulink
url="http://www.umich.edu/~rsug/netatalk/">Netatalk</ulink> and <ulink
url="http://www.cs.mu.oz.au/appletalk/atalk.html">CAP</ulink>.  What Samba offers MS Windows users, these
packages offer to Macs.  For more info on these packages, Samba, and Linux (and other UNIX-based systems), see
<ulink noescape="1" url="http://www.eats.com/linux_mac_win.html">http://www.eats.com/linux_mac_win.html.</ulink>
</para>

<para>Newer versions of the Macintosh (Mac OS X) include Samba.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>OS2 Client</title>

	<sect2>
		<title>Configuring OS/2 Warp Connect or OS/2 Warp 4</title>

		<para>Basically, you need three components:</para>
		
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>The File and Print Client (IBM peer)</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>TCP/IP (Internet support) </para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>The <quote>NetBIOS over TCP/IP</quote> driver (TCPBEUI)</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		
		<para>Installing the first two together with the base operating 
		system on a blank system is explained in the Warp manual. If Warp 
		has already been installed, but you now want to install the 
		networking support, use the <quote>Selective Install for Networking</quote> 
		object in the <quote>System Setup</quote> folder.</para>

		<para>Adding the <quote>NetBIOS over TCP/IP</quote> driver is not described 
		in the manual and just barely in the online documentation. Start 
		<command>MPTS.EXE</command>, click on <guiicon>OK</guiicon>, click on <guimenu>Configure LAPS</guimenu>, and click 
		on <guimenu>IBM OS/2 NETBIOS OVER TCP/IP</guimenu> in  <guilabel>Protocols</guilabel>. This line 
		is then moved to <guilabel>Current Configuration</guilabel>. Select that line, 
		click on <guimenuitem>Change number</guimenuitem>, and increase it from 0 to 1. Save this
		configuration.</para>

		<para>If the Samba server is not on your local subnet, you 
		can optionally add IP names and addresses of these servers 
		to the <guimenu>Names List</guimenu> or specify a  WINS server (NetBIOS 
		Nameserver in IBM and RFC terminology). For Warp Connect, you 
		may need to download an update for <constant>IBM Peer</constant> to bring it on 
		the same level as Warp 4. See the IBM OS/2 Warp Web page</para>
	</sect2>
	
	<sect2>
		<title>Configuring Other Versions of OS/2</title>
	
		<para>This sections deals with configuring OS/2 Warp 3 (not Connect), OS/2 1.2, 1.3 or 2.x.</para>
		
		<para>You can use the free Microsoft LAN Manager 2.2c Client for OS/2 that is
		available from 
		<ulink noescape="1" url="ftp://ftp.microsoft.com/BusSys/Clients/LANMAN.OS2/">
		ftp://ftp.microsoft.com/BusSys/Clients/LANMAN.OS2/</ulink>. In a nutshell, edit
	the file <filename>\OS2VER</filename> in the root directory of the OS/2 boot partition and add the lines:</para>
		
		<para><programlisting>
		20=setup.exe
		20=netwksta.sys
		20=netvdd.sys
		</programlisting></para>
		
		<para>before you install the client. Also, do not use the included NE2000 driver because it is buggy.
		Try the NE2000 or NS2000 driver from <ulink noescape="1" url="ftp://ftp.cdrom.com/pub/os2/network/ndis/">
 		ftp://ftp.cdrom.com/pub/os2/network/ndis/</ulink> instead.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	
	<sect2>
		<title>Printer Driver Download for OS/2 Clients</title>

		<para>Create a share called <smbconfsection name="[PRINTDRV]"/> that is 
		world-readable. Copy your OS/2 driver files there. The <filename>.EA_</filename>
		files must still be separate, so you will need to use the original install files
		and not copy an installed driver from an OS/2 system.</para>
		
		<para>Install the NT driver first for that printer. Then, add to your &smb.conf; a parameter,
		<smbconfoption name="os2 driver map"><replaceable>filename</replaceable></smbconfoption>. 
		Next, in the file specified by <replaceable>filename</replaceable>, map the 
		name of the NT driver name to the OS/2 driver name as follows:</para>
		
		<para><parameter><replaceable>nt driver name</replaceable> = <replaceable>os2 driver name</replaceable>.<replaceable>device name</replaceable></parameter>, e.g.,</para>

		<para><parameter>
		HP LaserJet 5L = LASERJET.HP LaserJet 5L</parameter></para>

		<para>You can have multiple drivers mapped in this file.</para>
	
		<para>If you only specify the OS/2 driver name, and not the 
		device name, the first attempt to download the driver will 
		actually download the files, but the OS/2 client will tell 
		you the driver is not available. On the second attempt, it 
		will work. This is fixed simply by adding the device name
  		 to the mapping, after which it will work on the first attempt.
		</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Windows for Workgroups</title>

<sect2>
<title>Latest TCP/IP Stack from Microsoft</title>

<para>Use the latest TCP/IP stack from Microsoft if you use Windows
for Workgroups. The early TCP/IP stacks had lots of bugs.</para>

<para> 
Microsoft has released an incremental upgrade to its TCP/IP 32-bit VxD drivers. The latest release can be
found at ftp.microsoft.com, located in <filename>/Softlib/MSLFILES/TCP32B.EXE</filename>.  There is an
update.txt file there that describes the problems that were fixed. New files include
<filename>WINSOCK.DLL</filename>, <filename>TELNET.EXE</filename>, <filename>WSOCK.386</filename>,
<filename>VNBT.386</filename>, <filename>WSTCP.386</filename>, <filename>TRACERT.EXE</filename>,
<filename>NETSTAT.EXE</filename>, and <filename>NBTSTAT.EXE</filename>.
</para>

<para>
More information about this patch is available in <ulink
url="http://support.microsoft.com/kb/q99891/">Knowledge Base article 99891</ulink>.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Delete .pwl Files After Password Change</title>

<para>
Windows for Workgroups does a lousy job with passwords. When you change passwords on either
the UNIX box or the PC, the safest thing to do is delete the .pwl files in the Windows
directory. The PC will complain about not finding the files, but will soon get over it,
allowing you to enter the new password.
</para>

<para> 
If you do not do this, you may find that Windows for Workgroups remembers and uses the old
password, even if you told it a new one.
</para>

<para> 
Often Windows for Workgroups will totally ignore a password you give it in a dialog box.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Configuring Windows for Workgroups Password Handling</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>admincfg.exe</primary></indexterm>
There is a program call <filename>admincfg.exe</filename> on the last disk (disk 8) of the WFW 3.11 disk set.
To install it, type <userinput>EXPAND A:\ADMINCFG.EX_ C:\WINDOWS\ADMINCFG.EXE</userinput>.  Then add an icon
for it via the <application>Program Manager</application> <guimenu>New</guimenu> menu.  This program allows
you to control how WFW handles passwords, Disable Password Caching and so on, for use with <smbconfoption
name="security">user</smbconfoption>.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Password Case Sensitivity</title>

<para>Windows for Workgroups uppercases the password before sending it to the server.
UNIX passwords can be case-sensitive though. Check the &smb.conf; information on
<smbconfoption name="password level"/> to specify what characters
Samba should try to uppercase when checking.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Use TCP/IP as Default Protocol</title>

<para>To support print queue reporting, you may find
that you have to use TCP/IP as the default protocol under
Windows for Workgroups. For some reason, if you leave NetBEUI as the default,
it may break the print queue reporting on some systems.
It is presumably a Windows for Workgroups bug.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="speedimpr">
<title>Speed Improvement</title>

<para>
Note that some people have found that setting <parameter>DefaultRcvWindow</parameter> in
the <smbconfsection name="[MSTCP]"/> section of the 
<filename>SYSTEM.INI</filename> file under Windows for Workgroups to 3072 gives a
big improvement.
</para>

<para>
My own experience with DefaultRcvWindow is that I get a much better
performance with a large value (16384 or larger). Other people have
reported that anything over 3072 slows things down enormously. One
person even reported a speed drop of a factor of 30 when he went from
3072 to 8192.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Windows 95/98</title>

<para>
When using Windows 95 OEM SR2, the following updates are recommended where Samba
is being used. Please note that the changes documented in 
<link linkend="speedimpr">Speed Improvement</link> will affect you once these
updates  have been installed.
</para>

<para> 
There are more updates than the ones mentioned here. Refer to the
Microsoft Web site for all currently available updates to your specific version
of Windows 95.
</para>

<simplelist>
<member>Kernel Update: KRNLUPD.EXE</member>
<member>Ping Fix: PINGUPD.EXE</member>
<member>RPC Update: RPCRTUPD.EXE</member>
<member>TCP/IP Update: VIPUPD.EXE</member>
<member>Redirector Update: VRDRUPD.EXE</member>
</simplelist>

<para>
Also, if using <application>MS Outlook,</application> it is desirable to 
install the <command>OLEUPD.EXE</command> fix. This
fix may stop your machine from hanging for an extended period when exiting
Outlook, and you may notice a significant speedup when accessing network
neighborhood services.
</para>

<sect2>
<title>Speed Improvement</title>

<para>
Configure the Windows 95 TCP/IP registry settings to give better
performance. I use a program called <command>MTUSPEED.exe</command> that I got off the
Internet. There are various other utilities of this type freely available.
</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Windows 2000 Service Pack 2</title>

<para> 
There are several annoyances with Windows 2000 SP2, one of which
only appears when using a Samba server to host user profiles
to Windows 2000 SP2 clients in a Windows domain. This assumes
that Samba is a member of the domain, but the problem will
most likely occur if it is not.
</para>

<para> 
In order to serve profiles successfully to Windows 2000 SP2 
clients (when not operating as a PDC), Samba must have 
<smbconfoption name="nt acl support">no</smbconfoption>
added to the file share that houses the roaming profiles.
If this is not done, then the Windows 2000 SP2 client will
complain about not being able to access the profile (Access 
Denied) and create multiple copies of it on disk (DOMAIN.user.001,
DOMAIN.user.002, and so on). See the &smb.conf; man page
for more details on this option. Also note that the 
<smbconfoption name="nt acl support"/> parameter was formally a global parameter in
releases prior to Samba 2.2.2.
</para>

<para> 
<link linkend="minimalprofile">Following example</link> provides a minimal profile share.
</para>

<example id="minimalprofile">
<title>Minimal Profile Share</title>
<smbconfblock>
<smbconfsection name="[profile]"/>
<smbconfoption name="path">/export/profile</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="create mask">0600</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="directory mask">0700</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="nt acl support">no</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="read only">no</smbconfoption>
</smbconfblock>
</example>

<para>
The reason for this bug is that the Windows 200x SP2 client copies
the security descriptor for the profile that contains
the Samba server's SID, and not the domain SID. The client
compares the SID for SAMBA\user and realizes it is
different from the one assigned to DOMAIN\user; hence,
<errorname>access denied</errorname> message.
</para>

<para>
When the <smbconfoption name="nt acl support"/> parameter is disabled, Samba will send
the Windows 200x client a response to the QuerySecurityDescriptor trans2 call, which causes the client
to set a default ACL for the profile. This default ACL includes:
</para>

<para><emphasis>DOMAIN\user 	<quote>Full Control</quote></emphasis>></para>

<note><para>This bug does not occur when using Winbind to
create accounts on the Samba host for Domain users.</para></note>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Windows NT 3.1</title>

<para>If you have problems communicating across routers with Windows 
NT 3.1 workstations, read <ulink url="http://support.microsoft.com/default.aspx?scid=kb;Q103765">this Microsoft Knowledge Base article:</ulink>.

</para>

</sect1>

</chapter>
