<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Samba-Team//DTD DocBook V4.2-Based Variant V1.0//EN" "http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<chapter id="install">
<chapterinfo>
	&author.tridge;
	&author.jelmer;
	&author.jht;
	&author.kauer;
	&author.danshearer;
	<!-- Isn't some of this written by others as well? -->

</chapterinfo>

<title>How to Install and Test SAMBA</title>

<sect1>
	<title>Obtaining and Installing Samba</title>

	<para>
	<indexterm><primary>packages</primary></indexterm>
	Binary packages of Samba are included in almost any Linux or UNIX distribution. There are also some
	packages available at <ulink url="http://samba.org/">the Samba home page</ulink>. Refer to the manual of your
	operating system for details on installing packages for your specific operating system.
	</para>

	<para>
	<indexterm><primary>compile</primary></indexterm>
	If you need to compile Samba from source, check <link linkend="compiling">How to Compile Samba</link>.
	</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
	<title>Configuring Samba (smb.conf)</title>

	<para>
	<indexterm><primary>/etc/samba/smb.conf</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>SWAT</primary></indexterm>
	Samba's configuration is stored in the &smb.conf; file, which usually resides in
	<filename>/etc/samba/smb.conf</filename> or <filename>/usr/local/samba/lib/smb.conf</filename>. You can either
	edit this file yourself or do it using one of the many graphical tools that are available, such as the
	Web-based interface SWAT, that is included with Samba.
	</para>

	<sect2>
	<title>Configuration File Syntax</title>

	<para>
	<indexterm><primary>section name</primary></indexterm>
	The &smb.conf; file uses the same syntax as the various old <filename>.ini</filename> files in Windows
	3.1: Each file consists of various sections, which are started by putting the section name between brackets
	(<literal>[]</literal>) on a new line. Each contains zero or more key/value pairs separated by an equality
	sign (<literal>=</literal>). The file is just a plaintext file, so you can open and edit it with your favorite
	editing tool.
	</para>

	<para>
	<indexterm><primary>meta-service</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>print</primary><secondary>queue</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>share</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>spooler.</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>print</primary><secondary>spooler</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>spool</primary><secondary>directory</secondary></indexterm>
	Each section in the &smb.conf; file represents either a share or a meta-service on the Samba server. The
	section <literal>[global]</literal> is special, since it contains settings that apply to the whole Samba
	server.  Samba supports a number of meta-services, each of which serves its own purpose. For example, the
	<literal>[homes]</literal> share is a meta-service that causes Samba to provide a personal home share for
	each user. The <literal>[printers]</literal> share is a meta-service that establishes print queue support
	and that specifies the location of the intermediate spool directory into which print jobs are received
	from Windows clients prior to being dispatched to the UNIX/Linux print spooler.
	</para>

	<para>
<indexterm><primary>printers</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>meta-service</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>printcap</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>lpstat</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>CUPS API</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>browseable</primary></indexterm>
	The <literal>printers</literal> meta-service will cause every printer that is either specified in a
	<literal>printcap</literal> file, via the <command>lpstat</command>,  or via the CUPS API, to be
	published as a shared print queue. The <literal>printers</literal> stanza in the &smb.conf; file can
	be set as not browseable. If it is set to be browseable, then it will be visible as if it is a share.
	That makes no sense given that this meta-service is responsible only for making UNIX system printers
	available as Windows print queues. If a <literal>comment</literal> parameter is specified, the value
	of it will be displayed as part of the printer name in Windows Explorer browse lists.
	</para>

	<para>
	<indexterm><primary>stanza</primary></indexterm>
	Each section of the &smb.conf; file that specifies a share, or a meta-service, is called a stanza.
	The <literal>global</literal> stanza specifies settings that affect all the other stanzas in the
	&smb.conf; file. Configuration parameters are documented in the &smb.conf; man page. Some parameters
	can be used only in the <literal>global</literal> stanza, some only in share or meta-service stanzas,
	and some can be used globally or just within a share or meta-service stanza.
	</para>

	<para>
	<indexterm><primary>minimal</primary><secondary>configuration</secondary></indexterm>
	<link linkend="smbconfminimal">A minimal smb.conf</link> contains a very minimal &smb.conf;.
	<indexterm><primary>minimal configuration</primary></indexterm>
	</para>

	<example id="smbconfminimal">
		<title>A minimal smb.conf</title>
		<smbconfblock>

		<smbconfsection name="[global]"/>
		<smbconfoption name="workgroup">WKG</smbconfoption>
		<smbconfoption name="netbios name">MYNAME</smbconfoption>
		<smbconfsection name="[share1]"/>
		<smbconfoption name="path">/tmp</smbconfoption>

		<smbconfsection name="[share2]"/>
		<smbconfoption name="path">/my_shared_folder</smbconfoption>
		<smbconfoption name="comment">Some random files</smbconfoption>
	</smbconfblock>
	</example>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="tdbdocs">
	<title>TDB Database File Information</title>

	<para>
	This section contains brief descriptions of the databases that are used by Samba-3.
	</para>

	<para>
<indexterm><primary>tdb file locations</primary></indexterm>
	The directory in which Samba stores the tdb files is determined by compile-time directives. Samba-3 stores
	tdb files in two locations. The best way to determine these locations is to execute the following
	command:
<screen>
&rootprompt; smbd -b | grep PRIVATE_DIR
   PRIVATE_DIR: /etc/samba/private
</screen>
	This means that the confidential tdb files are stored in the <filename>/etc/samba/private</filename>
	directory. Samba-3 also uses a number of tdb files that contain more mundane data. The location of
	these files can be found by executing:
<screen>
&rootprompt; smbd -b | grep LOCKDIR
   LOCKDIR: /var/lib/samba
</screen>
	Therefore the remaining control files will, in the example shown, be stored in the
	<filename>/var/lib/samba</filename> directory.
	</para>

	<para>
<indexterm><primary>tdb file descriptions</primary></indexterm>
	The persistent tdb files are described in <link linkend="tdbpermfiledesc">the Persistent TDB File
	Descriptions table</link>. All persistent tdb files should be regularly backed up. Use the
	<command>tdbbackup</command> utility to backup the tdb files. All persistent tdb files must be
	preserved during machine migrations, updates and upgrades.
	</para>

	<para>
	The temporary tdb files do not need to be backed up, nor do they need to be preseved across machine
	migrations, updates or upgrades. The temporary tdb files are described in <link linkend="tdbtempfiledesc">
	the Temporary TDB File Descriptions</link>.
	</para>

        <table frame='all' id="tdbpermfiledesc"><title>Persistent TDB File Descriptions</title>
        <tgroup cols='2'>
			<colspec align="left"/>
			<colspec align="justify" colwidth="1*"/>
			<colspec align="left"/>
                <thead>
                <row>
                        <entry align="left">Name</entry>
                        <entry align="justify">Description</entry>
                </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
		<row>
			<entry>account_policy</entry>
			<entry><para>Samba/NT account policy settings, includes password expiration settings.</para></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
			<entry>group_mapping</entry>
			<entry><para>Mapping table from Windows groups/SID to UNIX groups.</para></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
			<entry>ntdrivers</entry>
			<entry><para>Stores per-printer installed driver information.</para></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
			<entry>ntforms</entry>
			<entry><para>Stores per-printer installed forms information.</para></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
			<entry>ntprinters</entry>
			<entry><para>Stores the per-printer devmode configuration settings.</para></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
			<entry>passdb</entry>
			<entry><para>
				Exists only when the tdbsam passwd backend is used. This file stores the
				SambaSAMAccount information. Note: This file requires that user POSIX account information is
				availble from either the /etc/passwd file, or from an alternative system source.
			</para></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
			<entry>registry</entry>
			<entry><para>
				Read-only Samba database of a Windows registry skeleton that provides support for exporting 
				various database tables via the winreg RPCs.
			</para></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
			<entry>secrets</entry>
			<entry><para>
				This file stores the Workgroup/Domain/Machine SID, the LDAP directory update password, and
				a further collection of critical environmental data that is necessary for Samba to operate
				correctly. This file contains very sensitive information that must be protected. It is stored
				in the PRIVATE_DIR directory.
			</para></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
			<entry>share_info</entry>
			<entry><para>Stores per-share ACL information.</para></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
			<entry>winbindd_idmap</entry>
			<entry><para>Winbindd's local IDMAP database.</para></entry>
		</row>
		</tbody>
	</tgroup>
	</table>

        <table frame='all' id="tdbtempfiledesc"><title>Temporary TDB File Descriptions</title>
        <tgroup cols='3'>
			<colspec align="left"/>
			<colspec align="justify" colwidth="1*"/>
			<colspec align="left"/>
                <thead>
                <row>
                        <entry align="left">Name</entry>
                        <entry align="justify">Description</entry>
                        <entry align="center">Backup</entry>
                </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
		<row>
			<entry>brlock</entry>
			<entry><para>Byte-range locking information.</para></entry>
			<entry>No</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
			<entry>connections</entry>
			<entry><para>A temporary cache for current connection information used to enforce max connections.</para></entry>
			<entry>no</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
			<entry>eventlog/*tdb</entry>
			<entry><para>Records of eventlog entries. In most circumstances this is just a cache of system logs.</para></entry>
			<entry>no</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
			<entry>gencache</entry>
			<entry><para>Generic caching database for dead WINS servers and trusted domain data.</para></entry>
			<entry>no</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
			<entry>login_cache</entry>
			<entry><para>A temporary cache for login information, in particular bad password attempts.</para></entry>
			<entry>no</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
			<entry>messages</entry>
			<entry><para>Temporary storage of messages being processed by smbd.</para></entry>
			<entry>no</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
			<entry>netsamlogon_cache</entry>
			<entry><para>Caches user net_info_3 structure data from net_samlogon requests (as a domain member).</para></entry>
			<entry>no</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
			<entry>perfmon/*.tdb</entry>
			<entry><para>Performance counter information.</para></entry>
			<entry>no</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
			<entry>printing/*.tdb</entry>
			<entry><para>Cached output from lpq command created on a per-print-service basis.</para></entry>
			<entry>no</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
			<entry>schannel_store</entry>
			<entry><para>
				A confidential file, stored in the PRIVATE_DIR, containing crytographic connection
				information so that clients that have temporarily disconnected can reconnect without
				needing to renegotiate the connection setup process.
			</para></entry>
			<entry>no</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
			<entry>sessionid</entry>
			<entry><para>Temporary cache for miscellaneous session information and for utmp handling.</para></entry>
			<entry>no</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
			<entry>unexpected</entry>
			<entry><para>Stores packets received for which no process is actively listening.</para></entry>
			<entry>no</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
			<entry>winbindd_cache</entry>
			<entry><para>Cache of Identity information received from an NT4 domain or from ADS. Includes user
				lists, etc.</para></entry>
			<entry>yes</entry>
		</row>
		</tbody>
	</tgroup>
	</table>

</sect2>

<sect2>
	<title>Starting Samba</title>

	<para>
	<indexterm><primary>daemon</primary></indexterm>
	Samba essentially consists of two or three daemons. A daemon is a UNIX application that runs in the background and provides services.
	An example of a service is the Apache Web server for which the daemon is called <command>httpd</command>. In the case of Samba there
	are three daemons, two of which are needed as a minimum.
	</para>

	<para>
	The Samba server is made up of the following daemons:
	</para>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry><term>nmbd</term>
			<listitem><para>
			<indexterm><primary>smbd</primary></indexterm>
			<indexterm><primary>starting samba</primary><secondary>smbd</secondary></indexterm>
			This daemon handles all name registration and resolution requests. It is the primary vehicle involved
			in network browsing. It handles all UDP-based protocols. The <command>nmbd</command> daemon should
			be the first command started as part of the Samba startup process.
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry><term>smbd</term>
			<listitem><para>
			<indexterm><primary>nmbd</primary></indexterm>
			<indexterm><primary>starting samba</primary><secondary>nmbd</secondary></indexterm>
			This daemon handles all TCP/IP-based connection services for file- and print-based operations. It also
			manages local authentication. It should be started immediately following the startup of <command>nmbd</command>.
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry><term>winbindd</term>
			<listitem><para>
			<indexterm><primary>winbindd</primary></indexterm>
			<indexterm><primary>starting samba</primary><secondary>winbindd</secondary></indexterm>
			This daemon should be started when Samba is a member of a Windows NT4 or ADS domain. It is also needed when
			Samba has trust relationships with another domain. The <command>winbindd</command> daemon will check the
			&smb.conf; file for the presence of the <parameter>idmap uid</parameter> and <parameter>idmap gid</parameter>
			parameters. If they are are found, <command>winbindd</command> will use the values specified for
			for UID and GID allocation. If these parameters are not specified, <command>winbindd</command>
			will start but it will not be able to allocate UIDs or GIDs.
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<para>
	<indexterm><primary>startup</primary><secondary>process</secondary></indexterm>
	When Samba has been packaged by an operating system vendor, the startup process is typically a custom feature of its
	integration into the platform as a whole. Please refer to your operating system platform administration manuals for
	specific information pertaining to correct management of Samba startup.
	</para>

</sect2>
	
<sect2>
	<title>Example Configuration</title>
	
	<para>
	<indexterm><primary>examples</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>source code</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>distribution</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>tarball</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>package</primary></indexterm>
	There are sample configuration files in the examples subdirectory in the source code distribution tarball
	package. It is suggested you read them carefully so you can see how the options go together in practice. See
	the man page for all the options.  It might be worthwhile to start out with the
	<filename>smb.conf.default</filename> configuration file and adapt it to your needs. It contains plenty of comments.
	</para>

	<para>
	<indexterm><primary>simplest</primary><secondary>configuration</secondary></indexterm>
	The simplest useful configuration file would contain something like that shown in
	<link linkend="simple-example">Another simple smb.conf File</link>.
	<indexterm><primary>simple configuration</primary></indexterm>
	</para>

<example id="simple-example">
<title>Another simple smb.conf File</title>
<smbconfblock>
<smbconfsection name="[global]"/>
<smbconfoption name="workgroup">&example.workgroup;</smbconfoption>

<smbconfsection name="[homes]"/>
<smbconfoption name="guest ok">no</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="read only">no</smbconfoption>
</smbconfblock>
</example>
	
	<para>
	<indexterm><primary>connections</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>account</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>login name</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>service name</primary></indexterm>
	This will allow connections by anyone with an account on the server, using either
	their login name or <smbconfsection name="homes"/> as the service name.
	(Note: The workgroup that Samba should appear in must also be set. The default
	workgroup name is WORKGROUP.)
	</para>
	
	<para>
	<indexterm><primary>smbd</primary></indexterm>
	Make sure you put the &smb.conf; file in the correct place. Note, the correct location of this file
	depends on how the binary files were built. You can discover the correct location by executing from
	the directory that contains the <command>smbd</command> command file:
<screen>
&rootprompt; smbd -b | grep smb.conf
</screen>
	</para>

	<para>
	<indexterm><primary>security</primary><secondary>settings</secondary></indexterm>
	For more information about security settings for the <smbconfsection name="[homes]"/> share, please refer to 
	<link linkend="securing-samba">Securing Samba</link>.
	</para>

<sect3>
	<title>Test Your Config File with <command>testparm</command></title>

	<para>
	<indexterm><primary>validate</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>testparm</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>misconfigurations</primary></indexterm>
	It's important to validate the contents of the &smb.conf; file using the &testparm; program.
	If testparm runs correctly, it will list the loaded services. If not, it will give an error message.
	Make sure it runs correctly and that the services look reasonable before proceeding. Enter the command: 
	<screen>
	&rootprompt; testparm /etc/samba/smb.conf
	</screen>
	Testparm will parse your configuration file and report any unknown parameters or incorrect syntax.
	It also performs a check for common misconfigurations and will issue a warning if one is found.
	</para>

	<para>
	Always run testparm again whenever the &smb.conf; file is changed!
	</para>

	<para>
	<indexterm><primary>smbd</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>nmbd</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>winbindd</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>configuration</primary><secondary>documentation</secondary></indexterm>
	The &smb.conf; file is constantly checked by the Samba daemons <command>smbd</command> and every instance of
	itself that it spawns, <command>nmbd</command> and <command>winbindd</command>. It is good practice to
	keep this file as small as possible. Many administrators prefer to document Samba configuration settings
	and thus the need to keep this file small goes against good documentation wisdom. One solution that may
	be adopted is to do all documentation and configuration in a file that has another name, such as
	<filename>smb.conf.master</filename>. The <command>testparm</command> utility can be used to generate a
	fully optimized &smb.conf; file from this master configuration and documentation file as shown here:
<screen>
&rootprompt; testparm -s smb.conf.master > smb.conf
</screen>
	This administrative method makes it possible to maintain detailed configuration change records while at
	the same time keeping the working &smb.conf; file size to the minimum necessary.
	</para>

</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2>
	<title>SWAT</title>

	<para>
	<indexterm><primary>swat</primary></indexterm>
	SWAT is a Web-based interface that can be used to facilitate the configuration of Samba.  SWAT might not
	be available in the Samba package that shipped with your platform, but in a separate package. If you need to build SWAT please read the SWAT man page regarding compilation, installation, and
	configuration of SWAT from the source code.
	</para>

	<para>
	To launch SWAT, just run your favorite Web browser and point it to
	<ulink url="http://localhost:901/" noescape="1">http://localhost:901/</ulink>.
	Replace <replaceable>localhost</replaceable> with the name of the computer on which
	Samba is running if that is a different computer than your browser.
	</para>

	<para>
	SWAT can be used from a browser on any IP-connected machine, but be aware that connecting from a remote
	machine leaves your connection open to password sniffing because passwords will be sent over the wire in the clear.
	</para>

	<para>
	Please note that re-writing the configuration file using SWAT will
	remove all comments!
	More information about SWAT can be found in <link linkend="SWAT">The Samba Web Administration Tool</link>.
	</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
	<title>List Shares Available on the Server</title>

	<para>
	To list shares that are available from the configured Samba server, execute the
	following command:
	</para>

<para><screen>
&prompt;<userinput>smbclient -L <replaceable>yourhostname</replaceable></userinput>
</screen></para>

	<para>
	You should see a list of shares available on your server. If you do not, then
	something is incorrectly configured. This method can also be used to see what shares 
	are available on other SMB servers, such as Windows 2000.
	</para>

	<para>
	If you choose user-level security, you may find that Samba requests a password
	before it will list the shares. See the <command>smbclient</command> man page for details.
	You can force it to list the shares without a password by adding the option
	<option>-N</option> to the command line. 
	</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
	<title>Connect with a UNIX Client</title>
	
	<para>
	Enter the following command:
<screen>
&prompt;<userinput>smbclient <replaceable> //yourhostname/aservice</replaceable></userinput>
</screen></para>
	
	<para>Typically <replaceable>yourhostname</replaceable> is the name of the host on which &smbd;
	has been installed. The <replaceable>aservice</replaceable> is any service that has been defined in the &smb.conf;
	file. Try your username if you just have a <smbconfsection name="[homes]"/> section in the &smb.conf; file.</para>

	<para>Example: If the UNIX host is called <replaceable>bambi</replaceable> and a valid login name
	is <replaceable>fred</replaceable>, you would type:</para>

<para><screen>
&prompt;<userinput>smbclient //<replaceable>bambi</replaceable>/<replaceable>fred</replaceable></userinput>
</screen></para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
	<title>Connect from a Remote SMB Client</title>

	<para>
	Now that Samba is working correctly locally, you can try to access it from other clients. Within a few
	minutes, the Samba host should be listed in the Network Neighborhood on all Windows clients of its subnet.
	Try browsing the server from another client or "mounting" it.
	</para>

	<para>
	Mounting disks from a DOS, Windows, or OS/2 client can be done by running a command such as:
<screen>
&dosprompt;<userinput>net use m: \\servername\service</userinput>
</screen>
	Where the drive letter m: is any available drive letter. It is important to double-check that the
	service (share) name that you used does actually exist.
	</para>

	<para>
	Try printing, for example,
<screen>
&dosprompt;<userinput>net use lpt1:	\\servername\spoolservice</userinput>
</screen>
	The <literal>spoolservice</literal> is the name of the printer (actually the print queue) on the target
	server. This will permit all print jobs that are captured by the lpt1: port on the Windows client to
	be sent to the printer that owns the spoolservice that has been specified.
	</para>

<para>
<screen>&dosprompt;<userinput>print filename</userinput>
</screen></para>

	<sect2>
	<title>What If Things Don't Work?</title>
	
	<para>
	You might want to read <link linkend="diagnosis">The Samba Checklist</link>.  If you are still
	stuck, refer to <link linkend="problems">Analyzing and Solving Samba Problems</link>.  Samba has
	been successfully installed at thousands of sites worldwide.  It is unlikely that your particular problem is
	unique, so it might be productive to perform an Internet search to see if someone else has encountered your
	problem and has found a way to overcome it.
	</para>

	<para>
	If you are new to Samba, and particularly if you are new to Windows networking, or to UNIX/Linux,
	the book <quote>Samba-3 by Example</quote> will help you to create a validated network environment.
	Simply choose from the first five chapters the network design that most closely matches site needs,
	then follow the simple step-by-step procedure to deploy it. Later, when you have a working network
	you may well want to refer back to this book for further insight into opportunities for improvement.
	</para>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
	<title>Still Stuck?</title>

	<para>
	The best advice under the stress of abject frustration is to cool down! That may be challenging
	of itself, but while you are angry or annoyed your ability to seek out a solution is somewhat
	undermined. A cool head clears the way to finding the answer you are looking for. Just remember,
	every problem has a solution &smbmdash; there is a good chance that someone else has found it
	even though you can't right now. That will change with time, patience and learning.
	</para>

	<para>
	Now that you have cooled down a bit, please refer to <link linkend="diagnosis">the Samba Checklist</link>
	for a process that can be followed to identify the cause of your problem.
	</para>

	</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Common Errors</title>

<para>
The following questions and issues are raised repeatedly on the Samba mailing list.
</para>

<sect2>
	<title>Large Number of smbd Processes</title>

	<para>
	Samba consists of three core programs: &nmbd;, &smbd;, and &winbindd;. &nmbd; is the name server message daemon,
	&smbd; is the server message daemon, and &winbindd; is the daemon that handles communication with domain controllers.
	</para>

	<para>
	If Samba is <emphasis>not</emphasis> running as a WINS server, then there will be one single instance of
	 &nmbd; running on your system. If it is running as a WINS server, then there will be
	two instances &smbmdash; one to handle the WINS requests.
	</para>

	<para>
	&smbd; handles all connection requests. It spawns a new process for each client
	connection made. That is why you may see so many of them, one per client connection.
	</para>

	<para>
	&winbindd; will run as one or two daemons, depending on whether or not it is being
	run in <emphasis>split mode</emphasis> (in which case there will be two instances).
	</para>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
		<title>Error Message: open_oplock_ipc</title>

	<para>
	An error message is observed in the log files when &smbd; is started: <quote>open_oplock_ipc: Failed to
	get local UDP socket for address 100007f. Error was Cannot assign requested.</quote>
	</para>

	<para>
	Your loopback device isn't working correctly. Make sure it is configured correctly. The loopback
	device is an internal (virtual) network device with the IP address <emphasis>127.0.0.1</emphasis>.
	Read your OS documentation for details on how to configure the loopback on your system.
	</para>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
		<title><quote><errorname>The network name cannot be found</errorname></quote></title>

		<para>
		This error can be caused by one of these misconfigurations:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>You specified a nonexisting path
			for the share in &smb.conf;.</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>The user you are trying to access the share with does not 
			have sufficient permissions to access the path for
			the share. Both read (r) and access (x) should be possible.</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>The share you are trying to access does not exist.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	</sect2>
</sect1>

</chapter>
