<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Samba-Team//DTD DocBook V4.2-Based Variant V1.0//EN" "http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<chapter id="InterdomainTrusts">
<chapterinfo>
	&author.jht;
	&author.mimir;
	<author>&person.jelmer;<contrib>drawing</contrib></author>
        <author>
                <firstname>Stephen</firstname><surname>Langasek</surname>
                <affiliation>
                        <address><email>vorlon@netexpress.net</email></address>
                </affiliation>
        </author>
	<pubdate>April 3, 2003</pubdate>
</chapterinfo>

<title>Interdomain Trust Relationships</title>


<para>
<indexterm><primary>Interdomain Trusts</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>LDAP</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>trusts</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>samba-to-samba trusts</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Active Directory</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>NT4-style domain</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>trust relationships</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ADS</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>LDAP-based</primary></indexterm>
Samba-3 supports NT4-style domain trust relationships. This is a feature that many sites
will want to use if they migrate to Samba-3 from an NT4-style domain and do not want to
adopt Active Directory or an LDAP-based authentication backend. This chapter explains
some background information regarding trust relationships and how to create them. It is now
possible for Samba-3 to trust NT4 (and vice versa), as well as to create Samba-to-Samba 
trusts.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>winbind</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>UID range</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>GID range</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>daemon</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>winbindd</primary></indexterm>
The use of interdomain trusts requires use of <command>winbind</command>, so the
<command>winbindd</command> daemon must be running. Winbind operation in this mode is
dependent on the specification of a valid UID range and a valid GID range in the &smb.conf; file.
These are specified respectively using:
<smbconfblock>
<smbconfoption name="idmap uid">10000-20000</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="idmap gid">10000-20000</smbconfoption>
</smbconfblock>
<indexterm><primary>passdb backend</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>POSIX user accounts</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>maximum value</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>4294967295</primary></indexterm>
The range of values specified must not overlap values used by the host operating system and must
not overlap values used in the passdb backend for POSIX user accounts. The maximum value is
limited by the upper-most value permitted by the host operating system. This is a UNIX kernel
limited parameter. Linux kernel 2.6-based systems support a maximum value of 4294967295 
(32-bit unsigned variable).
</para>

<note><para>
<indexterm><primary>winbind</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>trusting domain</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>trusted domain</primary></indexterm>
The use of winbind is necessary only when Samba is the trusting domain, not when it is the
trusted domain.
</para></note>

<sect1>
<title>Features and Benefits</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>scalability</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>trust relationships</primary></indexterm>
Samba-3 can participate in Samba-to-Samba as well as in Samba-to-MS Windows NT4-style
trust relationships. This imparts to Samba scalability similar to that with MS Windows NT4.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>scalable backend</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>authentication database</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>LDAP</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>interdomain trusts</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ADS</primary></indexterm>
Given that Samba-3 can function with a scalable backend authentication database such as LDAP, and given its
ability to run in primary as well as backup domain control modes, the administrator would be well-advised to
consider alternatives to the use of interdomain trusts simply because, by the very nature of how trusts
function, this system is fragile.  That was, after all, a key reason for the development and adoption of
Microsoft Active Directory.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Trust Relationship Background</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>security domains</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>nonhierarchical</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>security structure</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>large organizations</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>delegation</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>administrative responsibilities</primary></indexterm>
MS Windows NT3/4-type security domains employ a nonhierarchical security structure.
The limitations of this architecture as it effects the scalability of MS Windows networking
in large organizations is well known. Additionally, the flat namespace that results from
this design significantly impacts the delegation of administrative responsibilities in
large and diverse organizations.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>ADS</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Kerberos</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>LDAP</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>limitations</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>domain security</primary></indexterm>
Microsoft developed Active Directory Service (ADS), based on Kerberos and LDAP, as a means
of circumventing the limitations of the older technologies. Not every organization is ready
or willing to embrace ADS. For small companies the older NT4-style domain security paradigm
is quite adequate, and so there remains an entrenched user base for whom there is no direct
desire to go through a disruptive change to adopt ADS.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>security domains</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>access rights</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>privileges</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>trusts</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>trusted domain</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>trusting domain</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>one direction</primary></indexterm>
With Windows NT, Microsoft introduced the ability to allow different security domains
to effect a mechanism so users from one domain may be given access rights and privileges
in another domain. The language that describes this capability is couched in terms of
<emphasis>trusts</emphasis>. Specifically, one domain will <emphasis>trust</emphasis> the users
from another domain. The domain from which users can access another security domain is
said to be a trusted domain. The domain in which those users have assigned rights and privileges
is the trusting domain. With NT3.x/4.0 all trust relationships are always in one direction only,
so if users in both domains are to have privileges and rights in each others' domain, then it is
necessary to establish two relationships, one in each direction.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>security domain</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>nontransitive</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>trust relationship</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>transitive</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>explicit trust</primary></indexterm>
Further, in an NT4-style MS security domain, all trusts are nontransitive. This means that if there are three
domains (let's call them red, white, and blue), where red and white have a trust relationship, and white and
blue have a trust relationship, then it holds that there is no implied trust between the red and blue domains.
Relationships are explicit and not transitive.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>ADS</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>security contexts</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>trust relationships</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>two-way trust</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Windows 2000</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>security domains</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>NT4-style domains</primary></indexterm>
New to MS Windows 2000 ADS security contexts is the fact that trust relationships are two-way by default.
Also, all inter-ADS domain trusts are transitive. In the case of the red, white, and blue domains, with
Windows 2000 and ADS, the red and blue domains can trust each other. This is an inherent feature of ADS
domains. Samba-3 implements MS Windows NT4-style interdomain trusts and interoperates with MS Windows 200x ADS
security domains in similar manner to MS Windows NT4-style domains.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Native MS Windows NT4 Trusts Configuration</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>Interdomain Trusts</primary><secondary>creating</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>two-way trust</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>security credentials</primary></indexterm>
There are two steps to creating an interdomain trust relationship. To effect a two-way trust
relationship, it is necessary for each domain administrator to create a trust account for the 
other domain to use in verifying security credentials.
</para>


<sect2>
<title>Creating an NT4 Domain Trust</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>domain trust</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>trust relationships</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>>Domain User Manager</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>remote domain</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>standard confirmation</primary></indexterm>
For MS Windows NT4, all domain trust relationships are configured using the 
<application>Domain User Manager</application>. This is done from the Domain User Manager Policies
entry on the menu bar. From the <guimenu>Policy</guimenu> menu, select
<guimenuitem>Trust Relationships</guimenuitem>. Next to the lower box labeled
<guilabel>Permitted to Trust this Domain</guilabel> are two buttons, <guibutton>Add</guibutton>
and <guibutton>Remove</guibutton>. The <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button will open a panel in which
to enter the name of the remote domain that will be able to assign access rights to users in 
your domain. You will also need to enter a password for this trust relationship, which the 
trusting domain will use when authenticating users from the trusted domain.
The password needs to be typed twice (for standard confirmation).
</para>

</sect2>


<sect2>
<title>Completing an NT4 Domain Trust</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>trust relationship</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>trusting domain</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>trusted domain</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>remote domain</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>password assigned</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Interdomain Trusts</primary><secondary>Completing</secondary></indexterm>
A trust relationship will work only when the other (trusting) domain makes the appropriate connections
with the trusted domain. To consummate the trust relationship, the administrator launches the
Domain User Manager from the menu selects <guilabel>Policies</guilabel>, then select
<guilabel>Trust Relationships</guilabel>, and clicks on the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button
next to the box that is labeled <guilabel>Trusted Domains</guilabel>. A panel opens in which
must be entered the name of the remote domain as well as the password assigned to that trust.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Interdomain Trust Facilities</title>


<para>
<indexterm><primary>two-way trust</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>trust relationship</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>trust established</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>one-way trust</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Windows NT4 domains</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Interdomain Trusts</primary><secondary>Facilities</secondary></indexterm>
A two-way trust relationship is created when two one-way trusts are created, one in each direction.
Where a one-way trust has been established between two MS Windows NT4 domains (let's call them
DomA and DomB), the following facilities are created:
</para>

<figure id="trusts1">
	<title>Trusts overview.</title>
	<imagefile>trusts1</imagefile>
</figure>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	DomA (completes the trust connection) <parameter>Trusts</parameter> DomB.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	DomA is the <parameter>Trusting</parameter> domain.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	DomB is the <parameter>Trusted</parameter> domain (originates the trust account).
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Users in DomB can access resources in DomA.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Users in DomA cannot access resources in DomB.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Global groups from DomB can be used in DomA.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Global groups from DomA cannot be used in DomB.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	DomB does appear in the logon dialog box on client workstations in DomA.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	DomA does not appear in the logon dialog box on client workstations in DomB.
	</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	Users and groups in a trusting domain cannot be granted rights, permissions, or access
	to a trusted domain.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	The trusting domain can access and use accounts (users/global groups) in the
	trusted domain.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Administrators of the trusted domain can be granted administrative rights in the 
	trusting domain.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Users in a trusted domain can be given rights and privileges in the trusting
	domain.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Trusted domain global groups can be given rights and permissions in the trusting
	domain.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Global groups from the trusted domain can be made members in local groups on
	MS Windows domain member machines.
	</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Configuring Samba NT-Style Domain Trusts</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>interdomain trust</primary></indexterm>
This description is meant to be a fairly short introduction about how to set up a Samba server so
that it can participate in interdomain trust relationships. Trust relationship support in Samba
is at an early stage, so do not be surprised if something does not function as it should.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>peer domain</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>trust relationship</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Windows NT4 Server</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>between domains</primary></indexterm>
Each of the procedures described next assumes the peer domain in the trust relationship is controlled by a
Windows NT4 server. However, the remote end could just as well be another Samba-3  domain. It can be clearly
seen, after reading this document, that combining Samba-specific parts of what's written in the following
sections leads to trust between domains in a purely Samba environment.
</para>

<sect2 id="samba-trusted-domain">
<title>Samba as the Trusted Domain</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>trusted party</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>special account</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>trusting party</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>PDC</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>smbpasswd</primary></indexterm>
In order to set the Samba PDC to be the trusted party of the relationship, you first need
to create a special account for the domain that will be the trusting party. To do that,
you can use the <command>smbpasswd</command> utility. Creating the trusted domain account is 
similar to creating a trusted machine account. Suppose, your domain is
called SAMBA, and the remote domain is called RUMBA. The first step
will be to issue this command from your favorite shell:
</para>

<para>
<screen>
&rootprompt; <userinput>smbpasswd -a -i rumba</userinput>
New SMB password: <userinput>XXXXXXXX</userinput>
Retype SMB password: <userinput>XXXXXXXX</userinput>
Added user rumba$
</screen>

where <option>-a</option> means to add a new account into the
passdb database and <option>-i</option> means to <quote>create this
account with the Interdomain trust flag</quote>.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>account name</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>remote domain</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>password database</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>/etc/passwd</primary></indexterm>
The account name will be <quote>rumba$</quote> (the name of the remote domain).
If this fails, you should check that the trust account has been added to the system
password database (<filename>/etc/passwd</filename>). If it has not been added, you
can add it manually and then repeat the previous step.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>password</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>new account</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>confirm the trust</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Windows NT Server</primary></indexterm>
After issuing this command, you will be asked to enter the password for the account. You can use any password
you want, but be aware that Windows NT will not change this password until 7 days following account creation.
After the command returns successfully, you can look at the entry for the new account (in the standard way as
appropriate for your configuration) and see that the account's name is really RUMBA$ and it has the
<quote>I</quote> flag set in the flags field. Now you are ready to confirm the trust by establishing it from
Windows NT Server.
</para>


<para>
<indexterm><primary>User Manager</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>trusted domain name</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>relationship password</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>remote domain</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>established</primary></indexterm>
Open <application>User Manager for Domains</application> and from the <guimenu>Policies</guimenu> menu, select
<guimenuitem>Trust Relationships...</guimenuitem>.  Beside the <guilabel>Trusted domains</guilabel> list box,
click the <guimenu>Add...</guimenu> button. You will be prompted for the trusted domain name and the
relationship password. Type in SAMBA, as this is the name of the remote domain and the password used at the
time of account creation.  Click on <guibutton>OK</guibutton> and, if everything went without incident, you
will see the <computeroutput>Trusted domain relationship successfully established</computeroutput> message.
</para>

</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Samba as the Trusting Domain</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>NT-controlled domain</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>PDC</primary></indexterm>
This time activities are somewhat reversed. Again, we'll assume that your domain
controlled by the Samba PDC is called SAMBA and the NT-controlled domain is called RUMBA.
</para>

<para>
The very first step is to add an account for the SAMBA domain on RUMBA's PDC.
</para>


<para>
<indexterm><primary>User Manager</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>trusted domain</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>password</primary></indexterm>
Launch the <application>Domain User Manager</application>, then from the menu select
<guimenu>Policies</guimenu>, <guimenuitem>Trust Relationships</guimenuitem>.
Now, next to the <guilabel>Trusting Domains</guilabel> box, press the <guibutton>Add</guibutton>
button and type in the name of the trusted domain (SAMBA) and the password to use in securing
the relationship.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>password</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>confirm the password</primary></indexterm>
The password can be arbitrarily chosen. It is easy to change the password from the Samba server whenever you
want. After you confirm the password, your account is ready for use. Now its Samba's turn.
</para>

<para>
Using your favorite shell while logged in as root, issue this command:
<indexterm><primary>net</primary><secondary>rpc</secondary><tertiary>trustdom establish</tertiary></indexterm>
</para>

<para>
&rootprompt;<userinput>net rpc trustdom establish rumba</userinput>
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>password</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>interdomain connection</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ordinary connection</primary></indexterm>
You will be prompted for the password you just typed on your Windows NT4 Server box.
An error message, <literal>"NT_STATUS_NOLOGON_INTERDOMAIN_TRUST_ACCOUNT,"</literal>
that may be reported periodically is of no concern and may safely be ignored.
It means the password you gave is correct and the NT4 server says the account is ready for
interdomain connection and not for ordinary connection.  After that, be patient;
it can take a while (especially in large networks), but eventually you should see
the <literal>Success</literal> message. Congratulations! Your trust
relationship has just been established.
</para>

<note><para>
You have to run this command as root because you must have write access to
the <filename>secrets.tdb</filename> file.
</para></note>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>NT4-Style Domain Trusts with Windows 2000</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>trust relationship</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Windows 2000 server</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>NT4-style</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>mixed mode</primary></indexterm>
Although <application>Domain User Manager</application> is not present in Windows 2000, it is 
also possible to establish an NT4-style trust relationship with a Windows 2000 domain 
controller running in mixed mode as the trusting server. It should also be possible for 
Samba to trust a Windows 2000 server; however, more testing is still needed in this area.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>interdomain trust</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>trust account</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>not transitive</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ADS</primary></indexterm>
After <link linkend="samba-trusted-domain">creating the interdomain trust account on the Samba server</link>
as described previously, open <application>Active Directory Domains and Trusts</application> on the AD
controller of the domain whose resources you wish Samba users to have access to. Remember that since NT4-style
trusts are not transitive, if you want your users to have access to multiple mixed-mode domains in your AD
forest, you will need to repeat this process for each of those domains. With <application>Active Directory
domains and trusts</application> open, right-click on the name of the Active Directory domain that will trust
our Samba domain and choose <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem>, then click on the
<guilabel>Trusts</guilabel> tab. In the upper part of the panel, you will see a list box labeled
<guilabel>Domains trusted by this domain:</guilabel> and an <guilabel>Add...</guilabel> button next to it.
Press this button and, just as with NT4, you will be prompted for the trusted domain name and the relationship
password. Press <emphasis>OK</emphasis> and after a moment, Active Directory will respond with
<computeroutput>The trusted domain has been added and the trust has been verified.</computeroutput> Your
Samba users can now be granted access to resources in the AD domain.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Common Errors</title>

<para>
Interdomain trust relationships should not be attempted on networks that are unstable
or that suffer regular outages. Network stability and integrity are key concerns with
distributed trusted domains.
</para>

<sect2>
<title>Browsing of Trusted Domain Fails</title>

<para>
<emphasis>Browsing from a machine in a trusted Windows 200x domain to a Windows 200x member of
a trusting Samba domain, I get the following error:</emphasis>
<screen>
The system detected a possible attempt to compromise security. Please
ensure that you can contact the server that authenticated you.
</screen>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>The event logs on the box I'm trying to connect to have entries regarding group
policy not being applied because it is a member of a down-level domain.</emphasis>
</para>

<para>If there is a computer account in the Windows
200x domain for the machine in question, and it is disabled, this problem can
occur.  If there is no computer account (removed or never existed), or if that 
account is still intact (i.e., you just joined it to another domain), everything 
seems to be fine. By default, when you unjoin a domain (the Windows 200x 
domain), the computer tries to automatically disable the computer account in 
the domain.  If you are running as an account that has privileges to do this 
when you unjoin the machine, it is done; otherwise it is not done.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Problems with LDAP ldapsam and Older Versions of smbldap-tools</title>

<para>
If you use the <command>smbldap-useradd</command> script to create a trust
account to set up interdomain trusts, the process of setting up the trust will
fail. The account that was created in the LDAP database will have an account
flags field that has <literal>[W          ]</literal>, when it must have
<literal>[I          ]</literal> for interdomain trusts to work.
</para>

<para>Here is a simple solution.
Create a machine account as follows:
<screen>
&rootprompt; smbldap-useradd -w domain_name
</screen>
Then set the desired trust account password as shown here:
<screen>
&rootprompt; smbldap-passwd domain_name\$
</screen>
Using a text editor, create the following file:
<screen>
dn: uid=domain_name$,ou=People,dc={your-domain},dc={your-top-level-domain}
changetype: modify
sambaAcctFlags: [I         ]
</screen>
Then apply the text file to the LDAP database as follows:
<screen>
&rootprompt; ldapmodify -x -h localhost \
 -D "cn=Manager,dc={your-domain},dc={your-top-level-domain}" \
 -W -f /path-to/foobar
</screen>
Create a single-sided trust under the NT4 Domain User Manager, then execute:
<screen>
&rootprompt; net rpc trustdom establish domain_name
</screen>
</para>

<para>
It works with Samba-3  and NT4 domains, and also with Samba-3 and Windows 200x ADS in mixed mode.
Both domain controllers, Samba and NT must have the same WINS server; otherwise,
the trust will never work. 
</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

</chapter>
