<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Samba-Team//DTD DocBook V4.2-Based Variant V1.0//EN" "http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<chapter id="FastStart">
<chapterinfo>
	&author.jht;
</chapterinfo>

<title>Fast Start: Cure for Impatience</title>

<para>
When we first asked for suggestions for inclusion in the Samba HOWTO documentation,
someone wrote asking for example configurations &smbmdash; and lots of them. That is remarkably
difficult to do without losing a lot of value that can be derived from presenting
many extracts from working systems. That is what the rest of this document does.
It does so with extensive descriptions of the configuration possibilities within the
context of the chapter that covers it. We hope that this chapter is the medicine 
that has been requested.
</para>

<para>
The information in this chapter is very sparse compared with the book <quote>Samba-3 by Example</quote>
that was written after the original version of this book was nearly complete. <quote>Samba-3 by Example</quote>
was the result of feedback from reviewers during the final copy editing of the first edition. It
was interesting to see that reader feedback mirrored that given by the original reviewers.
In any case, a month and a half was spent in doing basic research to better understand what
new as well as experienced network administrators would best benefit from. The book <quote>Samba-3 by Example</quote>
is the result of that research. What is presented in the few pages of this book is covered
far more comprehensively in the second edition of <quote>Samba-3 by Example</quote>. The second edition
of both books will be released at the same time.
</para>

<para>
So in summary, the book <quote>The Official Samba-3 HOWTO &amp; Reference Guide</quote> is intended
as the equivalent of an auto mechanic's repair guide. The book <quote>Samba-3 by Example</quote> is the
equivalent of the driver's guide that explains how to drive the car. If you want complete network
configuration examples, go to <ulink url="http://www.samba.org/samba/docs/Samba3-ByExample.pdf">Samba-3 by
Example</ulink>.
</para>

<sect1>
<title>Features and Benefits</title>

<para>
Samba needs very little configuration to create a basic working system.
In this chapter we progress from the simple to the complex, for each providing
all steps and configuration file changes needed to make each work. Please note
that a comprehensively configured system will likely employ additional smart
features. These additional features are covered in the remainder of this document.
</para>

<para>
The examples used here have been obtained from a number of people who made
requests for example configurations. All identities have been obscured to protect
the guilty, and any resemblance to unreal nonexistent sites is deliberate.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Description of Example Sites</title>

<para>
In the first set of configuration examples we consider the case of exceptionally simple system requirements.
There is a real temptation to make something that should require little effort much too complex.
</para>

<para>
<link linkend="anon-ro"></link> documents the type of server that might be sufficient to serve CD-ROM images,
or reference document files for network client use. This configuration is also discussed in <link
linkend="StandAloneServer"></link>, <link linkend="RefDocServer"></link>.  The purpose for this configuration
is to provide a shared volume that is read-only that anyone, even guests, can access.
</para>

<para>
The second example shows a minimal configuration for a print server that anyone can print to as long as they
have the correct printer drivers installed on their computer. This is a mirror of the system described in
<link linkend="StandAloneServer"></link>, <link linkend="SimplePrintServer"></link>.
</para>

<para>
The next example is of a secure office file and print server that will be accessible only to users who have an
account on the system. This server is meant to closely resemble a workgroup file and print server, but has to
be more secure than an anonymous access machine.  This type of system will typically suit the needs of a small
office. The server provides no network logon facilities, offers no domain control; instead it is just a
network-attached storage (NAS) device and a print server.
</para>

<para>
The later example consider more complex systems that will either integrate into existing MS Windows networks
or replace them entirely. These cover domain member servers as well as Samba domain control (PDC/BDC) and
finally describes in detail a large distributed network with branch offices in remote locations.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Worked Examples</title>

<para>
The configuration examples are designed to cover everything necessary to get Samba 
running. They do not cover basic operating system platform configuration, which is
clearly beyond the scope of this text.
</para>

<para>
It is also assumed that Samba has been correctly installed, either by way of installation
of the packages that are provided by the operating system vendor or through other means.
</para>

	<sect2>
	<title>Standalone Server</title>

	<para>
	<indexterm><primary>Server Type</primary><secondary>Stand-alone</secondary></indexterm>
	A standalone server implies no more than the fact that it is not a domain controller
	and it does not participate in domain control. It can be a simple, workgroup-like
	server, or it can be a complex server that is a member of a domain security context.
	</para>

	<para>
	As the examples are developed, every attempt is made to progress the system toward greater capability, just as
	one might expect would happen in a real business office as that office grows in size and its needs change.
	</para>

		<sect3 id="anon-ro">
		<title>Anonymous Read-Only Document Server</title>

		<para>
		<indexterm><primary>read only</primary><secondary>server</secondary></indexterm>
		The purpose of this type of server is to make available to any user
		any documents or files that are placed on the shared resource. The
		shared resource could be a CD-ROM drive, a CD-ROM image, or a file
		storage area.
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>
			The file system share point will be <filename>/export</filename>.
			</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>
			All files will be owned by a user called Jack Baumbach.
			Jack's login name will be <emphasis>jackb</emphasis>. His password will be
			<emphasis>m0r3pa1n</emphasis> &smbmdash; of course, that's just the example we are
			using; do not use this in a production environment because
			all readers of this document will know it.
			</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<procedure>
		<title>Installation Procedure: Read-Only Server</title>
			<step><para>
			Add user to system (with creation of the user's home directory):
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>useradd -c "Jack Baumbach" -m -g users -p m0r3pa1n jackb</userinput>
</screen>
			</para></step>

			<step><para>
			Create directory, and set permissions and ownership:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>mkdir /export</userinput>
&rootprompt;<userinput>chmod u+rwx,g+rx,o+rx /export</userinput>
&rootprompt;<userinput>chown jackb.users /export</userinput>
</screen>
			</para></step>

			<step><para>
			Copy the files that should be shared to the <filename>/export</filename>
			directory.
			</para></step>

			<step><para>
			Install the Samba configuration file (<filename>/etc/samba/smb.conf</filename>)
			as shown in <link linkend="anon-example">Anonymous Read-Only Server Configuration</link>.
			</para></step>

<example id="anon-example">
<title>Anonymous Read-Only Server Configuration</title>
<smbconfblock>
<smbconfcomment>Global parameters</smbconfcomment>
<smbconfsection name="[global]"/>
<smbconfoption name="workgroup">MIDEARTH</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="netbios name">HOBBIT</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="security">share</smbconfoption>

<smbconfsection name="[data]"/>
<smbconfoption name="comment">Data</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="path">/export</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="read only">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="guest ok">Yes</smbconfoption>
</smbconfblock>
</example>

			<step><para>
			Test the configuration file by executing the following command:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>testparm</userinput>
</screen>
			Alternatively, where you are operating from a master configuration file called
			<filename>smb.conf.master</filename>, the following sequence of commands might prove
			more appropriate:
<screen>
&rootprompt; cd /etc/samba
&rootprompt; testparm -s smb.conf.master > smb.conf
&rootprompt; testparm
</screen>
			Note any error messages that might be produced. Proceed only if error-free output has been
			obtained. An example of typical output that should be generated from the above configuration
			file is shown here:
<screen>
Load smb config files from /etc/samba/smb.conf
Processing section "[data]"
Loaded services file OK.
Server role: ROLE_STANDALONE
Press enter to see a dump of your service definitions
<userinput>[Press enter]</userinput>

# Global parameters
[global]
	workgroup = MIDEARTH
	netbios name = HOBBIT
	security = share

[data]
	comment = Data
	path = /export
	read only = Yes
	guest only = Yes
</screen>
			</para></step>

			<step><para>
			Start Samba using the method applicable to your operating system platform. The method that
			should be used is platform dependent. Refer to <link linkend="startingSamba">Starting Samba</link>
			for further information regarding the starting of Samba.
			</para></step>

			<step><para>
			Configure your MS Windows client for workgroup <emphasis>MIDEARTH</emphasis>,
			set the machine name to ROBBINS, reboot, wait a few (2 - 5) minutes,
			then open Windows Explorer and visit the Network Neighborhood.
			The machine HOBBIT should be visible. When you click this machine
			icon, it should open up to reveal the <emphasis>data</emphasis> share. After
			you click the share, it should open up to reveal the files previously
			placed in the <filename>/export</filename> directory.
			</para></step>
		</procedure>

		<para>
		The information above (following # Global parameters) provides the complete
		contents of the <filename>/etc/samba/smb.conf</filename> file.
		</para>

		</sect3>

		<sect3>
		<title>Anonymous Read-Write Document Server</title>

		<para>
		<indexterm><primary>anonymous</primary><secondary>read-write server</secondary></indexterm>
		We should view this configuration as a progression from the previous example.
		The difference is that shared access is now forced to the user identity of jackb
		and to the primary group jackb belongs to. One other refinement we can make is to
		add the user <emphasis>jackb</emphasis> to the <filename>smbpasswd</filename> file.
		To do this, execute:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>smbpasswd -a jackb</userinput>
New SMB password: <userinput>m0r3pa1n</userinput>
Retype new SMB password: <userinput>m0r3pa1n</userinput>
Added user jackb.
</screen>
		Addition of this user to the <filename>smbpasswd</filename> file allows all files
		to be displayed in the Explorer Properties boxes as belonging to <emphasis>jackb</emphasis>
		instead of to <emphasis>User Unknown</emphasis>.
		</para>

		<para>
		The complete, modified &smb.conf; file is as shown in <link linkend="anon-rw"/>.
		</para>

<example id="anon-rw">
<title>Modified Anonymous Read-Write smb.conf</title>
<smbconfblock>
<smbconfcomment>Global parameters</smbconfcomment>
<smbconfsection name="[global]"/>
<smbconfoption name="workgroup">MIDEARTH</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="netbios name">HOBBIT</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="security">SHARE</smbconfoption>

<smbconfsection name="[data]"/>
<smbconfoption name="comment">Data</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="path">/export</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="force user">jackb</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="force group">users</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="read only">No</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="guest ok">Yes</smbconfoption>
</smbconfblock>
</example>

		</sect3>

		<sect3>
		<title>Anonymous Print Server</title>

		<para>
		<indexterm><primary>anonymous</primary><secondary>print server</secondary></indexterm>
		An anonymous print server serves two purposes:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>
			It allows printing to all printers from a single location.
			</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>
			It reduces network traffic congestion due to many users trying
			to access a limited number of printers.
			</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		In the simplest of anonymous print servers, it is common to require the installation
		of the correct printer drivers on the Windows workstation. In this case the print
		server will be designed to just pass print jobs through to the spooler, and the spooler
		should be configured to do raw pass-through to the printer. In other words, the print
		spooler should not filter or process the data stream being passed to the printer.
		</para>

		<para>
		In this configuration, it is undesirable to present the Add Printer Wizard, and we do
		not want to have automatic driver download, so we disable it in the following
		configuration. <link linkend="anon-print"></link> is the resulting &smb.conf; file.
		</para>

<example id="anon-print">
<title>Anonymous Print Server smb.conf</title>
<smbconfblock>
<smbconfcomment>Global parameters</smbconfcomment>
<smbconfsection name="[global]"/>
<smbconfoption name="workgroup">MIDEARTH</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="netbios name">LUTHIEN</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="security">share</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printcap name">cups</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="disable spoolss">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="show add printer wizard">No</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printing">cups</smbconfoption>

<smbconfsection name="[printers]"/>
<smbconfoption name="comment">All Printers</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="path">/var/spool/samba</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="guest ok">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printable">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="use client driver">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="browseable">No</smbconfoption>
</smbconfblock>
</example>

		<para>
		The above configuration is not ideal. It uses no smart features, and it deliberately
		presents a less than elegant solution. But it is basic, and it does print. Samba makes
		use of the direct printing application program interface that is provided by CUPS.
		When Samba has been compiled and linked with the CUPS libraries, the default printing
		system will be CUPS. By specifying that the printcap name is CUPS, Samba will use
		the CUPS library API to communicate directly with CUPS for all printer functions.
		It is possible to force the use of external printing commands by setting the value
		of the <parameter>printing</parameter> to either SYSV or BSD, and thus the value of
		the parameter <parameter>printcap name</parameter> must be set to something other than
		CUPS. In such case, it could be set to the name of any file that contains a list
		of printers that should be made available to Windows clients.
		</para>

		<note><para>
		Windows users will need to install a local printer and then change the print
		to device after installation of the drivers. The print to device can then be set to
		the network printer on this machine.
		</para></note>

		<para>
		Make sure that the directory <filename>/var/spool/samba</filename> is capable of being used
		as intended. The following steps must be taken to achieve this:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>
			The directory must be owned by the superuser (root) user and group:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>chown root.root /var/spool/samba</userinput>
</screen>
			</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>
			Directory permissions should be set for public read-write with the
			sticky bit set as shown:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>chmod a+twrx /var/spool/samba</userinput>
</screen>
		The purpose of setting the sticky bit is to prevent who does not own the temporary print file
		from being able to take control of it with the potential for devious misuse.
			</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>


		<note><para>
		<indexterm><primary>MIME</primary><secondary>raw</secondary></indexterm>
		<indexterm><primary>raw printing</primary></indexterm>
		On CUPS-enabled systems there is a facility to pass raw data directly to the printer without
		intermediate processing via CUPS print filters. Where use of this mode of operation is desired,
		it is necessary to configure a raw printing device. It is also necessary to enable the raw mime
		handler in the <filename>/etc/mime.conv</filename> and <filename>/etc/mime.types</filename>
		files. Refer to <link linkend="cups-raw"></link>.
		</para></note>

		</sect3>

		<sect3>

		<title>Secure Read-Write File and Print Server</title>

		<para>
		We progress now from simple systems to a server that is slightly more complex.
		</para>

		<para>
		Our new server will require a public data storage area in which only authenticated
		users (i.e., those with a local account) can store files, as well as a home directory.
		There will be one printer that should be available for everyone to use.
		</para>

		<para>
		In this hypothetical environment (no espionage was conducted to obtain this data),
		the site is demanding a simple environment that is <emphasis>secure enough</emphasis>
		but not too difficult to use. 
		</para>

		<para>
		Site users will be Jack Baumbach, Mary Orville, and Amed Sehkah. Each will have
		a password (not shown in further examples). Mary will be the printer administrator and will
		own all files in the public share.
		</para>

		<para>
		This configuration will be based on <emphasis>user-level security</emphasis> that
		is the default, and for which the default is to store Microsoft Windows-compatible
		encrypted passwords in a file called <filename>/etc/samba/smbpasswd</filename>.
		The default &smb.conf; entry that makes this happen is
		<smbconfoption name="passdb backend">smbpasswd, guest</smbconfoption>. Since this is the default,
		it is not necessary to enter it into the configuration file. Note that the guest backend is
		added to the list of active passdb backends no matter whether it specified directly in Samba configuration
		file or not.
		</para>


		<procedure>
		<title>Installing the Secure Office Server</title>
			<step><para>
		<indexterm><primary>office server</primary></indexterm>
			Add all users to the operating system:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>useradd -c "Jack Baumbach" -m -g users -p m0r3pa1n jackb</userinput>
&rootprompt;<userinput>useradd -c "Mary Orville" -m -g users -p secret maryo</userinput>
&rootprompt;<userinput>useradd -c "Amed Sehkah" -m -g users -p secret ameds</userinput>
</screen>
			</para></step>

			<step><para>
			Configure the Samba &smb.conf; file as shown in <link linkend="OfficeServer"/>.
			</para></step>

<example id="OfficeServer">
<title>Secure Office Server smb.conf</title>
<smbconfblock>
<smbconfcomment>Global parameters</smbconfcomment>
<smbconfsection name="[global]"/>
<smbconfoption name="workgroup">MIDEARTH</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="netbios name">OLORIN</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printcap name">cups</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="disable spoolss">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="show add printer wizard">No</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printing">cups</smbconfoption>

<smbconfsection name="[homes]"/>
<smbconfoption name="comment">Home Directories</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="valid users">%S</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="read only">No</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="browseable">No</smbconfoption>

<smbconfsection name="[public]"/>
<smbconfoption name="comment">Data</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="path">/export</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="force user">maryo</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="force group">users</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="read only">No</smbconfoption>

<smbconfsection name="[printers]"/>
<smbconfoption name="comment">All Printers</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="path">/var/spool/samba</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printer admin">root, maryo</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="create mask">0600</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="guest ok">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printable">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="use client driver">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="browseable">No</smbconfoption>
</smbconfblock>
</example>

			<step><para>
			Initialize the Microsoft Windows password database with the new users:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>smbpasswd -a root</userinput>
New SMB password: <userinput>bigsecret</userinput>
Reenter smb password: <userinput>bigsecret</userinput>
Added user root.

&rootprompt;<userinput>smbpasswd -a jackb</userinput>
New SMB password: <userinput>m0r3pa1n</userinput>
Retype new SMB password: <userinput>m0r3pa1n</userinput>
Added user jackb.

&rootprompt;<userinput>smbpasswd -a maryo</userinput>
New SMB password: <userinput>secret</userinput>
Reenter smb password: <userinput>secret</userinput>
Added user maryo.

&rootprompt;<userinput>smbpasswd -a ameds</userinput>
New SMB password: <userinput>mysecret</userinput>
Reenter smb password: <userinput>mysecret</userinput>
Added user ameds.
</screen>
			</para></step>

			<step><para>
			Install printer using the CUPS Web interface. Make certain that all
			printers that will be shared with Microsoft Windows clients are installed
			as raw printing devices.
			</para></step>

			<step><para>
			Start Samba using the operating system administrative interface.
			Alternately, this can be done manually by executing:
			<indexterm><primary>smbd</primary></indexterm>
			<indexterm><primary>nmbd</primary></indexterm>
			<indexterm><primary>starting samba</primary><secondary>smbd</secondary></indexterm>
			<indexterm><primary>starting samba</primary><secondary>nmbd</secondary></indexterm>
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput> nmbd; smbd;</userinput>
</screen>
			Both applications automatically execute as daemons. Those who are paranoid about
			maintaining control can add the <constant>-D</constant> flag to coerce them to start
			up in daemon mode.
			</para></step>

			<step><para>
			Configure the <filename>/export</filename> directory:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>mkdir /export</userinput>
&rootprompt;<userinput>chown maryo.users /export</userinput>
&rootprompt;<userinput>chmod u=rwx,g=rwx,o-rwx /export</userinput>
</screen>
			</para></step>

			<step><para>
			Check that Samba is running correctly:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>smbclient -L localhost -U%</userinput>
Domain=[MIDEARTH] OS=[UNIX] Server=[Samba-3.0.20]

Sharename      Type      Comment
---------      ----      -------
public         Disk      Data
IPC$           IPC       IPC Service (Samba-3.0.20)
ADMIN$         IPC       IPC Service (Samba-3.0.20)
hplj4          Printer   hplj4

Server               Comment
---------            -------
OLORIN               Samba-3.0.20

Workgroup            Master
---------            -------
MIDEARTH             OLORIN
</screen>
			The following error message indicates that Samba was not running:
<screen>
&rootprompt; smbclient -L olorin -U%
Error connecting to 192.168.1.40 (Connection refused)
Connection to olorin failed
</screen>
			</para></step>

			<step><para>
			Connect to OLORIN as maryo:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>smbclient //olorin/maryo -Umaryo%secret</userinput>
OS=[UNIX] Server=[Samba-3.0.20]
smb: \> <userinput>dir</userinput>
.                              D        0  Sat Jun 21 10:58:16 2003
..                             D        0  Sat Jun 21 10:54:32 2003
Documents                      D        0  Fri Apr 25 13:23:58 2003
DOCWORK                        D        0  Sat Jun 14 15:40:34 2003
OpenOffice.org                 D        0  Fri Apr 25 13:55:16 2003
.bashrc                        H     1286  Fri Apr 25 13:23:58 2003
.netscape6                    DH        0  Fri Apr 25 13:55:13 2003
.mozilla                      DH        0  Wed Mar  5 11:50:50 2003
.kermrc                        H      164  Fri Apr 25 13:23:58 2003
.acrobat                      DH        0  Fri Apr 25 15:41:02 2003

		55817 blocks of size 524288. 34725 blocks available
smb: \> <userinput>q</userinput>
</screen>
			</para></step>
		</procedure>

			<para>
			By now you should be getting the hang of configuration basics. Clearly, it is time to
			explore slightly more complex examples. For the remainder of this chapter we abbreviate
			instructions, since there are previous examples.
			</para>

		</sect3>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
	<title>Domain Member Server</title>

	<para>
	<indexterm><primary>Server Type</primary><secondary>Domain Member</secondary></indexterm>
	In this instance we consider the simplest server configuration we can get away with
	to make an accounting department happy. Let's be warned, the users are accountants and they
	do have some nasty demands. There is a budget for only one server for this department.
	</para>

	<para>
	The network is managed by an internal Information Services Group (ISG), to which we belong.
	Internal politics are typical of a medium-sized organization; Human Resources is of the
	opinion that they run the ISG because they are always adding and disabling users. Also,
	departmental managers have to fight tooth and nail to gain basic network resources access for
	their staff. Accounting is different, though, they get exactly what they want. So this should
	set the scene.
	</para>

	<para>
	We use the users from the last example. The accounting department
	has a general printer that all departmental users may use. There is also a check printer
	that may be used only by the person who has authority to print checks. The chief financial
	officer (CFO) wants that printer to be completely restricted and for it to be located in the
	private storage area in her office. It therefore must be a network printer.
	</para>

	<para>
	The accounting department uses an accounting application called <emphasis>SpytFull</emphasis>
	that must be run from a central application server. The software is licensed to run only off
	one server, there are no workstation components, and it is run off a mapped share. The data
	store is in a UNIX-based SQL backend. The UNIX gurus look after that, so this is not our
	problem.
	</para>

	<para>
	The accounting department manager (maryo) wants a general filing system as well as a separate
	file storage area for form letters (nastygrams). The form letter area should be read-only to
	all accounting staff except the manager. The general filing system has to have a structured
	layout with a general area for all staff to store general documents as well as a separate
	file area for each member of her team that is private to that person, but she wants full
	access to all areas. Users must have a private home share for personal work-related files
	and for materials not related to departmental operations.
	</para>
	
		<sect3>
		<title>Example Configuration</title>
		
		<para>
		The server <emphasis>valinor</emphasis> will be a member server of the company domain.
		Accounting will have only a local server. User accounts will be on the domain controllers,
		as will desktop profiles and all network policy files.
		</para>

		<procedure>
			<step><para>
			Do not add users to the UNIX/Linux server; all of this will run off the
			central domain.
			</para></step>

			<step><para>
			Configure &smb.conf; according to <link linkend="fast-member-server">Member server smb.conf
			(globals)</link> and <link linkend="fast-memberserver-shares">Member server smb.conf (shares
			and services)</link>.
			</para></step>

<example id="fast-member-server">
<title>Member Server smb.conf (Globals)</title>
<smbconfblock>
<smbconfcomment>Global parameters</smbconfcomment>
<smbconfsection name="[global]"/>
<smbconfoption name="workgroup">MIDEARTH</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="netbios name">VALINOR</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="security">DOMAIN</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printcap name">cups</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="disable spoolss">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="show add printer wizard">No</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="idmap uid">15000-20000</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="idmap gid">15000-20000</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="winbind use default domain">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printing">cups</smbconfoption>
</smbconfblock>
</example>

<example id="fast-memberserver-shares">
<title>Member Server smb.conf (Shares and Services)</title>
<smbconfblock>
<smbconfsection name="[homes]"/>
<smbconfoption name="comment">Home Directories</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="valid users">%S</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="read only">No</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="browseable">No</smbconfoption>

<smbconfsection name="[spytfull]"/>
<smbconfoption name="comment">Accounting Application Only</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="path">/export/spytfull</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="valid users">@Accounts</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="admin users">maryo</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="read only">Yes</smbconfoption>

<smbconfsection name="[public]"/>
<smbconfoption name="comment">Data</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="path">/export/public</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="read only">No</smbconfoption>

<smbconfsection name="[printers]"/>
<smbconfoption name="comment">All Printers</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="path">/var/spool/samba</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printer admin">root, maryo</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="create mask">0600</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="guest ok">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printable">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="use client driver">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="browseable">No</smbconfoption>
</smbconfblock>
</example>

			<step><para>
			<indexterm><primary>net</primary><secondary>rpc</secondary></indexterm>
			Join the domain. Note: Do not start Samba until this step has been completed!
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>net rpc join -Uroot%'bigsecret'</userinput>
Joined domain MIDEARTH.
</screen>
			</para></step>

			<step><para>
			Make absolutely certain that you disable (shut down) the <command>nscd</command>
			daemon on any system on which <command>winbind</command> is configured to run.
			</para></step>

			<step><para>
			Start Samba following the normal method for your operating system platform.
			If you wish to do this manually, execute as root:
			<indexterm><primary>smbd</primary></indexterm>
			<indexterm><primary>nmbd</primary></indexterm>
			<indexterm><primary>winbindd</primary></indexterm>
			<indexterm><primary>starting samba</primary><secondary>smbd</secondary></indexterm>
			<indexterm><primary>starting samba</primary><secondary>nmbd</secondary></indexterm>
			<indexterm><primary>starting samba</primary><secondary>winbindd</secondary></indexterm>
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>nmbd; smbd; winbindd;</userinput>
</screen>
			</para></step>

			<step><para>
			Configure the name service switch (NSS) control file on your system to resolve user and group names
			via winbind. Edit the following lines in <filename>/etc/nsswitch.conf</filename>:
<programlisting>
passwd: files winbind
group:  files winbind
hosts:  files dns winbind
</programlisting>
			</para></step>

			<step><para>
			Set the password for <command>wbinfo</command> to use:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>wbinfo --set-auth-user=root%'bigsecret'</userinput>
</screen>
			</para></step>

			<step><para>
			Validate that domain user and group credentials can be correctly resolved by executing:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>wbinfo -u</userinput>
MIDEARTH\maryo
MIDEARTH\jackb
MIDEARTH\ameds
...
MIDEARTH\root

&rootprompt;<userinput>wbinfo -g</userinput>
MIDEARTH\Domain Users
MIDEARTH\Domain Admins
MIDEARTH\Domain Guests
...
MIDEARTH\Accounts
</screen>
			</para></step>

			<step><para>
			Check that <command>winbind</command> is working. The following demonstrates correct
			username resolution via the <command>getent</command> system utility:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>getent passwd maryo</userinput>
maryo:x:15000:15003:Mary Orville:/home/MIDEARTH/maryo:/bin/false
</screen>
			</para></step>

			<step><para>
			A final test that we have this under control might be reassuring:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>touch /export/a_file</userinput>
&rootprompt;<userinput>chown maryo /export/a_file</userinput>
&rootprompt;<userinput>ls -al /export/a_file</userinput>
...
-rw-r--r--    1 maryo    users       11234 Jun 21 15:32 a_file
...

&rootprompt;<userinput>rm /export/a_file</userinput>
</screen>
			</para></step>

			<step><para>
			Configuration is now mostly complete, so this is an opportune time
			to configure the directory structure for this site:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>mkdir -p /export/{spytfull,public}</userinput>
&rootprompt;<userinput>chmod ug=rwxS,o=x /export/{spytfull,public}</userinput>
&rootprompt;<userinput>chown maryo.Accounts /export/{spytfull,public}</userinput>
</screen>
			</para></step>
		</procedure>

		</sect3>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
	<title>Domain Controller</title>


	<para>
	<indexterm><primary>Server Type</primary><secondary>Domain Controller</secondary></indexterm>
	For the remainder of this chapter the focus is on the configuration of domain control.
	The examples that follow are for two implementation strategies. Remember, our objective is
	to create a simple but working solution. The remainder of this book should help to highlight
	opportunity for greater functionality and the complexity that goes with it.
	</para>

	<para>
	A domain controller configuration can be achieved with a simple configuration using the new
	tdbsam password backend. This type of configuration is good for small
	offices, but has limited scalability (cannot be replicated), and performance can be expected
	to fall as the size and complexity of the domain increases.
	</para>

	<para>
	The use of tdbsam is best limited to sites that do not need
	more than a Primary Domain Controller (PDC). As the size of a domain grows the need
	for additional domain controllers becomes apparent. Do not attempt to under-resource
	a Microsoft Windows network environment; domain controllers provide essential
	authentication services. The following are symptoms of an under-resourced domain control
	environment:
	</para>

	<itemizedlist>	
		<listitem><para>
		 Domain logons intermittently fail.
		</para></listitem>

		<listitem><para>
		File access on a domain member server intermittently fails, giving a permission denied
		error message.
		</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>
	A more scalable domain control authentication backend option might use
	Microsoft Active Directory or an LDAP-based backend. Samba-3 provides
	for both options as a domain member server. As a PDC, Samba-3 is not able to provide
	an exact alternative to the functionality that is available with Active Directory.
	Samba-3 can provide a scalable LDAP-based PDC/BDC solution.
	</para>

	<para>
	The tdbsam authentication backend provides no facility to replicate
	the contents of the database, except by external means (i.e., there is no self-contained protocol
	in Samba-3 for Security Account Manager database [SAM] replication).
	</para>

	<note><para>
	If you need more than one domain controller, do not use a tdbsam authentication backend.
	</para></note>

		<sect3>
		<title>Example: Engineering Office</title>

		<para>
		The engineering office network server we present here is designed to demonstrate use
		of the new tdbsam password backend. The tdbsam
		facility is new to Samba-3. It is designed to provide many user and machine account controls
		that are possible with Microsoft Windows NT4. It is safe to use this in smaller networks.
		</para>

		<procedure>
			<step><para>
			A working PDC configuration using the tdbsam
			password backend can be found in <link linkend="fast-engoffice-global">Engineering Office smb.conf
			(globals)</link> together with <link linkend="fast-engoffice-shares">Engineering Office smb.conf
			(shares and services)</link>:
			<indexterm><primary>pdbedit</primary></indexterm>
			</para></step>

<example id="fast-engoffice-global">
<title>Engineering Office smb.conf (globals)</title>
<smbconfblock>
<smbconfsection name="[global]"/>
<smbconfoption name="workgroup">MIDEARTH</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="netbios name">FRODO</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="passdb backend">tdbsam</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printcap name">cups</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="add user script">/usr/sbin/useradd -m %u</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="delete user script">/usr/sbin/userdel -r %u</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="add group script">/usr/sbin/groupadd %g</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="delete group script">/usr/sbin/groupdel %g</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="add user to group script">/usr/sbin/groupmod -A %u %g</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="delete user from group script">/usr/sbin/groupmod -R %u %g</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="add machine script">/usr/sbin/useradd -s /bin/false -d /var/lib/nobody %u</smbconfoption>
<smbconfcomment>Note: The following specifies the default logon script.</smbconfcomment>
<smbconfcomment>Per user logon scripts can be specified in the user account using pdbedit </smbconfcomment>
<smbconfoption name="logon script">scripts\logon.bat</smbconfoption>
<smbconfcomment>This sets the default profile path. Set per user paths with pdbedit</smbconfcomment>
<smbconfoption name="logon path">\\%L\Profiles\%U</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="logon drive">H:</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="logon home">\\%L\%U</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="domain logons">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="os level">35</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="preferred master">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="domain master">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="idmap uid">15000-20000</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="idmap gid">15000-20000</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printing">cups</smbconfoption>
</smbconfblock>
</example>

<example id="fast-engoffice-shares">
<title>Engineering Office smb.conf (shares and services)</title>
<smbconfblock>
<smbconfsection name="[homes]"/>
<smbconfoption name="comment">Home Directories</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="valid users">%S</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="read only">No</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="browseable">No</smbconfoption>

<smbconfcomment>Printing auto-share (makes printers available thru CUPS)</smbconfcomment>
<smbconfsection name="[printers]"/>
<smbconfoption name="comment">All Printers</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="path">/var/spool/samba</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printer admin">root, maryo</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="create mask">0600</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="guest ok">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printable">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="browseable">No</smbconfoption>

<smbconfsection name="[print$]"/>
<smbconfoption name="comment">Printer Drivers Share</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="path">/var/lib/samba/drivers</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="write list">maryo, root</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printer admin">maryo, root</smbconfoption>

<smbconfcomment>Needed to support domain logons</smbconfcomment>
<smbconfsection name="[netlogon]"/>
<smbconfoption name="comment">Network Logon Service</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="path">/var/lib/samba/netlogon</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="admin users">root, maryo</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="guest ok">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="browseable">No</smbconfoption>

<smbconfcomment>For profiles to work, create a user directory under the path</smbconfcomment>
<smbconfcomment> shown. i.e., mkdir -p /var/lib/samba/profiles/maryo</smbconfcomment>
<smbconfsection name="[Profiles]"/>
<smbconfoption name="comment">Roaming Profile Share</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="path">/var/lib/samba/profiles</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="read only">No</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="profile acls">Yes</smbconfoption>

<smbconfcomment>Other resource (share/printer) definitions would follow below.</smbconfcomment>
</smbconfblock>
</example>

			<step><para>
			Create UNIX group accounts as needed using a suitable operating system tool:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>groupadd ntadmins</userinput>
&rootprompt;<userinput>groupadd designers</userinput>
&rootprompt;<userinput>groupadd engineers</userinput>
&rootprompt;<userinput>groupadd qateam</userinput>
</screen>
			</para></step>

			<step><para>
			Create user accounts on the system using the appropriate tool
			provided with the operating system. Make sure all user home directories
			are created also. Add users to groups as required for access control
			on files, directories, printers, and as required for use in the Samba
			environment.
			</para></step>


			<step><para>
			<indexterm><primary>net</primary><secondary>groupmap</secondary></indexterm>
			<indexterm><primary>initGroups.sh</primary></indexterm>
			Assign each of the UNIX groups to NT groups by executing this shell script
			(You could name the script <filename>initGroups.sh</filename>):
<screen>
#!/bin/bash
#### Keep this as a shell script for future re-use
			
# First assign well known groups
net groupmap add ntgroup="Domain Admins" unixgroup=ntadmins rid=512 type=d
net groupmap add ntgroup="Domain Users"  unixgroup=users rid=513 type=
net groupmap add ntgroup="Domain Guests" unixgroup=nobody rid=514 type=d

# Now for our added Domain Groups
net groupmap add ntgroup="Designers" unixgroup=designers type=d
net groupmap add ntgroup="Engineers" unixgroup=engineers type=d
net groupmap add ntgroup="QA Team"   unixgroup=qateam    type=d
</screen>
			</para></step>

			<step><para>
			Create the <filename>scripts</filename> directory for use in the 
			<smbconfsection name="[NETLOGON]"/> share:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>mkdir -p /var/lib/samba/netlogon/scripts</userinput>
</screen>
			Place the logon scripts that will be used (batch or cmd scripts)
			in this directory.
			</para></step>
		</procedure>

		<para>
		The above configuration provides a functional PDC
		system to which must be added file shares and printers as required.
		</para>

		</sect3>

		<sect3>
		<title>A Big Organization</title>

		<para>
		In this section we finally get to review in brief a Samba-3 configuration that
		uses a Lightweight Directory Access (LDAP)-based authentication backend. The
		main reasons for this choice are to provide the ability to host primary
		and Backup Domain Control (BDC), as well as to enable a higher degree of
		scalability to meet the needs of a very distributed environment.
		</para>

			<sect4>
			<title>The Primary Domain Controller</title>

			<para>
			This is an example of a minimal configuration to run a Samba-3 PDC
			using an LDAP authentication backend. It is assumed that the operating system
			has been correctly configured.
			</para>

			<para>
			The Idealx scripts (or equivalent) are needed to manage LDAP-based POSIX and/or
			SambaSamAccounts. The Idealx scripts may be downloaded from the <ulink url="http://www.idealx.org">
			Idealx</ulink> Web site. They may also be obtained from the Samba tarball. Linux
			distributions tend to install the Idealx scripts in the 
			<filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/sambaXXXXXX/examples/LDAP/smbldap-tools</filename> directory.
			Idealx scripts version <constant>smbldap-tools-0.9.1</constant> are known to work well.
			</para>

			<procedure>
				<step><para>
				Obtain from the Samba sources <filename>~/examples/LDAP/samba.schema</filename>
				and copy it to the <filename>/etc/openldap/schema/</filename> directory.
				</para></step>

				<step><para>
				Set up the LDAP server. This example is suitable for OpenLDAP 2.1.x.
				The <filename>/etc/openldap/slapd.conf</filename> file.
				<indexterm><primary>/etc/openldap/slapd.conf</primary></indexterm>
<title>Example slapd.conf File</title>
<screen>
# Note commented out lines have been removed
include         /etc/openldap/schema/core.schema
include         /etc/openldap/schema/cosine.schema
include         /etc/openldap/schema/inetorgperson.schema
include         /etc/openldap/schema/nis.schema
include         /etc/openldap/schema/samba.schema

pidfile         /var/run/slapd/slapd.pid
argsfile        /var/run/slapd/slapd.args

database        bdb
suffix          "dc=quenya,dc=org"
rootdn          "cn=Manager,dc=quenya,dc=org"
rootpw          {SSHA}06qDkonA8hk6W6SSnRzWj0/pBcU3m0/P
# The password for the above is 'nastyon3'

directory     /var/lib/ldap

index   objectClass     eq
index cn                      pres,sub,eq
index sn                      pres,sub,eq
index uid                     pres,sub,eq
index displayName             pres,sub,eq
index uidNumber               eq
index gidNumber               eq
index memberUid               eq
index   sambaSID              eq
index   sambaPrimaryGroupSID  eq
index   sambaDomainName       eq
index   default               sub
</screen>
				</para></step>

				<step><para>
				Create the following file <filename>initdb.ldif</filename>:
				<indexterm><primary>initdb.ldif</primary></indexterm>
<programlisting>
# Organization for SambaXP Demo
dn: dc=quenya,dc=org
objectclass: dcObject
objectclass: organization
dc: quenya
o: SambaXP Demo
description: The SambaXP Demo LDAP Tree

# Organizational Role for Directory Management
dn: cn=Manager,dc=quenya,dc=org
objectclass: organizationalRole
cn: Manager
description: Directory Manager

# Setting up the container for users
dn: ou=People, dc=quenya, dc=org
objectclass: top
objectclass: organizationalUnit
ou: People

# Set up an admin handle for People OU
dn: cn=admin, ou=People, dc=quenya, dc=org
cn: admin
objectclass: top
objectclass: organizationalRole
objectclass: simpleSecurityObject
userPassword: {SSHA}0jBHgQ1vp4EDX2rEMMfIudvRMJoGwjVb
# The password for above is 'mordonL8'
</programlisting>
				</para></step>

				<step><para>
				Load the initial data above into the LDAP database:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>slapadd -v -l initdb.ldif</userinput>
</screen>
				</para></step>

				<step><para>
				Start the LDAP server using the appropriate tool or method for
				the operating system platform on which it is installed.
				</para></step>

				<step><para>
				Install the Idealx script files in the <filename>/usr/local/sbin</filename> directory,
				then configure the smbldap_conf.pm file to match your system configuration.
				</para></step>

				<step><para>
				The &smb.conf; file that drives this backend can be found in example <link
				linkend="fast-ldap">LDAP backend smb.conf for PDC</link>. Add additional stanzas
				as required.
				</para></step>

<example id="fast-ldap">
<title>LDAP backend smb.conf for PDC</title>
<smbconfblock>
<smbconfcomment>Global parameters</smbconfcomment>
<smbconfsection name="[global]"/>
<smbconfoption name="workgroup">MIDEARTH</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="netbios name">FRODO</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="passdb backend">ldapsam:ldap://localhost</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="username map">/etc/samba/smbusers</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printcap name">cups</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="add user script">/usr/local/sbin/smbldap-useradd -m '%u'</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="delete user script">/usr/local/sbin/smbldap-userdel %u</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="add group script">/usr/local/sbin/smbldap-groupadd -p '%g'</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="delete group script">/usr/local/sbin/smbldap-groupdel '%g'</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="add user to group script">/usr/local/sbin/smbldap-groupmod -m '%u' '%g'</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="delete user from group script">/usr/local/sbin/smbldap-groupmod -x '%u' '%g'</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="set primary group script">/usr/local/sbin/smbldap-usermod -g '%g' '%u'</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="add machine script">/usr/local/sbin/smbldap-useradd -w '%u'</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="logon script">scripts\logon.bat</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="logon path">\\%L\Profiles\%U</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="logon drive">H:</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="logon home">\\%L\%U</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="domain logons">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="os level">35</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="preferred master">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="domain master">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="ldap suffix">dc=quenya,dc=org</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="ldap machine suffix">ou=People</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="ldap user suffix">ou=People</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="ldap group suffix">ou=People</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="ldap idmap suffix">ou=People</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="ldap admin dn">cn=Manager</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="ldap ssl">no</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="ldap passwd sync">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="idmap uid">15000-20000</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="idmap gid">15000-20000</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printing">cups</smbconfoption>
</smbconfblock>
</example>

				<step><para>
				Add the LDAP password to the <filename>secrets.tdb</filename> file so Samba can update
				the LDAP database:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>smbpasswd -w mordonL8</userinput>
</screen>
				</para></step>

				<step><para>
				Add users and groups as required. Users and groups added using Samba tools
				will automatically be added to both the LDAP backend and the operating
				system as required.
				</para></step>

			</procedure>

			</sect4>

			<sect4>
			<title>Backup Domain Controller</title>

			<para>
			<link linkend="fast-bdc"/> shows the example configuration for the BDC. Note that
			the &smb.conf; file does not specify the smbldap-tools scripts &smbmdash; they are
			not needed on a BDC. Add additional stanzas for shares and printers as required.
			</para>

			<procedure>
				<step><para>
				Decide if the BDC should have its own LDAP server or not. If the BDC is to be
				the LDAP server, change the following &smb.conf; as indicated. The default
				configuration in <link linkend="fast-bdc">Remote LDAP BDC smb.conf</link>
				uses a central LDAP server.
				</para></step>

<example id="fast-bdc">
<title>Remote LDAP BDC smb.conf</title>
<smbconfblock>
<smbconfcomment>Global parameters</smbconfcomment>
<smbconfsection name="[global]"/>
<smbconfoption name="workgroup">MIDEARTH</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="netbios name">GANDALF</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="passdb backend">ldapsam:ldap://frodo.quenya.org</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="username map">/etc/samba/smbusers</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printcap name">cups</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="logon script">scripts\logon.bat</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="logon path">\\%L\Profiles\%U</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="logon drive">H:</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="logon home">\\%L\%U</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="domain logons">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="os level">33</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="preferred master">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="domain master">No</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="ldap suffix">dc=quenya,dc=org</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="ldap machine suffix">ou=People</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="ldap user suffix">ou=People</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="ldap group suffix">ou=People</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="ldap idmap suffix">ou=People</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="ldap admin dn">cn=Manager</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="ldap ssl">no</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="ldap passwd sync">Yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="idmap uid">15000-20000</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="idmap gid">15000-20000</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printing">cups</smbconfoption>
</smbconfblock>
</example>

				<step><para>
				Configure the NETLOGON and PROFILES directory as for the PDC in <link linkend="fast-bdc"/>.
				</para></step>
			</procedure>

			</sect4>

		</sect3>

	</sect2>

</sect1>

</chapter>
