<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//Samba-Team//DTD DocBook V4.2-Based Variant V1.0//EN" "http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<refentry id="libsmbclient.7">

<refmeta>
	<refentrytitle>libsmbclient</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
	<refmiscinfo class="source">Samba</refmiscinfo>
	<refmiscinfo class="manual">7</refmiscinfo>
	<refmiscinfo class="version">3.0</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>


<refnamediv>
	<refname>libsmbclient</refname>
	<refpurpose>An extension library for browsers and that can be used as a generic browsing API.</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
	<cmdsynopsis>
	<para>
	Browser URL:
	<command moreinfo="none">smb://[[[domain:]user[:password@]]server[/share[/path[/file]]]] [?options]
	</command>
	</para>
	</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>


<refsect1>
	<title>DESCRIPTION</title>

	<para>
	This tool is part of the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>samba</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>7</manvolnum></citerefentry> suite.
	</para>

	<para>
	<command>libsmbclient</command> is a library toolset that permits applications to manipulate CIFS/SMB network
	resources using many of the standards POSIX functions available for manipulating local UNIX/Linux files. It
	permits much more than just browsing, files can be opened and read or written, permissions changed, file times
	modified, attributes and ACL's can be manipulated, and so on. Of course, its functionality includes all the
	capabilities commonly called browsing.
	</para>

	<para>
	<command>libsmbclient</command> can not be used directly from the command line, instead it provides an
	extension of the capabilities of tools such as file managers and browsers.  This man page describes the
	configuration options for this tool so that the user may obtain greatest utility of use.
	</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>OPTIONS</title>

	<para>
	What the URLs mean:
	</para>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>smb://</term>
			<listitem><para>
			Shows all workgroups or domains that are visible in the network. The behavior matches
			that of the Microsoft Windows Explorer.
			</para>

			<para>
			The method of locating the list of workgroups (domains also) varies depending on the setting of
			the context variable <literal>(context-&gt;options.browse_max_lmb_count)</literal>. It is the
			responsibility of the application that calls this library to set this to a sensible value.  This
			is a compile-time option. This value determines the maximum number of local master browsers to
			query for the list of workgroups.  In order to ensure that the list is complete for those present
			on the network, all master browsers must be querried. If there are a large number of workgroups
			on the network, the time spent querying will be significant. For small networks (just a few
			workgroups), it is suggested to set this value to 0, instructing libsmbclient to query all local
			master browsers. In an environment that has many workgroups a more reasonable setting may be around 3.
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>smb://name/</term>
			<listitem><para>
			This command causes libsmbclient to perform a name look-up. If the NAME&lt;1D&gt; or
			NAME&lt;1B&gt; exists (workgroup name), libsmbclient will list all servers in the
			workgroup (or domain). Otherwise, a name look-up for the NAME&lt;20&gt; (machine name)
			will be performed, and the list of shared resources on the server will be displayed.
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<para>
	When libsmbclient is invoked by an application it searches for a directory called
	<filename>.smb</filename> in the $HOME directory that is specified in the users shell
	environment. It then searches for a file called <filename>smb.conf</filename> which,
	if present, will fully over-ride the system <filename>/etc/samba/smb.conf</filename> file. If
	instead libsmbclient finds a file called <filename>~/.smb/smb.conf.append</filename>,
	it will read the system <filename>/etc/samba/smb.conf</filename> and then append the
	contents of the <filename>~/.smb/smb.conf.append</filename> to it.
	</para>

	<para>
	<command>libsmbclient</command> will check the users shell environment for the <literal>USER</literal>
	parameter and will use its value when if the <literal>user</literal> parameter was not included
	in the URL.
	</para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>PROGRAMMERS GUIDE</title>

	<para>
	Watch this space for future updates.
	</para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>VERSION</title>

	<para>
	This man page is correct for version 3.0 of the Samba suite.
	</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>AUTHOR</title>

	<para>
	The original Samba software and related utilities were created by Andrew Tridgell.
	Samba is now developed by the Samba Team as an Open Source project similar to the way
	the Linux kernel is developed.
	</para> 

	<para>
	The libsmbclient manpage page was written by John H Terpstra.
	</para>
</refsect1>

</refentry>
