<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//Samba-Team//DTD DocBook V4.2-Based Variant V1.0//EN" "http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<refentry id="smbcacls.1">

<refmeta>
	<refentrytitle>smbcacls</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
	<refmiscinfo class="source">Samba</refmiscinfo>
	<refmiscinfo class="manual">User Commands</refmiscinfo>
	<refmiscinfo class="version">3.0</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>


<refnamediv>
	<refname>smbcacls</refname>
	<refpurpose>Set or get ACLs on an NT file or directory names</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
	<cmdsynopsis>
		<command>smbcacls</command>
		<arg choice="req">//server/share</arg>
		<arg choice="req">filename</arg>
		<arg choice="opt">-D acls</arg>
		<arg choice="opt">-M acls</arg>
		<arg choice="opt">-a acls</arg>
		<arg choice="opt">-S acls</arg>
		<arg choice="opt">-C name</arg>
		<arg choice="opt">-G name</arg>
		<arg choice="opt">--numeric</arg>
		<arg choice="opt">-t</arg>
		<arg choice="opt">-U username</arg>
		<arg choice="opt">-h</arg>
		<arg choice="opt">-d</arg>
	</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsect1>
	<title>DESCRIPTION</title>

	<para>This tool is part of the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>samba</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>7</manvolnum></citerefentry> suite.</para>

	<para>The <command>smbcacls</command> program manipulates NT Access Control
	Lists (ACLs) on SMB file shares. </para>
</refsect1>


<refsect1>
	<title>OPTIONS</title>

	<para>The following options are available to the <command>smbcacls</command> program.  
	The format of ACLs is described in the section ACL FORMAT </para>


	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
		<term>-a acls</term>
		<listitem><para>Add the ACLs specified to the ACL list.  Existing 
		access control entries are unchanged. </para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		
		
		
		<varlistentry>
		<term>-M acls</term>
		<listitem><para>Modify the mask value (permissions) for the ACLs 
		specified on the command line.  An error will be printed for each 
		ACL specified that was not already present in the ACL list
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		
		
		
		<varlistentry>
		<term>-D acls</term>
		<listitem><para>Delete any ACLs specified on the command line.  
		An error will be printed for each ACL specified that was not 
		already present in the ACL list. </para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		
		
		
		<varlistentry>
		<term>-S acls</term>
		<listitem><para>This command sets the ACLs on the file with 
		only the ones specified on the command line.  All other ACLs are 
		erased. Note that the ACL specified must contain at least a revision,
		type, owner and group for the call to succeed. </para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		
		
		
		<varlistentry>
		<term>-U username</term>
		<listitem><para>Specifies a username used to connect to the 
		specified service.  The username may be of the form "username" in 
		which case the user is prompted to enter in a password and the 
		workgroup specified in the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>smb.conf</refentrytitle>
		<manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry> file is 
		used, or "username%password"  or "DOMAIN\username%password" and the 
		password and workgroup names are used as provided. </para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		
		
		
		<varlistentry>
		<term>-C name</term>
		<listitem><para>The owner of a file or directory can be changed 
		to the name given using the <parameter>-C</parameter> option.  
		The name can be a sid in the form S-1-x-y-z or a name resolved 
		against the server specified in the first argument. </para>
		
		<para>This command is a shortcut for -M OWNER:name. 
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		
		
		
		<varlistentry>
		<term>-G name</term>
		<listitem><para>The group owner of a file or directory can 
		be changed to the name given using the <parameter>-G</parameter> 
		option.  The name can be a sid in the form S-1-x-y-z or a name 
		resolved against the server specified n the first argument.
		</para>
		
		<para>This command is a shortcut for -M GROUP:name.</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		
		
		
		<varlistentry>
		<term>--numeric</term>
		<listitem><para>This option displays all ACL information in numeric 
		format.  The default is to convert SIDs to names and ACE types 
		and masks to a readable string format.  </para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		
		<varlistentry>
		<term>-t</term>
		<listitem><para>
		Don't actually do anything, only validate the correctness of 
		the arguments.
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
				
		&stdarg.help;
		&stdarg.server.debug;
		&popt.common.samba;
	</variablelist>
</refsect1>


<refsect1>
	<title>ACL FORMAT</title>

	<para>The format of an ACL is one or more ACL entries separated by 
	either commas or newlines.  An ACL entry is one of the following: </para>

<para><programlisting> 
REVISION:&lt;revision number&gt;
OWNER:&lt;sid or name&gt;
GROUP:&lt;sid or name&gt;
ACL:&lt;sid or name&gt;:&lt;type&gt;/&lt;flags&gt;/&lt;mask&gt;
</programlisting></para>
  

	<para>The revision of the ACL specifies the internal Windows 
	NT ACL revision for the security descriptor.  
	If not specified it defaults to 1.  Using values other than 1 may 
	cause strange behaviour. </para>

	<para>The owner and group specify the owner and group sids for the 
	object.  If a SID in the format S-1-x-y-z is specified this is used, 
	otherwise the name specified is resolved using the server on which 
	the file or directory resides. </para>

	<para>ACLs specify permissions granted to the SID.  This SID again 
	can be specified in S-1-x-y-z format or as a name in which case 
	it is resolved against the server on which the file or directory 
	resides.  The type, flags and mask values determine the type of 
	access granted to the SID. </para>

	<para>The type can be either 0 or 1 corresponding to ALLOWED or 
	DENIED access to the SID.  The flags values are generally
	zero for file ACLs and either 9 or 2 for directory ACLs.  Some 
	common flags are: </para>

	<itemizedlist> 
		<listitem><para><constant>#define SEC_ACE_FLAG_OBJECT_INHERIT     	0x1</constant></para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><constant>#define SEC_ACE_FLAG_CONTAINER_INHERIT  	0x2</constant></para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><constant>#define SEC_ACE_FLAG_NO_PROPAGATE_INHERIT     0x4</constant></para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><constant>#define SEC_ACE_FLAG_INHERIT_ONLY       	0x8</constant></para></listitem>
 	</itemizedlist>
  
	<para>At present flags can only be specified as decimal or 
	hexadecimal values.</para>
 
	<para>The mask is a value which expresses the access right 
	granted to the SID. It can be given as a decimal or hexadecimal value, 
	or by using one of the following text strings which map to the NT 
	file permissions of the same name. </para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>R</emphasis> - Allow read access </para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>W</emphasis> - Allow write access</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>X</emphasis> - Execute permission on the object</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>D</emphasis> - Delete the object</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>P</emphasis> - Change permissions</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>O</emphasis> - Take ownership</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>


	<para>The following combined permissions can be specified:</para>


	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>READ</emphasis> -  Equivalent to 'RX'
		permissions</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>CHANGE</emphasis> - Equivalent to 'RXWD' permissions
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>FULL</emphasis> - Equivalent to 'RWXDPO' 
		permissions</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>EXIT STATUS</title>

	<para>The <command>smbcacls</command> program sets the exit status 
	depending on the success or otherwise of the operations performed.  
	The exit status may be one of the following values. </para>

	<para>If the operation succeeded, smbcacls returns and exit 
	status of 0.  If <command>smbcacls</command> couldn't connect to the specified server, 
	or there was an error getting or setting the ACLs, an exit status 
	of 1 is returned.  If there was an error parsing any command line 
	arguments, an exit status of 2 is returned. </para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>VERSION</title>

	<para>This man page is correct for version 3.0 of the Samba suite.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>AUTHOR</title>
	
	<para>The original Samba software and related utilities 
	were created by Andrew Tridgell. Samba is now developed
	by the Samba Team as an Open Source project similar 
	to the way the Linux kernel is developed.</para>
	
	<para><command>smbcacls</command> was written by Andrew Tridgell 
	and Tim Potter.</para>
	
	<para>The conversion to DocBook for Samba 2.2 was done 
	by Gerald Carter. The conversion to DocBook XML 4.2 for Samba 3.0 was done
	by Alexander Bokovoy.</para>
</refsect1>

</refentry>
