<samba:parameter name="domain master"
				 type="boolean"
                 context="G"
                 basic="1" advanced="1" developer="1"
                 xmlns:samba="http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<description>
	<para>
	Tell <citerefentry><refentrytitle>smbd</refentrytitle> <manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry> to enable
	WAN-wide browse list collation. Setting this option causes <command moreinfo="none">nmbd</command> to claim a
	special domain specific NetBIOS name that identifies it as a domain master browser for its given
	<smbconfoption name="workgroup"/>. Local master browsers in the same <smbconfoption name="workgroup"/> on
	broadcast-isolated subnets will give this <command moreinfo="none">nmbd</command> their local browse lists,
	and then ask <citerefentry><refentrytitle>smbd</refentrytitle> <manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry> for a
	complete copy of the browse list for the whole wide area network.  Browser clients will then contact their
	local master browser, and will receive the domain-wide browse list, instead of just the list for their
	broadcast-isolated subnet.
	</para>

	<para>
	Note that Windows NT Primary Domain Controllers expect to be able to claim this <smbconfoption
	name="workgroup"/> specific special NetBIOS name that identifies them as domain master browsers for that
	<smbconfoption name="workgroup"/> by default (i.e. there is no way to prevent a Windows NT PDC from attempting
	to do this). This means that if this parameter is set and <command moreinfo="none">nmbd</command> claims the
	special name for a <smbconfoption name="workgroup"/> before a Windows NT PDC is able to do so then cross
	subnet browsing will behave strangely and may fail.
	</para>
		
	<para>
	If <smbconfoption name="domain logons">yes</smbconfoption>, then the default behavior is to enable the
	<smbconfoption name="domain master"/> parameter.  If <smbconfoption name="domain logons"/> is not enabled (the
	default setting), then neither will <smbconfoption name="domain master"/> be enabled by default.
	</para>

	<para>
	When <smbconfoption name="domain logons">Yes</smbconfoption> the default setting for this parameter is
	Yes, with the result that Samba will be a PDC. If <smbconfoption name="domain master">No</smbconfoption>,
	Samba will function as a BDC. In general, this parameter should be set to 'No' only on a BDC.
	</para>

</description>
<value type="default">auto</value>
</samba:parameter>
