<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//Samba-Team//DTD DocBook V4.2-Based Variant V1.0//EN" "http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<refentry id="idmap_tdb2.8">

<refmeta>
	<refentrytitle>idmap_tdb2</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
	<refmiscinfo class="source">Samba</refmiscinfo>
	<refmiscinfo class="manual">System Administration tools</refmiscinfo>
	<refmiscinfo class="version">3.6</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>


<refnamediv>
	<refname>idmap_tdb2</refname>
	<refpurpose>Samba's idmap_tdb2 Backend for Winbind</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
	<title>DESCRIPTION</title>

	<para>
	The idmap_tdb2 plugin is a substitute for the default idmap_tdb
	backend used by winbindd for storing SID/uid/gid mapping tables
	in clustered environments with Samba and CTDB.
	</para>

	<para>
	In contrast to read only backends like idmap_rid, it is an allocating
	backend: This means that it needs to allocate new user and group IDs in
	order to create new mappings.
	</para>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsect1>
	<title>IDMAP OPTIONS</title>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
		<term>range = low - high</term>
		<listitem><para>
			Defines the available matching uid and gid range for which the
			backend is authoritative.
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>script</term>
		<listitem><para>
			This option can be used to configure an external program
			for performing id mappings instead of using the tdb
			counter. The mappings are then stored int tdb2 idmap
			database. For details see the section on IDMAP SCRIPT below.
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>IDMAP SCRIPT</title>

	<para>
	The tdb2 idmap backend supports an external program for performing id mappings
	through the smb.conf option <parameter>idmap config * : script</parameter> or
	its deprecated legacy form <parameter>idmap : script</parameter>.
	</para>

	<para>
	The mappings obtained by the script are then stored in the idmap tdb2
	database instead of mappings created by the incrementing id counters.
	It is therefore important that the script covers the complete range of
	SIDs that can be passed in for SID to Unix ID mapping, since otherwise
	SIDs unmapped by the script might get mapped to IDs that had
	previously been mapped by the script.
	</para>

	<para>
	The script should accept the following command line options.
	</para>

	<programlisting>
	SIDTOID S-1-xxxx
	IDTOSID UID xxxx
	IDTOSID GID xxxx
	</programlisting>

	<para>
	And it should return one of the following responses as a single line of
	text.
	</para>

	<programlisting>
	UID:yyyy
	GID:yyyy
	SID:yyyy
	ERR:yyyy
	</programlisting>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>EXAMPLES</title>

	<para>
	This example shows how tdb2 is used as a the default idmap backend.
	</para>

	<programlisting>
	[global]
	idmap config * : backend = tdb2
	idmap config * : range = 1000000-2000000
	</programlisting>

	<para>
	This example shows how tdb2 is used as a the default idmap backend
	using an external program via the script parameter:
	</para>

	<programlisting>
	[global]
	idmap config * : backend = tdb2
	idmap config * : range = 1000000-2000000
	idmap config * : script = /usr/local/samba/bin/idmap_script.sh
	</programlisting>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>AUTHOR</title>

	<para>
	The original Samba software and related utilities
	were created by Andrew Tridgell. Samba is now developed
	by the Samba Team as an Open Source project similar
	to the way the Linux kernel is developed.
	</para>
</refsect1>

</refentry>
