<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Samba-Team//DTD DocBook V4.2-Based Variant V1.0//EN" "http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<chapter id="classicalprinting">

<chapterinfo>
	<author>
		<firstname>Kurt</firstname><surname>Pfeifle</surname>
		<affiliation>
			<orgname>Danka Deutschland GmbH</orgname>
			<address><email>kpfeifle@danka.de</email></address>
		</affiliation>
	</author>
	&author.jerry;
	&author.jht;
	<pubdate>May 31, 2003</pubdate>
</chapterinfo>

<title>Classical Printing Support</title>

<sect1>
<title>Features and Benefits</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>mission-critical</primary></indexterm>
Printing is often a mission-critical service for the users. Samba can provide this service reliably and
seamlessly for a client network consisting of Windows workstations.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>print service</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>domain member server</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>standalone server</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>file serving</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>dedicated print server</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>print server</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>printing support</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Point'n'Print</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Add Printer Wizard</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>upload drivers</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>manage drivers</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>install drivers</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>print accounting</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Common UNIX Printing System</primary><see>CUPS</see></indexterm>
A Samba print service may be run on a standalone or domain member server, side by side with file serving
functions, or on a dedicated print server.  It can be made as tightly or as loosely secured as needs dictate.
Configurations may be simple or complex. Available authentication schemes are essentially the same as
described for file services in previous chapters. Overall, Samba's printing support is now able to replace an
NT or Windows 2000 print server full-square, with additional benefits in many cases. Clients may download and
install drivers and printers through their familiar <literal>Point'n'Print</literal> mechanism. Printer
installations executed by <literal>Logon Scripts</literal> are no problem. Administrators can upload and manage
drivers to be used by clients through the familiar <literal>Add Printer Wizard</literal>. As an additional
benefit, driver and printer management may be run from the command line or through scripts, making it more
efficient in case of large numbers of printers. If a central accounting of print jobs (tracking every single
page and supplying the raw data for all sorts of statistical reports) is required, this function is best
supported by the newer Common UNIX Printing System (CUPS) as the print subsystem underneath the Samba hood.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>BSD</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>CUPS</primary></indexterm>
This chapter outlines the fundamentals of Samba printing as implemented by the more traditional UNIX
BSD- and System V-style printing systems. Much of the information in this chapter applies also to CUPS.  If
you use CUPS, you may be tempted to jump to the next chapter, but you will certainly miss a few things if you
do. For further information refer to <link linkend="CUPS-printing">CUPS Printing Support</link>.
</para>

<note>
<para>
<indexterm><primary>Windows XP Professional</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Windows 200x/XP</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Windows NT4</primary></indexterm>
Most of the following examples have been verified on Windows XP Professional clients. Where this document
describes the responses to commands given, bear in mind that Windows 200x/XP clients are quite similar but may
differ in minor details. Windows NT4 is somewhat different again.
</para>
</note>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Technical Introduction</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>printing support</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>print subsystem</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>printing system</primary></indexterm>
Samba's printing support always relies on the installed print subsystem of the UNIX OS it runs on. Samba is a
<literal>middleman.</literal> It takes print files from Windows (or other SMB) clients and passes them to the real
printing system for further processing; therefore, it needs to communicate with both sides: the Windows print
clients and the UNIX printing system. Hence, we must differentiate between the various client OS types, each
of which behave differently, as well as the various UNIX print subsystems, which themselves have different
features and are accessed differently.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>UNIX printing</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>CUPS</primary></indexterm>
This chapter deals with the traditional way of UNIX printing. The next chapter covers in great detail the more
modern CUPS.
</para>

<important><para>
<indexterm><primary>CUPS</primary></indexterm>
CUPS users, be warned: do not just jump on to the next chapter. You might miss important information only found here!
</para></important>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>print configuration</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>problematic print</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>print processing</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>print filtering</primary></indexterm>
It is apparent from postings on the Samba mailing list that print configuration is one of the most problematic
aspects of Samba administration today. Many new Samba administrators have the impression that Samba performs
some sort of print processing. Rest assured, Samba does not perform any type of print processing. It does not
do any form of print filtering.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>data stream</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>local spool area</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>spooled file</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>local system printing</primary></indexterm>
Samba obtains from its clients a data stream (print job) that it spools to a local spool area. When the entire
print job has been received, Samba invokes a local UNIX/Linux print command and passes the spooled file to it.
It is up to the local system printing subsystems to correctly process the print job and to submit it to the
printer.
</para>

<sect2>
<title>Client to Samba Print Job Processing</title>

<para>
Successful printing from a Windows client via a Samba print server to a UNIX
printer involves six (potentially seven) stages:
</para>

<orderedlist>
	<listitem><para>Windows opens a connection to the printer share.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Samba must authenticate the user.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Windows sends a copy of the print file over the network
	into Samba's spooling area.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Windows closes the connection.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Samba invokes the print command to hand the file over
	to the UNIX print subsystem's spooling area.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>The UNIX print subsystem processes the print job.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>The print file may need to be explicitly deleted
	from the Samba spooling area. This item depends on your print spooler
	configuration settings.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Printing-Related Configuration Parameters</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>global-level</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>service-level</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>printing behavior</primary></indexterm>
There are a number of configuration parameters to control Samba's printing behavior. Please refer to the man
page for &smb.conf; for an overview of these. As with other parameters, there are global-level (tagged with a
<emphasis>G</emphasis> in the listings) and service-level (<emphasis>S</emphasis>) parameters.
</para>

<variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term>Global Parameters</term>
		<listitem><para> These <emphasis>may not</emphasis> go into
		individual share definitions. If they go in by error,
		the <command>testparm</command> utility can discover this
		(if you run it) and tell you so.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term>Service-Level Parameters</term>
		<listitem><para> These may be specified in the
		<smbconfsection name="[global]"/> section of &smb.conf;.
		In this case they define the default behavior of all individual
		or service-level shares (provided they do not have a different
		setting defined for the same parameter, thus overriding the
		global default).
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Simple Print Configuration</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>BSD Printing</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>simple printing</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>enables clients to print</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>print environment</primary></indexterm>
<link linkend="simpleprc">Simple Configuration with BSD Printing</link> shows a simple printing configuration.
If you compare this with your own, you may find additional parameters that have been preconfigured by your OS
vendor. Following is a discussion and explanation of the parameters. This example does not use many
parameters.  However, in many environments these are enough to provide a valid &smb.conf; file that enables
all clients to print.
</para>

<example id="simpleprc">
<title>Simple Configuration with BSD Printing</title>
<smbconfblock>
<smbconfsection name="[global]"/>
<smbconfoption name="printing">bsd</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="load printers">yes</smbconfoption>

<smbconfsection name="[printers]"/>
<smbconfoption name="path">/var/spool/samba</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printable">yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="public">yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="writable">no</smbconfoption>
</smbconfblock>
</example>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>testparm</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>misconfigured settings</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>pager program</primary></indexterm>
This is only an example configuration. Samba assigns default values to all configuration parameters. The
defaults are conservative and sensible. When a parameter is specified in the &smb.conf; file, this overwrites
the default value. The <command>testparm</command> utility when run as root is capable of reporting all
settings, both default as well as &smb.conf; file settings. <command>Testparm</command> gives warnings for all
misconfigured settings. The complete output is easily 360 lines and more, so you may want to pipe it through a
pager program.
</para>

<para>  
<indexterm><primary>configuration syntax</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>syntax tolerates spelling errors</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>case-insensitive</primary></indexterm>
The syntax for the configuration file is easy to grasp. You should know that  is not very picky about its
syntax. As has been explained elsewhere in this book, Samba tolerates some spelling errors (such as
<smbconfoption name="browseable"/> instead of <smbconfoption name="browsable"/>), and spelling is
case-insensitive. It is permissible to use <parameter>Yes/No</parameter> or <parameter>True/False</parameter>
for Boolean settings. Lists of names may be separated by commas, spaces, or tabs.
</para>

<sect2>
<title>Verifying Configuration with <command>testparm</command></title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>printing-related settings</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>lp</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>print</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>spool</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>driver</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ports</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>testparm</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>smbd</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>print configuration</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>printer shares </primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>spooling path</primary></indexterm>
To see all (or at least most) printing-related settings in Samba, including the implicitly used ones, try the
command outlined below. This command greps for all occurrences of <constant>lp</constant>,
<constant>print</constant>, <constant>spool</constant>, <constant>driver</constant>,
<constant>ports</constant>, and <constant>[</constant> in <command>testparm</command>'s output. This provides
a convenient overview of the running <command>smbd</command> print configuration. This command does not show
individually created printer shares or the spooling paths they may use. Here is the output of my Samba setup,
with settings shown in <link linkend="simpleprc">the example above</link>:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>testparm -s -v | egrep "(lp|print|spool|driver|ports|\[)"</userinput>
 Load smb config files from /etc/samba/smb.conf
 Processing section "[homes]"
 Processing section "[printers]"
 
 [global]
        smb ports = 139 445
        lpq cache time = 10
        load printers = Yes
        printcap name = /etc/printcap
        disable spoolss = No
        enumports command =
        addprinter command = 
        deleteprinter command = 
        show add printer wizard = Yes
        os2 driver map =
        printer admin =
        min print space = 0
        max print jobs = 1000
        printable = No
        printing = bsd
        print command = lpr -r -P'%p' %s
        lpq command = lpq -P'%p'
        lprm command = lprm -P'%p' %j
        lppause command =
        lpresume command =
        printer name =
        use client driver = No

 [homes]

 [printers]
        path = /var/spool/samba
        printable = Yes
</screen>
</para>

<para>
You can easily verify which settings were implicitly added by Samba's default behavior. <emphasis>Remember: it
may be important in your future dealings with Samba.</emphasis>
</para>

<note><para>
The <command>testparm</command> in Samba-3 behaves differently from that in 2.2.x: used without the
<quote>-v</quote> switch, it only shows you the settings actually written into! To see the complete
configuration used, add the <quote>-v</quote> parameter to testparm.
</para></note>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Rapid Configuration Validation</title>

<para> 
<indexterm><primary>troubleshoot</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>testparm</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>parameters</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>verify</primary></indexterm>
Should you need to troubleshoot at any stage, please always come back to this point first and verify if
<command>testparm</command> shows the parameters you expect. To give you a warning from personal experience,
try to just comment out the <smbconfoption name="load printers"/> parameter. If your 2.2.x system behaves like
mine, you'll see this:
</para>

<para><screen>
&rootprompt;grep "load printers" /etc/samba/smb.conf
        #  load printers = Yes
        # This setting is commented out!!
 
&rootprompt;testparm -v /etc/samba/smb.conf | egrep "(load printers)"
        load printers = Yes
</screen></para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>commenting out setting</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>publishing printers</primary></indexterm>
I assumed that commenting out of this setting should prevent Samba from
publishing my printers, but it still did. It took some time to figure out
the reason. But I am no longer fooled ... at least not by this.
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>grep -A1 "load printers" /etc/samba/smb.conf</userinput>
        load printers = No
        # The above setting is what I want!
        #  load printers = Yes
        # This setting is commented out!

&rootprompt;<userinput>testparm -s -v smb.conf.simpleprinting | egrep "(load printers)"</userinput>
        load printers = No
</screen></para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>explicitly set</primary></indexterm>
Only when the parameter is explicitly set to <smbconfoption name="load printers">No</smbconfoption> would
Samba conform with my intentions. So, my strong advice is:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Never rely on commented-out parameters.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Always set parameters explicitly as you intend them to
	behave.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Use <command>testparm</command> to uncover hidden
	settings that might not reflect your intentions.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
The following is the most minimal configuration file:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>cat /etc/samba/smb.conf-minimal</userinput>
        [printers]
</screen></para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>testparm</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>smbd</primary></indexterm>
This example should show that you can use <command>testparm</command> to test any Samba configuration file.
Actually, we encourage you <emphasis>not</emphasis> to change your working system (unless you know exactly
what you are doing). Don't rely on the assumption that changes will only take effect after you restart smbd!
This is not the case. Samba rereads it every 60 seconds and on each new client connection. You might have to
face changes for your production clients that you didn't intend to apply. You will now note a few more
interesting things; <command>testparm</command> is useful to identify what the Samba print configuration would
be if you used this minimalistic configuration. Here is what you can expect to find:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>testparm -v smb.conf-minimal | egrep "(print|lpq|spool|driver|ports|[)"</userinput>
 Processing section "[printers]"
 WARNING: [printers] service MUST be printable!
 No path in service printers - using /tmp

        lpq cache time = 10
        load printers = Yes
        printcap name = /etc/printcap
        disable spoolss = No
        enumports command =
        addprinter command =
        deleteprinter command =
        show add printer wizard = Yes
        os2 driver map =
        printer admin =
        min print space = 0
        max print jobs = 1000
        printable = No
        printing = bsd
        print command = lpr -r -P%p %s
        lpq command = lpq -P%p
        printer name =
        use client driver = No

 [printers]
        printable = Yes
</screen></para>

<para>
<command>testparm</command> issued two warnings:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>We did not specify the <smbconfsection name="[printers]"/> section as printable.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>We did not tell Samba which spool directory to use.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>compile-time options</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary></primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary></primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary></primary></indexterm>
However, this was not fatal, and Samba will default to values that will work. Please, do not rely on this and
do not use this example. This was included to encourage you to be careful to design and specify your setup to
do precisely what you require. The outcome on your system may vary for some parameters given, since Samba may
have been built with  different compile-time options. <emphasis>Warning:</emphasis> do not put a comment sign
<emphasis>at the end</emphasis> of a valid line. It will cause the parameter to be ignored (just as if you had
put the comment sign at the front). At first I regarded this as a bug in my Samba versions. But the man page
clearly says: <literal>Internal whitespace in a parameter value is retained verbatim.</literal> This means
that a line consisting of, for example,
<smbconfblock>
<smbconfcomment>This defines LPRng as the printing system</smbconfcomment>
<smbconfoption name="printing"> lprng</smbconfoption>
</smbconfblock>
</para>

<para>
will regard the whole of the string after the <literal>=</literal> sign as the value you want to define. This
is an invalid value that will be ignored, and a default value will be used in its place.
</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Extended Printing Configuration</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>Extended BSD Printing</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>BSD-style printing</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>CUPS</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>testparm</primary></indexterm>
<link linkend="extbsdpr">Extended BSD Printing Configuration</link> shows a more verbose configuration for
print-related settings in a BSD-style printing environment. What follows is a discussion and explanation of
the various parameters. We chose to use BSD-style printing here because it is still the most commonly used
system on legacy UNIX/Linux installations. New installations predominantly use CUPS, which is discussed in a
separate chapter. The example explicitly names many parameters that do not need to be specified because they
are set by default. You could use a much leaner &smb.conf; file, or you can use <command>testparm</command> or
<command>SWAT</command> to optimize the &smb.conf; file to remove all parameters that are set at default.
</para>

<example id="extbsdpr">
<title>Extended BSD Printing Configuration</title>
<smbconfblock>
<smbconfsection name="[global]"/>
<smbconfoption name="printing">bsd</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="load printers">yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="show add printer wizard">yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printcap name">/etc/printcap</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printer admin">@ntadmin, root</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="max print jobs">100</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="lpq cache time">20</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="use client driver">no</smbconfoption>

<smbconfsection name="[printers]"/>
<smbconfoption name="comment">All Printers</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printable">yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="path">/var/spool/samba</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="browseable">no</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="guest ok">yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="public">yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="read only">yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="writable">no       </smbconfoption>

<smbconfsection name="[my_printer_name]"/>
<smbconfoption name="comment">Printer with Restricted Access</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="path">/var/spool/samba_my_printer</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printer admin">kurt</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="browseable">yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="printable">yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="writable">no</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="hosts allow">0.0.0.0</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="hosts deny">turbo_xp, 10.160.50.23, 10.160.51.60</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="guest ok">no</smbconfoption>
</smbconfblock></example>

<para>
<indexterm><primary></primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary></primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary></primary></indexterm>
This is an example configuration. You may not find all the settings that are in the configuration file that
was provided by the OS vendor. Samba configuration parameters, if not explicitly set, default to a sensible
value.  To see all settings, as <constant>root</constant> use the <command>testparm</command> utility.
<command>testparm</command> gives warnings for misconfigured settings.
</para>

<sect2>
<title>Detailed Explanation Settings</title>

<para>
The following is a discussion of the settings from <link linkend="extbsdpr">Extended BSD Printing
Configuration</link>.
</para>

<sect3>
<title>The [global] Section</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>global section</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>special sections</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>individual section</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>share</primary></indexterm>
The <smbconfsection name="[global]"/> section is one of four special sections (along with <smbconfsection
name="[homes]"/>, <smbconfsection name="[printers]"/>, and <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/>). The
<smbconfsection name="[global]"/> contains all parameters that apply to the server as a whole. It is the place
for parameters that have only a global meaning. It may also contain service-level parameters that define
default settings for all other sections and shares. This way you can simplify the configuration and avoid
setting the same value repeatedly. (Within each individual section or share, you may, however, override these
globally set share settings and specify other values).
</para>

<variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="printing">bsd </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
<indexterm><primary>default print commands</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>RFC 1179</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>printing</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>CUPS</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>LPD</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>LPRNG</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>SYSV</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>HPUX</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>AIX</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>QNX</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>PLP</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>queue control</primary></indexterm>
		Causes Samba to use default print commands applicable for the BSD (also known as RFC 1179 style or LPR/LPD)
		printing system. In general, the <parameter>printing</parameter> parameter informs Samba about the print
		subsystem it should expect. Samba supports CUPS, LPD, LPRNG, SYSV, HPUX, AIX, QNX, and PLP. Each of these
		systems defaults to a different <smbconfoption name="print command"/> (and other queue control commands).
		</para>

		<caution><para>
<indexterm><primary>service-level</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>SOFTQ printing system</primary></indexterm>
		The <smbconfoption name="printing"/> parameter is normally a service-level parameter. Since it is included
		here in the <smbconfsection name="[global]"/> section, it will take effect for all printer shares that are not
		defined differently. Samba-3 no longer supports the SOFTQ printing system.
		</para></caution>
	</listitem></varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="load printers">yes </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
<indexterm><primary>printer shares</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>printcap</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>separate shares</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>UNIX printer</primary></indexterm>
		Tells Samba to create automatically all available printer shares. Available printer shares are discovered by
		scanning the printcap file. All created printer shares are also loaded for browsing. If you use this
		parameter, you do not need to specify separate shares for each printer. Each automatically created printer
		share will clone the configuration options found in the <smbconfsection name="[printers]"/> section. (The
		<parameter>load printers = no</parameter> setting will allow you to specify each UNIX printer you want to
		share separately, leaving out some you do not want to be publicly visible and available).
		</para>
	</listitem></varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="show add printer wizard">yes </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
<indexterm><primary>Add Printer Wizard</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Printers</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Network Neighborhood</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>net view</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>uploaded driver</primary></indexterm>
		Setting is normally enabled by default (even if the parameter is not specified in &smb.conf;).  It causes the
		<guiicon>Add Printer Wizard</guiicon> icon to appear in the <guiicon>Printers</guiicon> folder of the Samba
		host's share listing (as shown in <guiicon>Network Neighborhood</guiicon> or by the <command>net
		view</command> command). To disable it, you need to explicitly set it to <constant>no</constant> (commenting
		it out will not suffice). The <parameter>Add Printer Wizard</parameter> lets you upload a printer driver to
		the <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> share and associate it with a printer (if the respective queue exists
		before the action), or exchange a printer's driver for any other previously uploaded driver.
		</para>
	</listitem></varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="max print jobs">100 </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
<indexterm><primary>print jobs</primary></indexterm>
		Sets the upper limit to 100 print jobs being active on the Samba server at any one time. Should a client
		submit a job that exceeds this number, a "no more space available on server" type of error message will be
		returned by Samba to the client. A setting of zero (the default) means there is <emphasis>no</emphasis> limit
		at all.
		</para>
	</listitem></varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="printcap name">/etc/printcap </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
<indexterm><primary>CUPS</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>available printerd</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>printcap</primary></indexterm>
		Tells Samba where to look for a list of available printer names. Where CUPS is used, make sure that a printcap
		file is written. This is controlled by the <constant>Printcap</constant> directive in the
		<filename>cupsd.conf</filename> file.
	</para></listitem></varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="printer admin">@ntadmin </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
<indexterm><primary>add drivers</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>/etc/group</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>printer share</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>set printer properties</primary></indexterm>
		Members of the ntadmin group should be able to add drivers and set printer properties
		(<constant>ntadmin</constant> is only an example name; it needs to be a valid UNIX group name); root is
		implicitly always a <smbconfoption name="printer admin"/>. The <literal>@</literal> sign precedes group names
		in the <filename>/etc/group</filename>. A printer admin can do anything to printers via the remote
		administration interfaces offered by MS-RPC (see <link linkend="cups-msrpc">Printing Developments Since
		Samba-2.2</link>).  In larger installations, the <smbconfoption name="printer admin"/> parameter is normally a
		per-share parameter. This permits different groups to administer each printer share.
	</para></listitem></varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="lpq cache time">20 </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
<indexterm><primary>lpq command</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>lpq cache time</primary></indexterm>
		Controls the cache time for the results of the lpq command. It prevents the lpq command being called too often
		and reduces the load on a heavily used print server.
	</para></listitem></varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="use client driver">no </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
<indexterm><primary>Windows NT/200x/XP</primary></indexterm>
		If set to <constant>yes</constant>, only takes effect for Windows NT/200x/XP clients (and not for Win
		95/98/ME). Its default value is <constant>No</constant> (or <constant>False</constant>).  It must
		<emphasis>not</emphasis> be enabled on print shares (with a <constant>yes</constant> or
		<constant>true</constant> setting) that have valid drivers installed on the Samba server. For more detailed
		explanations, see the &smb.conf; man page.
	</para></listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="ptrsect">
<title>The [printers] Section</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>printers section</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>printcap</primary></indexterm>
The printers section is the second special section. If a section with this name appears in the &smb.conf;,
users are able to connect to any printer specified in the Samba host's printcap file, because Samba on startup
then creates a printer share for every printer name it finds in the printcap file. You could regard this
section as a convenient shortcut to share all printers with minimal configuration. It is also a container for
settings that should apply as default to all printers. (For more details, see the &smb.conf; man page.)
Settings inside this container must be share-level parameters.
</para>

<variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="comment">All printers </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		The <smbconfoption name="comment"/> is shown next to the share if
		a client queries the server, either via <guiicon>Network Neighborhood</guiicon> or with
		the <command>net view</command> command, to list available shares.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="printable">yes </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		The <smbconfsection name="[printers]"/> service <emphasis>must</emphasis>
		be declared as printable. If you specify otherwise, smbd will refuse to load  at
		startup. This parameter allows connected clients to open, write to, and submit spool files
		into the directory specified with the <smbconfoption name="path"/>
		parameter for this service. It is used by Samba to differentiate printer shares from
		file shares. 
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="path">/var/spool/samba </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Must point to a directory used by Samba to spool incoming print files. <emphasis>It
		must not be the same as the spool directory specified in the configuration of your UNIX
		print subsystem!</emphasis> The path typically points to a directory that is world
		writable, with the <emphasis>sticky</emphasis> bit set to it.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="browseable">no </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Is always set to <constant>no</constant> if
		<smbconfoption name="printable">yes</smbconfoption>. It makes
		the <smbconfsection name="[printer]"/> share itself invisible in the list of
		available shares in a <command>net view</command> command or in the Explorer browse
		list. (You will of course see the individual printers.)
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="guest ok">yes </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		If this parameter is set to <constant>yes</constant>, no password is required to
		connect to the printer's service. Access will be granted with the privileges of the
		<smbconfoption name="guest account"/>. On many systems the guest
		account will map to a user named "nobody." This user will usually be found
		in the UNIX passwd file with an empty password, but with no valid UNIX login. On some
		systems the guest account might not have the privilege to be able to print. Test this
		by logging in as your guest user using <command>su - guest</command> and run a system
		print command like:
		</para>
	
		<para>
		<userinput>lpr -P printername /etc/motd</userinput>
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="public">yes </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Is a synonym for <smbconfoption name="guest ok">yes</smbconfoption>.
		Since we have <smbconfoption name="guest ok">yes</smbconfoption>, it
		really does not need to be here. (This leads to the interesting question, <quote>What if I
		by accident have two contradictory settings for the same share?</quote> The answer is that the
		last one encountered by Samba wins. <command>testparm</command> does not complain about different settings
		of the same parameter for the same share. You can test this by setting up multiple
		lines for the <parameter>guest account</parameter> parameter with different usernames,
		and then run testparm to see which one is actually used by Samba.)
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="read only">yes </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Normally (for other types of shares) prevents users from creating or modifying files
		in the service's directory. However, in a <emphasis>printable</emphasis> service, it is
		<emphasis>always</emphasis> allowed to write to the directory (if user privileges allow the
		connection), but only via print spooling operations. Normal write operations are not permitted.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="writable">no </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Is a synonym for <smbconfoption name="read only">yes</smbconfoption>.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Any [my_printer_name] Section</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>loading printer drivers</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>name conflict</primary></indexterm>
If a <parameter>[my_printer_name]</parameter> section appears in the &smb.conf; file, which includes the
parameter <smbconfoption name="printable">yes</smbconfoption> Samba will configure it as a printer share.
Windows 9x/Me clients may have problems with connecting or loading printer drivers if the share name has more
than eight characters. Do not name a printer share with a name that may conflict with an existing user or file
share name. On client connection requests, Samba always tries to find file shares with that name first. If it
finds one, it will connect to this and will not connect to a printer with the same name!
</para>

<?latex \newpage ?>
<variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="comment">Printer with Restricted Access </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		The comment says it all.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="path">/var/spool/samba_my_printer </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Sets the spooling area for this printer to a directory other than the default. It is not
		necessary to set it differently, but the option is available.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="printer admin">kurt </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		The printer admin definition is different for this explicitly defined printer share from the general
		<smbconfsection name="[printers]"/> share. It is not a requirement; we did it to show that it is possible.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="browseable">yes </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		This makes the printer browseable so the clients may conveniently find it when browsing the
		<guiicon>Network Neighborhood</guiicon>.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="printable">yes </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		See <link linkend="ptrsect">Section 20.4.1.2</link>.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="writable">no </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		See <link linkend="ptrsect">Section 20.4.1.2</link>.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="hosts allow">10.160.50.,10.160.51. </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Here we exercise a certain degree of access control by using the <smbconfoption name="hosts allow"/>
		and <smbconfoption name="hosts deny"/> parameters. This is not by any means a safe bet. It is not a
		way to secure your printers. This line accepts all clients from a certain subnet in a first evaluation of
		access control.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="hosts deny">turbo_xp,10.160.50.23,10.160.51.60 </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		All listed hosts are not allowed here (even if they belong to the allowed subnets). As
		you can see, you could name IP addresses as well as NetBIOS hostnames here.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="guest ok">no </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		This printer is not open for the guest account.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Print Commands</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>print command</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>print subsystem</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>temporary location</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>shell scripts</primary></indexterm>
In each section defining a printer (or in the <smbconfsection name="[printers]"/> section),
a <parameter>print command</parameter> parameter may be defined. It sets a command to process the files
that have been placed into the Samba print spool directory for that printer. (That spool directory was,
if you remember, set up with the <smbconfoption name="path"/> parameter). Typically,
this command will submit the spool file to the Samba host's print subsystem, using the suitable system
print command. But there is no requirement that this needs to be the case. For debugging or
some other reason, you may want to do something completely different than print the file. An example is a
command that just copies the print file to a temporary location for further investigation when you need
to debug printing. If you craft your own print commands (or even develop print command shell scripts),
make sure you pay attention to the need to remove the files from the Samba spool directory. Otherwise,
your hard disk may soon suffer from shortage of free space.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Default UNIX System Printing Commands</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>default print command</primary></indexterm>
You learned earlier that Samba, in most cases, uses its built-in settings for many parameters if it cannot
find an explicitly stated one in its configuration file. The same is true for the <smbconfoption name="print
command"/>. The default print command varies depending on the <smbconfoption name="printing"/> parameter
setting. In the commands listed in <link linkend="printOptions">Default Printing Settings</link> , you will
notice some parameters of the form <emphasis>%X</emphasis> where <emphasis>X</emphasis> is <emphasis>p, s,
J</emphasis>, and so on. These letters stand for printer name, spool file, and job ID, respectively.  They are
explained in more detail in <link linkend="printOptions">Default Printing Settings</link> presents an overview
of key printing options but excludes the special case of CUPS, is discussed in <link
linkend="CUPS-printing">CUPS Printing Support</link>.
</para>

<table frame='all' id="printOptions">
	<title>Default Printing Settings</title>
	<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
		<colspec align="left"/>
		<colspec align="left"/>
	<thead>
		<row>
		<entry>Setting</entry>
		<entry>Default Printing Commands</entry>
		</row>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
		<row>
		<entry><smbconfoption name="printing">bsd|aix|lprng|plp</smbconfoption></entry>
		<entry>print command is <command>lpr -r -P%p %s</command></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry><smbconfoption name="printing">sysv|hpux</smbconfoption></entry>
		<entry>print command is <command>lp -c -P%p %s; rm %s</command></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry> <smbconfoption name="printing">qnx</smbconfoption></entry>
		<entry>print command is <command>lp -r -P%p -s %s</command></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry><smbconfoption name="printing">bsd|aix|lprng|plp</smbconfoption></entry>
		<entry>lpq command is <command>lpq -P%p</command></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry><smbconfoption name="printing">sysv|hpux</smbconfoption></entry>
		<entry>lpq command is <command>lpstat -o%p</command></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry><smbconfoption name="printing">qnx</smbconfoption></entry>
		<entry>lpq command is <command>lpq -P%p</command></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry><smbconfoption name="printing">bsd|aix|lprng|plp</smbconfoption></entry>
		<entry>lprm command is <command>lprm -P%p %j</command></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry><smbconfoption name="printing">sysv|hpux</smbconfoption></entry>
		<entry>lprm command is <command>cancel %p-%j</command></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry><smbconfoption name="printing">qnx</smbconfoption></entry>
		<entry>lprm command is <command>cancel %p-%j</command></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry><smbconfoption name="printing">bsd|aix|lprng|plp</smbconfoption></entry>
		<entry>lppause command is <command>lp -i %p-%j -H hold</command></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry><smbconfoption name="printing">sysv|hpux</smbconfoption></entry>
		<entry>lppause command   (...is empty)</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry><smbconfoption name="printing">qnx</smbconfoption></entry>
		<entry>lppause command   (...is empty)</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry><smbconfoption name="printing">bsd|aix|lprng|plp</smbconfoption></entry>
		<entry>lpresume command is <command>lp -i %p-%j -H resume</command></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry><smbconfoption name="printing">sysv|hpux</smbconfoption></entry>
		<entry>lpresume command   (...is empty)</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry><smbconfoption name="printing">qnx</smbconfoption></entry>
		<entry>lpresume command   (...is empty)</entry>
		</row>
	</tbody>
	</tgroup>
</table>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>CUPS API</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>cupsd.conf</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>autogenerated printcap</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>libcups</primary></indexterm>
For <parameter>printing = CUPS</parameter>, if Samba is compiled against libcups, it uses the CUPS API to
submit jobs. (It is a good idea also to set <smbconfoption name="printcap">cups</smbconfoption> in case your
<filename>cupsd.conf</filename> is set to write its autogenerated printcap file to an unusual place).
Otherwise, Samba maps to the System V printing commands with the -oraw option for printing; that is, it uses
<command>lp -c -d%p -oraw; rm %s</command>. With <parameter>printing = cups</parameter>, and if Samba is
compiled against libcups, any manually set print command will be ignored!
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Custom Print Commands</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>print job</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>spooling</primary></indexterm>
After a print job has finished spooling to a service, the <smbconfoption name="print command"/> will be used
by Samba via a system() call to process the spool file. Usually the command specified will submit the spool
file to the host's printing subsystem. But there is no requirement at all that this must be the case. The
print subsystem may not remove the spool file on its own, so whatever command you specify, you should ensure
that the spool file is deleted after it has been processed.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>traditional printing</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>customized print commands</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>built-in commands</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>macros</primary></indexterm>
There is no difficulty with using your own customized print commands with the traditional printing systems.
However, if you do not wish to roll your own, you should be well informed about the default built-in commands
that Samba uses for each printing subsystem (see <link linkend="printOptions">Default Printing
Settings</link>). In all the commands listed in the last paragraphs, you see parameters of the form
<emphasis>%X</emphasis>. These are <emphasis>macros</emphasis>, or shortcuts, used as placeholders for the
names of real objects. At the time of running a command with such a placeholder, Samba will insert the
appropriate value automatically. Print commands can handle all Samba macro substitutions. In regard to
printing, the following ones do have special relevance:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para><parameter>%s, %f</parameter> &smbmdash; the path to the spool file name.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para><parameter>%p</parameter> &smbmdash; the appropriate printer name.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para><parameter>%J</parameter> &smbmdash; the job name as transmitted by the client.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para><parameter>%c</parameter> &smbmdash; the number of printed pages of the spooled job (if known).</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para><parameter>%z</parameter> &smbmdash; the size of the spooled print job (in bytes).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>default printer</primary></indexterm>
The print command must contain at least one occurrence of <parameter>%s</parameter> or
<parameter>%f</parameter>. The <parameter>%p</parameter> is optional. If no printer name is supplied,
the <parameter>%p</parameter> will be silently removed from the print command. In this case, the job is
sent to the default printer.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>global print command</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>spool files</primary></indexterm>
If specified in the <smbconfsection name="[global]"/> section, the print command given will be
used for any printable service that does not have its own print command specified. If there is neither a
specified print command for a printable service nor a global print command, spool files will be created
but not processed! Most importantly, print files will not be removed, so they will consume disk space.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>nobody account</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>guest account</primary></indexterm>
Printing may fail on some UNIX systems when using the <emphasis>nobody</emphasis> account. If this happens, create an
alternative guest account and give it the privilege to print. Set up this guest account in the
<smbconfsection name="[global]"/> section with the <parameter>guest account</parameter> parameter.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>environment variables</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>print commands</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>print job</primary></indexterm>
You can form quite complex print commands. You need to realize that print commands are just
passed to a UNIX shell. The shell is able to expand the included environment variables as
usual. (The syntax to include a UNIX environment variable <parameter>$variable</parameter>
in the Samba print command is <parameter>%$variable</parameter>.) To give you a working
<smbconfoption name="print command"/> example, the following will log a print job
to <filename>/tmp/print.log</filename>, print the file, then remove it. The semicolon (<quote>;</quote>)
is the usual separator for commands in shell scripts:
</para>

<para><smbconfblock>
	<smbconfoption name="print command">echo Printing %s &gt;&gt; /tmp/print.log; lpr -P %p %s; rm %s</smbconfoption>
</smbconfblock></para>

<para>
You may have to vary your own command considerably from this example depending on how you normally print
files on your system. The default for the <smbconfoption name="print command"/>
parameter varies depending on the setting of the <smbconfoption name="printing"/>
parameter. Another example is:
</para>

<para><smbconfblock>
<smbconfoption name="print command">/usr/local/samba/bin/myprintscript %p %s</smbconfoption>
</smbconfblock></para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="cups-msrpc">
<title>Printing Developments Since Samba-2.2</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>LanMan</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>MS-RPC</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>SPOOLSS</primary></indexterm>
Prior to Samba-2.2.x, print server support for Windows clients was limited to <emphasis>LanMan</emphasis>
printing calls. This is the same protocol level as Windows 9x/Me PCs offer when they share printers.
Beginning with the 2.2.0 release, Samba started to support the native Windows NT printing mechanisms. These
are implemented via <emphasis>MS-RPC</emphasis> (Remote Procedure Calls).
MS-RPCs use the <emphasis>SPOOLSS</emphasis> named pipe for all printing.
</para>

<para>
The additional functionality provided by the new SPOOLSS support includes:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
<indexterm><primary>Point'n'Print</primary></indexterm>
	Support for downloading printer driver files to Windows 95/98/NT/2000 clients upon
	demand (<emphasis>Point'n'Print</emphasis>).
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
<indexterm><primary>Add Printer Wizard</primary></indexterm>
	Uploading of printer drivers via the Windows NT <emphasis>Add Printer Wizard</emphasis> (APW)
	or the <ulink url="http://imprints.sourceforge.net/">Imprints</ulink> tool set.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>	
<indexterm><primary>MS-RPC</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>printing calls</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>StartDocPrinter</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>EnumJobs()</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Win32 printing API</primary></indexterm>
	Support for the native MS-RPC printing calls such as StartDocPrinter, EnumJobs(), and so on. (See the
	<ulink url="http://msdn.microsoft.com/">MSDN documentation</ulink> for more information on the
	Win32 printing API).
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
<indexterm><primary>ACL</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>printer objects</primary></indexterm>
	Support for NT Access Control Lists (ACL) on printer objects.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
<indexterm><primary>printer queue</primary></indexterm>
	Improved support for printer queue manipulation through the use of internal databases for spooled
	job information (implemented by various <filename>*.tdb</filename> files).
	</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>ADS</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>LDAP</primary></indexterm>
A benefit of updating is that Samba-3 is able to publish its printers to Active Directory (or LDAP).
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>publish printers</primary></indexterm>
A fundamental difference exists between MS Windows NT print servers and Samba operation. Windows NT
permits the installation of local printers that are not shared. This is an artifact of the fact that
any Windows NT machine (server or client) may be used by a user as a workstation. Samba will publish all
printers that are made available, either by default or by specific declaration via printer-specific shares.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>SMB</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>MS-RPC</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Everyone group</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>privileges</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>printer default permissions</primary></indexterm>
Windows NT/200x/XP Professional clients do not have to use the standard SMB printer share; they can
print directly to any printer on another Windows NT host using MS-RPC. This, of course, assumes that
the client has the necessary privileges on the remote host that serves the printer resource. The
default permissions assigned by Windows NT to a printer gives the print permissions to the well-known
<emphasis>Everyone</emphasis> group. (The older clients of type Windows 9x/Me can only print to shared
printers.)
</para>

<sect2>
<title>Point'n'Print Client Drivers on Samba Servers</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>printer drivers</primary></indexterm>
There is much confusion about what all this means. The question is often asked, <quote>Is it or is
it not necessary for printer drivers to be installed on a Samba host in order to support printing from
Windows clients?</quote> The answer to this is no, it is not necessary.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>install drivers</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>print queue</primary></indexterm>
Windows NT/2000 clients can, of course, also run their APW to install drivers <emphasis>locally</emphasis>
(which then connect to a Samba-served print queue). This is the same method used by Windows 9x/Me
clients. (However, a bug existed in Samba 2.2.0 that made Windows NT/2000 clients
require that the Samba server possess a valid driver for the printer. This was fixed in Samba 2.2.1).
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>printer drivers</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>uploading</primary></indexterm>
But it is a new capability to install the printer drivers into the <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/>
share of the Samba server, and a big convenience, too. Then <emphasis>all</emphasis> clients
(including 95/98/ME) get the driver installed when they first connect to this printer share. The
<emphasis>uploading</emphasis> or <emphasis>depositing</emphasis> of the driver into this
<smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> share and the following binding of this driver to an existing
Samba printer share can be achieved by different means:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	Running the <emphasis>APW</emphasis> on an NT/200x/XP Professional client (this does not work from 95/98/ME clients).
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Using the <emphasis>Imprints</emphasis> toolset.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Using the <emphasis>smbclient</emphasis> and <emphasis>rpcclient</emphasis> command-line tools.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Using <emphasis>cupsaddsmb</emphasis> (only works for the CUPS printing system, not for LPR/LPD, LPRng, and so on).
	</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>uploaded drivers</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Point'n'Print</primary></indexterm>
Samba does not use these uploaded drivers in any way to process spooled files. These drivers are utilized
entirely by the clients who download and install them via the <quote>Point'n'Print</quote> mechanism
supported by Samba. The clients use these drivers to generate print files in the format the printer
(or the UNIX print system) requires. Print files received by Samba are handed over to the UNIX printing
system, which is responsible for all further processing, as needed.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>The Obsoleted [printer$] Section</title>

	<para>
<indexterm><primary>printer$ share</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>printer driver</primary></indexterm>
	Versions of Samba prior to 2.2 made it possible to use a share named <parameter>[printer$]</parameter>. This
	name was taken from the same named service created by Windows 9x/Me clients when a printer was shared by them.
	Windows 9x/Me printer servers always have a <smbconfsection name="[printer$]"/> service that provides
	read-only access (with no password required) to support printer driver downloads. However, Samba's initial
	implementation allowed for a parameter named <parameter>printer driver location</parameter> to be used on a
	per-share basis. This specified the location of the driver files associated with that printer. Another
	parameter named <parameter>printer driver</parameter> provided a means of defining the printer driver name to
	be sent to the client.
	</para>

	<para>
<indexterm><primary>printer driver file</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>read-write access</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ACLs</primary></indexterm>
	These parameters, including the <parameter>printer driver file</parameter> parameter,
	are now removed and cannot be used in installations of Samba-3. The share name
	<smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> is now used for the location of downloadable printer
	drivers. It is taken from the <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> service created
	by Windows NT PCs when a printer is shared by them. Windows NT print servers always have a
	<smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> service that provides read-write access (in the context
	of its ACLs) to support printer driver downloads and uploads. This does not mean Windows
	9x/Me clients are now thrown aside. They can use Samba's <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/>
	share support just fine.
	</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Creating the [print$] Share</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>printer driver</primary></indexterm>
In order to support the uploading and downloading of printer driver files, you must first configure a
file share named <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/>. The public name of this share is hard coded
in the MS Windows clients. It cannot be renamed, since Windows clients are programmed to search for a
service of exactly this name if they want to retrieve printer driver files.
</para>

<para>
You should modify the server's file to add the global parameters and create the
<smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> file share (of course, some of the parameter values, such
as <smbconfoption name="path"/>, are arbitrary and should be replaced with appropriate values for your
site). See <link linkend="prtdollar">[print\$] Example</link>.
</para>

<example id="prtdollar">
<title>[print$] Example</title>
<smbconfblock>
<smbconfsection name="[global]"/>
<smbconfcomment>members of the ntadmin group should be able to add drivers and set</smbconfcomment>
<smbconfcomment>printer properties. root is implicitly always a 'printer admin'.</smbconfcomment>
<smbconfoption name="printer admin">@ntadmin</smbconfoption>
<smbconfcomment>...</smbconfcomment>

<smbconfsection name="[printers]"/>
<smbconfcomment>...</smbconfcomment>

<smbconfsection name="[print$]"/>
<smbconfoption name="comment">Printer Driver Download Area</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="path">/etc/samba/drivers</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="browseable">yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="guest ok">yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="read only">yes</smbconfoption>
<smbconfoption name="write list">@ntadmin, root</smbconfoption>
</smbconfblock>
</example>

<para>
Of course, you also need to ensure that the directory named by the
<smbconfoption name="path"/> parameter exists on the UNIX file system.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>[print$] Stanza Parameters</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>special section</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>special stanza</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>potential printer</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>driver download</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>local print driver</primary></indexterm>
The <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> is a special section in &smb.conf;. It contains settings relevant to
potential printer driver download and is used by Windows clients for local print driver installation.
The following parameters are frequently needed in this share section:
</para>

<variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="comment">Printer Driver Download Area </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		The comment appears next to the share name if it is listed in a share list (usually Windows
		clients will not see it, but it will also appear up in a <command>smbclient -L sambaserver
		</command> output).
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="path">/etc/samba/printers </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		The path to the location of the Windows driver file deposit from the UNIX point of view.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="browseable">no </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Makes the <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> share invisible to clients from the
		<guimenu>Network Neighborhood</guimenu>. By excuting from a <command>cmd</command> shell:
<screen>
&dosprompt; <command>net use g:\\sambaserver\print$</command>
</screen>
		 you can still mount it from any client. This can also be done from the
		<guimenu>Connect network drive</guimenu> menu from Windows Explorer.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="guest ok">yes </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Gives read-only access to this share for all guest users. Access may be granted to
		download and install printer drivers on clients. The requirement for <parameter>guest ok
		= yes</parameter> depends on how your site is configured. If users will be guaranteed
		to have an account on the Samba host, then this is a non-issue.
		</para>

		<note><para> 
		If all your Windows NT users are guaranteed to be authenticated by the Samba server
		(for example, if Samba authenticates via an NT domain server and the user has already been
		validated by the domain controller in order to log on to the Windows NT session), then guest
		access is not necessary. Of course, in a workgroup environment where you just want
		to print without worrying about silly accounts and security, then configure the share for
		guest access. You should consider adding <smbconfoption name="map to guest">Bad	User</smbconfoption>
		in the <smbconfsection name="[global]"/> section as well. Make sure you understand what this
		parameter does before using it.
		</para></note>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="read only">yes </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Because we do not want everybody to upload driver files (or even change driver settings),
		we tagged this share as not writable.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term><smbconfoption name="write list">@ntadmin, root </smbconfoption></term>
		<listitem><para>
		The <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> was made read-only by the previous
		setting so we should create a <parameter>write list</parameter> entry also. UNIX
		groups are denoted with a leading <quote>@</quote> character. Users listed here are allowed
		write-access (as an exception to the general public's read-only access), which they need to
		update files on the share. Normally, you will want to name only administrative-level user
		account in this setting. Check the file system permissions to make sure these accounts
		can copy files to the share. If this is a non-root account, then the account should also
		be mentioned in the global <smbconfoption name="printer admin"/>
		parameter. See the &smb.conf; man page for more information on configuring file shares.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>The [print$] Share Directory</title>

<para>
In order for a Windows NT print server to support the downloading of driver files by multiple client
architectures, you must create several subdirectories within the <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/>
service (i.e., the UNIX directory named by the <smbconfoption name="path"/>
parameter). These correspond to each of the supported client architectures. Samba follows this model as
well. Just like the name of the <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> share itself, the subdirectories
must be exactly the names listed below (you may leave out the subdirectories of architectures you do
not need to support).
</para>

<para>
Therefore, create a directory tree below the
<smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> share for each architecture you wish
to support like this:
<programlisting>
[print$]--+
          |--W32X86           # serves drivers to Windows NT x86
          |--WIN40            # serves drivers to Windows 95/98
          |--W32ALPHA         # serves drivers to Windows NT Alpha_AXP
          |--W32MIPS          # serves drivers to Windows NT R4000
          |--W32PPC           # serves drivers to Windows NT PowerPC
</programlisting>
</para>

<important><title>Required Permissions</title>
	<para>
	In order to add a new driver to your Samba host, one of two conditions must hold true:
	</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
		The account used to connect to the Samba host must have a UID of 0 (i.e., a root account).
		</para></listitem>

		<listitem><para>
		The account used to connect to the Samba host must be named in the <emphasis>printer admin</emphasis> list.
		</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>
	Of course, the connected account must still have write access to add files to the subdirectories beneath
	<smbconfsection name="[print$]"/>. Remember that all file shares are set to <quote>read-only</quote> by default.
	</para>
</important>

<para>
Once you have created the required <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> service and
associated subdirectories, go to a Windows NT 4.0/200x/XP client workstation. Open <guiicon>Network
Neighborhood</guiicon> or <guiicon>My Network Places</guiicon> and browse for the Samba host. Once you
have located the server, navigate to its <guiicon>Printers and Faxes</guiicon> folder. You should see
an initial listing of printers that matches the printer shares defined on your Samba host.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Installing Drivers into [print$]</title>

<para>
Have you successfully created the <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> share in &smb.conf;, and have you forced
Samba to reread its &smb.conf; file? Good. But you are not yet ready to use the new facility. The client
driver files need to be installed into this share. So far, it is still an empty share. Unfortunately, it is
not enough to just copy the driver files over. They need to be correctly installed so that appropriate records
for each driver will exist in the Samba internal databases so it can provide the correct drivers as they are
requested from MS Windows clients. And that is a bit tricky, to say the least. We now discuss two alternative
ways to install the drivers into <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/>:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	Using the Samba command-line utility <command>rpcclient</command> with its various subcommands (here,
	<command>adddriver</command> and <command>setdriver</command>) from any UNIX workstation.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Running a GUI (<guiicon>Printer Properties</guiicon> and <guiicon>Add Printer Wizard</guiicon>)
	from any Windows NT/200x/XP client workstation.
	</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
The latter option is probably the easier one (even if the process may seem a little bit weird at first).
</para>

<sect2>
<title>Add Printer Wizard Driver Installation</title>

<para>
The printers initially listed in the Samba host's <guiicon>Printers</guiicon> folder accessed from a
client's Explorer will have no real printer driver assigned to them. By default this driver name is set
to a null string. This must be changed now. The local <guiicon>Add Printer Wizard</guiicon> (APW), run from
NT/2000/XP clients, will help us in this task.
</para>

<para>
Installation of a valid printer driver is not straightforward. You must attempt to view the printer properties
for the printer to which you want the driver assigned. Open Windows Explorer, open <guiicon>Network
Neighborhood</guiicon>, browse to the Samba host, open Samba's <guiicon>Printers</guiicon> folder, right-click
on the printer icon, and select <guimenu>Properties...</guimenu>. You are now trying to view printer and
driver properties for a queue that has this default <constant>NULL</constant> driver assigned. This will
result in the following error message: <quote> Device settings cannot be displayed. The driver for the
specified printer is not installed, only spooler properties will be displayed. Do you want to install the
driver now?</quote>
</para>

<para>
Do <emphasis>not</emphasis> click on <guibutton>Yes</guibutton>!  Instead, click on <guibutton>No</guibutton>
in the error dialog.  Now you will be presented with the printer properties window. From here, the way to
assign a driver to a printer is open. You now have the choice of:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	Select a driver from the pop-up list of installed drivers. Initially this list will be empty.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Click on <guibutton>New Driver</guibutton> to install a new printer driver (which will
	start up the APW).
	</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
Once the APW is started, the procedure is exactly the same as the one you are familiar with in Windows (we
assume here that you are familiar with the printer driver installations procedure on Windows NT). Make sure
your connection is, in fact, set up as a user with <smbconfoption name="printer admin"/>
privileges (if in doubt, use <command>smbstatus</command> to check for this). If you wish to install
printer drivers for client operating systems other than <application>Windows NT x86</application>,
you will need to use the <guilabel>Sharing</guilabel> tab of the printer properties dialog.
</para>

<para>
Assuming you have connected with an administrative (or root) account (as named by the
<smbconfoption name="printer admin"/> parameter), you will also be able to modify
other printer properties such as ACLs and default device settings using this dialog. For the default
device settings, please consider the advice given further in <link linkend="inst-rpc">Installing
Print Drivers Using <command>rpcclient</command></link>.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="inst-rpc">
<title>Installing Print Drivers Using <command>rpcclient</command></title>

<para>
The second way to install printer drivers into <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> and set them
up in a valid way is to do it from the UNIX command line. This involves four distinct steps:
</para>

<orderedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	Gather information about required driver files and collect the files.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Deposit the driver files into the <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> share's correct subdirectories
	(possibly by using <command>smbclient</command>).
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Run the <command>rpcclient</command> command-line utility once with the <command>adddriver</command>
	subcommand.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Run <command>rpcclient</command> a second time with the <command>setdriver</command> subcommand.
	</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>
We provide detailed hints for each of these steps in the paragraphs that follow.
</para>

<sect3>
<title>Identifying Driver Files</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>driver files</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>driver CDROM</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>inf file</primary></indexterm>
To find out about the driver files, you have two options. You can check the contents of the driver
CDROM that came with your printer. Study the <filename>*.inf</filename> files located on the CD-ROM. This
may not be possible, since the <filename>*.inf</filename> file might be missing. Unfortunately, vendors have now started
to use their own installation programs. These installations packages are often in some Windows platform
archive format. Additionally, the files may be re-named during the installation process. This makes it
extremely difficult to identify the driver files required.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>W32X86</primary></indexterm>
Then you have the second option. Install the driver locally on a Windows client and
investigate which filenames and paths it uses after they are installed. (You need to repeat
this procedure for every client platform you want to support. We show it here for the
<application>W32X86</application> platform only, a name used by Microsoft for all Windows NT/200x/XP
clients.)
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>driver files</primary></indexterm>
A good method to recognize the driver files is to print the test page from the driver's
<guilabel>Properties</guilabel> dialog (<guilabel>General</guilabel> tab). Then look at the list of
driver files named on the printout. You'll need to recognize what Windows (and Samba) are calling the
<guilabel>Driver File</guilabel>, <guilabel>Data File</guilabel>, <guilabel>Config File</guilabel>,
<guilabel>Help File</guilabel>, and (optionally) <guilabel>Dependent Driver Files</guilabel>
(this may vary slightly for Windows NT). You need to note all filenames for the next steps.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>rpcclient</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>enumdrivers</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>getdriver</primary></indexterm>
Another method to quickly test the driver filenames and related paths is provided by the
<command>rpcclient</command> utility. Run it with <command>enumdrivers</command> or with the
<command>getdriver</command> subcommand, each at the <filename>3</filename> info level. In the following example,
<emphasis>TURBO_XP</emphasis> is the name of the Windows PC (in this case it was a Windows XP Professional
laptop). I installed the driver locally to TURBO_XP from a Samba server called <constant>KDE-BITSHOP</constant>.
We could run an interactive <command>rpcclient</command> session; then we would get an
<command>rpcclient /></command> prompt and would type the subcommands at this prompt. This is left as
a good exercise for you. For now, we use <command>rpcclient</command> with the <option>-c</option>
parameter to execute a single subcommand line and exit again. This is the method you use if you
want to create scripts to automate the procedure for a large number of printers and drivers. Note the
different quotation marks used to overcome the different spaces between words:
</para>

<para><screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>rpcclient -U'Danka%xxxx' -c \
	'getdriver "Heidelberg Digimaster 9110 (PS)" 3' TURBO_XP</userinput>
cmd = getdriver "Heidelberg Digimaster 9110 (PS)" 3

[Windows NT x86]
Printer Driver Info 3:
  Version: [2]
  Driver Name: [Heidelberg Digimaster 9110 (PS)]
  Architecture: [Windows NT x86]
  Driver Path: [C:\WINNT\System32\spool\DRIVERS\W32X86\2\HDNIS01_de.DLL]
  Datafile: [C:\WINNT\System32\spool\DRIVERS\W32X86\2\Hddm91c1_de.ppd]
  Configfile: [C:\WINNT\System32\spool\DRIVERS\W32X86\2\HDNIS01U_de.DLL]
  Helpfile: [C:\WINNT\System32\spool\DRIVERS\W32X86\2\HDNIS01U_de.HLP]
  
  Dependentfiles: [C:\WINNT\System32\spool\DRIVERS\W32X86\2\Hddm91c1_de.DLL]
  Dependentfiles: [C:\WINNT\System32\spool\DRIVERS\W32X86\2\Hddm91c1_de.INI]
  Dependentfiles: [C:\WINNT\System32\spool\DRIVERS\W32X86\2\Hddm91c1_de.dat]
  Dependentfiles: [C:\WINNT\System32\spool\DRIVERS\W32X86\2\Hddm91c1_de.cat]
  Dependentfiles: [C:\WINNT\System32\spool\DRIVERS\W32X86\2\Hddm91c1_de.def]
  Dependentfiles: [C:\WINNT\System32\spool\DRIVERS\W32X86\2\Hddm91c1_de.hre]
  Dependentfiles: [C:\WINNT\System32\spool\DRIVERS\W32X86\2\Hddm91c1_de.vnd]
  Dependentfiles: [C:\WINNT\System32\spool\DRIVERS\W32X86\2\Hddm91c1_de.hlp]
  Dependentfiles: [C:\WINNT\System32\spool\DRIVERS\W32X86\2\HDNIS01Aux.dll]
  Dependentfiles: [C:\WINNT\System32\spool\DRIVERS\W32X86\2\HDNIS01_de.NTF]
  
  Monitorname: []
  Defaultdatatype: []
</screen></para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>Driver File</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Driver Path</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>WIN40</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>W32X86</primary></indexterm>
You may notice that this driver has quite a large number of <guilabel>Dependent files</guilabel>
(there are worse cases, however). Also, strangely, the
<guilabel>Driver File</guilabel> is tagged here
<guilabel>Driver Path</guilabel>. We do not yet have support for the so-called
<application>WIN40</application> architecture installed. This name is used by Microsoft for the Windows
9x/Me platforms. If we want to support these, we need to install the Windows 9x/Me driver files in
addition to those for <application>W32X86</application> (i.e., the Windows NT 2000/XP clients) onto a
Windows PC. This PC can also host the Windows 9x/Me drivers, even if it runs on Windows NT, 2000, or XP.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>UNC notation</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Windows Explorer</primary></indexterm>
Since the <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> share is usually accessible through the <guiicon>Network
Neighborhood</guiicon>, you can also use the UNC notation from Windows Explorer to poke at it. The Windows
9x/Me driver files will end up in subdirectory <filename>0</filename> of the <filename>WIN40</filename>
directory. The full path to access them is <filename>\\WINDOWSHOST\print$\WIN40\0\</filename>.
</para>

<note><para>
More recent drivers on Windows 2000 and Windows XP are installed into the <quote>3</quote> subdirectory
instead of the <quote>2</quote>. The version 2 of drivers, as used in Windows NT, were running in kernel
mode. Windows 2000 changed this. While it still can use the kernel mode drivers (if this is enabled by
the Admin), its native mode for printer drivers is user mode execution. This requires drivers designed
for this purpose. These types of drivers install into the <quote>3</quote> subdirectory.
</para></note>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Obtaining Driver Files from Windows Client [print$] Shares</title>

<para>
Now we need to collect all the driver files we identified in our previous step. Where do we get them
from? Well, why not retrieve them from the very PC and the same <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/>
share that we investigated in our last step to identify the files? We can use <command>smbclient</command>
to do this. We will use the paths and names that were leaked to us by <command>getdriver</command>. The
listing is edited to include line breaks for readability:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>smbclient //TURBO_XP/print\$ -U'Danka%xxxx' \ 
   -c 'cd W32X86/2;mget HD*_de.* hd*ppd Hd*_de.* Hddm*dll HDN*Aux.DLL'</userinput>

added interface ip=10.160.51.60 bcast=10.160.51.255 nmask=255.255.252.0
Got a positive name query response from 10.160.50.8 ( 10.160.50.8 )
Domain=[DEVELOPMENT] OS=[Windows 5.1] Server=[Windows 2000 LAN Manager]
<prompt>Get file Hddm91c1_de.ABD? </prompt><userinput>n</userinput>
<prompt>Get file Hddm91c1_de.def? </prompt><userinput>y</userinput>
getting file \W32X86\2\Hddm91c1_de.def of size 428 as Hddm91c1_de.def
<prompt>Get file Hddm91c1_de.DLL? </prompt><userinput>y</userinput>
getting file \W32X86\2\Hddm91c1_de.DLL of size 876544 as Hddm91c1_de.DLL
[...]
</screen></para>

<para>
After this command is complete, the files are in our current local directory. You probably have noticed
that this time we passed several commands to the <option>-c</option> parameter, separated by semicolons.
This ensures that all commands are executed in sequence on the remote Windows server before
<command>smbclient</command> exits again.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>WIN40</primary></indexterm>
Remember to repeat the procedure for the <application>WIN40</application> architecture should you need to
support Windows 9x/Me/XP clients. Remember too, the files for these architectures are in the
<filename>WIN40/0/</filename> subdirectory. Once this is complete, we can run <command>smbclient. .
.put</command> to store the collected files on the Samba server's <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> share.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Installing Driver Files into [print$]</title>

<para>
We are now going to locate the driver files into the <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> share. Remember, the
UNIX path to this share has been defined previously in your &smb.conf; file. You also have created
subdirectories for the different Windows client types you want to support. If, for example, your
<smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> share maps to the UNIX path <filename>/etc/samba/drivers/</filename>, your
driver files should now go here:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	For all Windows NT, 2000, and XP clients, <filename>/etc/samba/drivers/W32X86/</filename> but
	not (yet) into the <filename>2</filename> subdirectory.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	For all Windows 95, 98, and Me clients, <filename>/etc/samba/drivers/WIN40/</filename> but not
	(yet) into the <filename>0</filename> subdirectory.
	</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>smbclient</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>getdriver</primary></indexterm>
We again use smbclient to transfer the driver files across the network. We specify the same files
and paths as were leaked to us by running <command>getdriver</command> against the original
<emphasis>Windows</emphasis> install. However, now we are going to store the files into a
<emphasis>Samba/UNIX</emphasis> print server's <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> share.
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>smbclient //SAMBA-CUPS/print\$ -U'root%xxxx' -c \
  'cd W32X86; put HDNIS01_de.DLL; \
  put Hddm91c1_de.ppd; put HDNIS01U_de.DLL;        \
  put HDNIS01U_de.HLP; put Hddm91c1_de.DLL;        \
  put Hddm91c1_de.INI; put Hddm91c1KMMin.DLL;      \
  put Hddm91c1_de.dat; put Hddm91c1_de.dat;        \
  put Hddm91c1_de.def; put Hddm91c1_de.hre;        \
  put Hddm91c1_de.vnd; put Hddm91c1_de.hlp;        \
  put Hddm91c1_de_reg.HLP; put HDNIS01Aux.dll;     \
  put HDNIS01_de.NTF'</userinput>

added interface ip=10.160.51.60 bcast=10.160.51.255 nmask=255.255.252.0
Got a positive name query response from 10.160.51.162 ( 10.160.51.162 )
Domain=[CUPS-PRINT] OS=[UNIX] Server=[Samba 2.2.7a]
putting file HDNIS01_de.DLL as \W32X86\HDNIS01_de.DLL
putting file Hddm91c1_de.ppd as \W32X86\Hddm91c1_de.ppd
putting file HDNIS01U_de.DLL as \W32X86\HDNIS01U_de.DLL
putting file HDNIS01U_de.HLP as \W32X86\HDNIS01U_de.HLP
putting file Hddm91c1_de.DLL as \W32X86\Hddm91c1_de.DLL
putting file Hddm91c1_de.INI as \W32X86\Hddm91c1_de.INI
putting file Hddm91c1KMMin.DLL as \W32X86\Hddm91c1KMMin.DLL
putting file Hddm91c1_de.dat as \W32X86\Hddm91c1_de.dat
putting file Hddm91c1_de.dat as \W32X86\Hddm91c1_de.dat
putting file Hddm91c1_de.def as \W32X86\Hddm91c1_de.def
putting file Hddm91c1_de.hre as \W32X86\Hddm91c1_de.hre
putting file Hddm91c1_de.vnd as \W32X86\Hddm91c1_de.vnd
putting file Hddm91c1_de.hlp as \W32X86\Hddm91c1_de.hlp
putting file Hddm91c1_de_reg.HLP as \W32X86\Hddm91c1_de_reg.HLP
putting file HDNIS01Aux.dll as \W32X86\HDNIS01Aux.dll
putting file HDNIS01_de.NTF as \W32X86\HDNIS01_de.NTF
</screen>
<indexterm><primary>PPD</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>PostScript driver</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>adddriver</primary></indexterm>
Whew &smbmdash; that was a lot of typing! Most drivers are a lot smaller &smbmdash; many have only three generic
PostScript driver files plus one PPD. While we did retrieve the files from the <filename>2</filename>
subdirectory of the <filename>W32X86</filename> directory from the Windows box, we do not put them
(for now) in this same subdirectory of the Samba box. This relocation will automatically be done by the
<command>adddriver</command> command, which we will run shortly (and do not forget to also put the files
for the Windows 9x/Me architecture into the <filename>WIN40/</filename> subdirectory should you need them).
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3>
<title><command>smbclient</command> to Confirm Driver Installation</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>smbclient</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>SSH</primary></indexterm>
For now we verify that our files are there. This can be done with <command>smbclient</command>, too
(but, of course, you can log in via SSH also and do this through a standard UNIX shell access):
</para>

<para><screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>smbclient //SAMBA-CUPS/print\$ -U 'root%xxxx' \
	-c 'cd W32X86; pwd; dir; cd 2; pwd; dir'</userinput>
 added interface ip=10.160.51.60 bcast=10.160.51.255 nmask=255.255.252.0
Got a positive name query response from 10.160.51.162 ( 10.160.51.162 )
Domain=[CUPS-PRINT] OS=[UNIX] Server=[Samba 2.2.8a]

Current directory is \\SAMBA-CUPS\print$\W32X86\
.                                  D        0  Sun May  4 03:56:35 2003
..                                 D        0  Thu Apr 10 23:47:40 2003
2                                   D        0  Sun May  4 03:56:18 2003
HDNIS01Aux.dll                      A    15356  Sun May  4 03:58:59 2003
Hddm91c1KMMin.DLL                   A    46966  Sun May  4 03:58:59 2003
HDNIS01_de.DLL                      A   434400  Sun May  4 03:58:59 2003
HDNIS01_de.NTF                      A   790404  Sun May  4 03:56:35 2003
Hddm91c1_de.DLL                     A   876544  Sun May  4 03:58:59 2003
Hddm91c1_de.INI                     A      101  Sun May  4 03:58:59 2003
Hddm91c1_de.dat                     A     5044  Sun May  4 03:58:59 2003
Hddm91c1_de.def                     A      428  Sun May  4 03:58:59 2003
Hddm91c1_de.hlp                     A    37699  Sun May  4 03:58:59 2003
Hddm91c1_de.hre                     A   323584  Sun May  4 03:58:59 2003
Hddm91c1_de.ppd                     A    26373  Sun May  4 03:58:59 2003
Hddm91c1_de.vnd                     A    45056  Sun May  4 03:58:59 2003
HDNIS01U_de.DLL                     A   165888  Sun May  4 03:58:59 2003
HDNIS01U_de.HLP                     A    19770  Sun May  4 03:58:59 2003
Hddm91c1_de_reg.HLP                 A   228417  Sun May  4 03:58:59 2003
              40976 blocks of size 262144. 709 blocks available

Current directory is \\SAMBA-CUPS\print$\W32X86\2\
.                                  D        0  Sun May  4 03:56:18 2003
..                                 D        0  Sun May  4 03:56:35 2003
ADOBEPS5.DLL                        A   434400  Sat May  3 23:18:45 2003
laserjet4.ppd                       A     9639  Thu Apr 24 01:05:32 2003
ADOBEPSU.DLL                        A   109568  Sat May  3 23:18:45 2003
ADOBEPSU.HLP                        A    18082  Sat May  3 23:18:45 2003
PDFcreator2.PPD                     A    15746  Sun Apr 20 22:24:07 2003
              40976 blocks of size 262144. 709 blocks available
</screen></para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>Point'n'Print</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>printer driver files</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>print queue</primary></indexterm>
Notice that there are already driver files present in the <filename>2</filename> subdirectory (probably from a
previous installation). Once the files for the new driver are there too, you are still a few steps away from
being able to use them on the clients. The only thing you could do now is retrieve them from a client just
like you retrieve ordinary files from a file share, by opening print$ in Windows Explorer. But that wouldn't
install them per Point'n'Print. The reason is that Samba does not yet know that these files are something
special, namely <emphasis>printer driver files</emphasis>, and it does not know to which print queue(s) these
driver files belong.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Running <command>rpcclient</command> with <command>adddriver</command></title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>adddriver</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>register driver files</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>TDB database</primary></indexterm>
Next, you must tell Samba about the special category of the files you just uploaded into the
<smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> share. This is done by the <command>adddriver</command>
command. It will prompt Samba to register the driver files into its internal TDB database files. The
following command and its output has been edited for readability:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>rpcclient -Uroot%xxxx -c 'adddriver "Windows NT x86" \
  "dm9110:HDNIS01_de.DLL: \
  Hddm91c1_de.ppd:HDNIS01U_de.DLL:HDNIS01U_de.HLP:   \
  NULL:RAW:Hddm91c1_de.DLL,Hddm91c1_de.INI,          \
  Hddm91c1_de.dat,Hddm91c1_de.def,Hddm91c1_de.hre,   \
  Hddm91c1_de.vnd,Hddm91c1_de.hlp,Hddm91c1KMMin.DLL, \
  HDNIS01Aux.dll,HDNIS01_de.NTF,                     \
  Hddm91c1_de_reg.HLP' SAMBA-CUPS</userinput>

cmd = adddriver "Windows NT x86" \
  "dm9110:HDNIS01_de.DLL:Hddm91c1_de.ppd:HDNIS01U_de.DLL:   \
  HDNIS01U_de.HLP:NULL:RAW:Hddm91c1_de.DLL,Hddm91c1_de.INI, \
  Hddm91c1_de.dat,Hddm91c1_de.def,Hddm91c1_de.hre,          \
  Hddm91c1_de.vnd,Hddm91c1_de.hlp,Hddm91c1KMMin.DLL,        \
  HDNIS01Aux.dll,HDNIS01_de.NTF,Hddm91c1_de_reg.HLP"

Printer Driver dm9110 successfully installed.
</screen></para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>NT_STATUS_UNSUCCESSFUL</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>error message</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>adddriver</primary></indexterm>
After this step, the driver should be recognized by Samba on the print server. You need to be very
careful when typing the command. Don't exchange the order of the fields. Some changes would lead to
an <computeroutput>NT_STATUS_UNSUCCESSFUL</computeroutput> error message. These become obvious. Other
changes might install the driver files successfully but render the driver unworkable. So take care!
Hints about the syntax of the adddriver command are in the man page. 
provides a more detailed description, should you need it.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Checking <command>adddriver</command> Completion</title>

<para>
One indication for Samba's recognition of the files as driver files is the <computeroutput>successfully
installed</computeroutput> message. Another one is the fact that our files have been moved by the
<command>adddriver</command> command into the <filename>2</filename> subdirectory. You can check this
again with <command>smbclient</command>:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>smbclient //SAMBA-CUPS/print\$ -Uroot%xx \
	-c 'cd W32X86;dir;pwd;cd 2;dir;pwd'</userinput>
 added interface ip=10.160.51.162 bcast=10.160.51.255 nmask=255.255.252.0
 Domain=[CUPS-PRINT] OS=[UNIX] Server=[Samba 2.2.7a]

  Current directory is \\SAMBA-CUPS\print$\W32X86\
  .                                  D        0  Sun May  4 04:32:48 2003
  ..                                 D        0  Thu Apr 10 23:47:40 2003
  2                                   D        0  Sun May  4 04:32:48 2003
                40976 blocks of size 262144. 731 blocks available 

  Current directory is \\SAMBA-CUPS\print$\W32X86\2\
  .                                  D        0  Sun May  4 04:32:48 2003
  ..                                 D        0  Sun May  4 04:32:48 2003
  DigiMaster.PPD                      A   148336  Thu Apr 24 01:07:00 2003
  ADOBEPS5.DLL                        A   434400  Sat May  3 23:18:45 2003
  laserjet4.ppd                       A     9639  Thu Apr 24 01:05:32 2003
  ADOBEPSU.DLL                        A   109568  Sat May  3 23:18:45 2003
  ADOBEPSU.HLP                        A    18082  Sat May  3 23:18:45 2003
  PDFcreator2.PPD                     A    15746  Sun Apr 20 22:24:07 2003
  HDNIS01Aux.dll                      A    15356  Sun May  4 04:32:18 2003
  Hddm91c1KMMin.DLL                   A    46966  Sun May  4 04:32:18 2003
  HDNIS01_de.DLL                      A   434400  Sun May  4 04:32:18 2003
  HDNIS01_de.NTF                      A   790404  Sun May  4 04:32:18 2003
  Hddm91c1_de.DLL                     A   876544  Sun May  4 04:32:18 2003
  Hddm91c1_de.INI                     A      101  Sun May  4 04:32:18 2003
  Hddm91c1_de.dat                     A     5044  Sun May  4 04:32:18 2003
  Hddm91c1_de.def                     A      428  Sun May  4 04:32:18 2003
  Hddm91c1_de.hlp                     A    37699  Sun May  4 04:32:18 2003
  Hddm91c1_de.hre                     A   323584  Sun May  4 04:32:18 2003
  Hddm91c1_de.ppd                     A    26373  Sun May  4 04:32:18 2003
  Hddm91c1_de.vnd                     A    45056  Sun May  4 04:32:18 2003
  HDNIS01U_de.DLL                     A   165888  Sun May  4 04:32:18 2003
  HDNIS01U_de.HLP                     A    19770  Sun May  4 04:32:18 2003
  Hddm91c1_de_reg.HLP                 A   228417  Sun May  4 04:32:18 2003
                40976 blocks of size 262144. 731 blocks available
</screen></para>

<para>
Another verification is that the timestamp of the printing TDB files is now updated
(and possibly their file size has increased).
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Check Samba for Driver Recognition</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>registered</primary></indexterm>
Now the driver should be registered with Samba. We can easily verify this and will do so in a
moment. However, this driver is not yet associated with a particular printer. We may check the driver
status of the files by at least three methods:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
<indexterm><primary>Network Neighborhood</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Printers and Faxes</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>printer icon</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Windows95/98/ME</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Windows NT/2000/XP</primary></indexterm>
	From any Windows client browse Network Neighborhood, find the Samba host, and open the Samba
	<guiicon>Printers and Faxes</guiicon> folder. Select any printer icon, right-click and select
	the printer <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem>. Click the <guilabel>Advanced</guilabel>
	tab. Here is a field indicating the driver for that printer. A drop-down menu allows you to
	change that driver (be careful not to do this unwittingly). You can use this list to view
	all drivers known to Samba. Your new one should be among them. (Each type of client will
	see only its own architecture's list. If you do not have every driver installed for each platform,
	the list will differ if you look at it from Windows95/98/ME or Windows NT/2000/XP.)
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
<indexterm><primary>Network Neighborhood</primary></indexterm>
	From a Windows 200x/XP client (not Windows NT) browse <guiicon>Network Neighborhood</guiicon>,
	search for the Samba server, open the server's <guiicon>Printers</guiicon> folder,
	and right-click on the white background (with no printer highlighted). Select <guimenuitem>Server
	Properties</guimenuitem>. On the <guilabel>Drivers</guilabel> tab you will see the new driver
	listed. This view enables you to also inspect the list of files belonging to that driver
	(this does not work on Windows NT, but only on Windows 2000 and Windows XP; Windows NT does not
	provide the <guimenuitem>Drivers</guimenuitem> tab). An alternative and much quicker method for
	Windows 2000/XP to start this dialog is by typing into a DOS box (you must of course adapt the
	name to your Samba server instead of <replaceable>SAMBA-CUPS</replaceable>):
	<screen>
	<userinput>rundll32 printui.dll,PrintUIEntry /s /t2 /n\\<replaceable>SAMBA-CUPS</replaceable></userinput>
	</screen>
	</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	From a UNIX prompt, run this command (or a variant thereof), where
	<replaceable>SAMBA-CUPS</replaceable> is the name of the Samba host and xxxx represents the
	actual Samba password assigned to root:
	<screen>
	<userinput>rpcclient -U'root%xxxx' -c 'enumdrivers' <replaceable>SAMBA-CUPS</replaceable></userinput>
	</screen>
	</para>

	<para>
	You will see a listing of all drivers Samba knows about. Your new one should be among
	them. But it is only listed under the <parameter>[Windows NT x86]</parameter> heading, not under
	<smbconfsection name="[Windows 4.0]"/>, since you didn't install that part. Or did you?
	In our example it is named <constant>dm9110</constant>. Note that the third column shows the other
	installed drivers twice, one time for each supported architecture. Our new driver only shows up
	for <application>Windows NT 4.0 or 2000</application>. To have it present for <application>Windows
	95, 98, and Me</application>, you'll have to repeat the whole procedure with the WIN40 architecture
	and subdirectory.
	</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Specific Driver Name Flexibility</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>adddriver</primary></indexterm>
You can name the driver as you like. If you repeat the <command>adddriver</command> step with the same
files as before but with a different driver name, it will work the same:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>rpcclient -Uroot%xxxx         \
  -c 'adddriver "Windows NT x86"                     \
  "mydrivername:HDNIS01_de.DLL:              \
  Hddm91c1_de.ppd:HDNIS01U_de.DLL:HDNIS01U_de.HLP:   \
  NULL:RAW:Hddm91c1_de.DLL,Hddm91c1_de.INI,          \
  Hddm91c1_de.dat,Hddm91c1_de.def,Hddm91c1_de.hre,   \
  Hddm91c1_de.vnd,Hddm91c1_de.hlp,Hddm91c1KMMin.DLL, \
  HDNIS01Aux.dll,HDNIS01_de.NTF,Hddm91c1_de_reg.HLP' SAMBA-CUPS
  </userinput>

cmd = adddriver "Windows NT x86" \
 "mydrivername:HDNIS01_de.DLL:Hddm91c1_de.ppd:HDNIS01U_de.DLL:\
  HDNIS01U_de.HLP:NULL:RAW:Hddm91c1_de.DLL,Hddm91c1_de.INI,           \
  Hddm91c1_de.dat,Hddm91c1_de.def,Hddm91c1_de.hre,                    \
  Hddm91c1_de.vnd,Hddm91c1_de.hlp,Hddm91c1KMMin.DLL,                  \
  HDNIS01Aux.dll,HDNIS01_de.NTF,Hddm91c1_de_reg.HLP"

Printer Driver mydrivername successfully installed.
</screen></para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>print queue</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>rpcclient</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>adddriver</primary></indexterm>
You will be able to bind that driver to any print queue (however, you are responsible that
you associate drivers to queues that make sense with respect to target printers). You cannot run the
<command>rpcclient</command> <command>adddriver</command> command repeatedly. Each run consumes the
files you had put into the <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> share by moving them into the
respective subdirectories, so you must execute an <command>smbclient ... put</command> command before
each <command>rpcclient ... adddriver</command> command.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Running <command>rpcclient</command> with <command>setdriver</command></title>

<para> 
<indexterm><primary>mapping printer driver</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>TDB</primary></indexterm>
Samba needs to know which printer owns which driver. Create a mapping of the driver to a printer, and
store this information in Samba's memory, the TDB files. The <command>rpcclient setdriver</command> command
achieves exactly this:
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>rpcclient -U'root%xxxx' -c 'setdriver dm9110 mydrivername' <replaceable>SAMBA-CUPS</replaceable></userinput>
 cmd = setdriver dm9110 mydrivername

Successfully set dm9110 to driver mydrivername.
</screen></para>

<para>
Ah, no, I did not want to do that. Repeat, this time with the name I intended: 
<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>rpcclient -U'root%xxxx' -c 'setdriver dm9110 dm9110' <replaceable>SAMBA-CUPS</replaceable></userinput>
 cmd = setdriver dm9110 dm9110
Successfully set dm9110 to driver dm9110.
</screen></para>

<para>
The syntax of the command is:
<screen>
<userinput>rpcclient -U'root%<replaceable>sambapassword</replaceable>' -c 'setdriver <replaceable>printername</replaceable> \
 <replaceable>drivername</replaceable>' <replaceable>SAMBA-Hostname</replaceable></userinput>. 
</screen>
Now we have done most of the work, but not all of it.
</para>

<note><para>
The <command>setdriver</command> command will only succeed if the printer is already known to Samba. A
bug in 2.2.x prevented Samba from recognizing freshly installed printers. You had to restart Samba,
or at least send an HUP signal to all running smbd processes to work around this: <userinput>kill -HUP
`pidof smbd`</userinput>.
</para></note>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Client Driver Installation Procedure</title>

<para>
As Don Quixote said, <quote>The proof of the pudding is in the eating.</quote> The proof
for our setup lies in the printing. So let's install the printer driver onto the client PCs. This is
not as straightforward as it may seem. Read on.
</para>

<sect2>
<title>First Client Driver Installation</title>

<para>
Especially important is the installation onto the first client PC (for each architectural platform
separately). Once this is done correctly, all further clients are easy to set up and shouldn't need further
attention. What follows is a description for the recommended first procedure. You now work from a client
workstation. You should check that your connection is not unwittingly mapped to <emphasis>bad
user</emphasis> nobody. In a DOS box type:
</para>

<para><userinput>net use \\<replaceable>SAMBA-SERVER</replaceable>\print$ /user:root</userinput></para>

<para>
Replace root, if needed, by another valid <smbconfoption name="printer admin"/> user as given in
the definition. Should you already be connected as a different user, you will get an error message. There
is no easy way to get rid of that connection, because Windows does not seem to know a concept of logging
off from a share connection (do not confuse this with logging off from the local workstation; that is
a different matter).  On Windows NT/200x, you can force a logoff from all smb/cifs connections by restarting the 
<emphasis>workstation</emphasis> service. You can try to close all Windows file explorers and Internet Explorer for 
Windows. As a last resort, you may have to reboot. Make sure there is no automatic reconnection set up. It may be
easier to go to a different workstation and try from there. After you have made sure you are connected
as a printer admin user (you can check this with the <command>smbstatus</command> command on Samba),
do this from the Windows workstation:
</para>

<procedure>
	<step><para>
	Open <guiicon>Network Neighborhood</guiicon>.
	</para></step>

	<step><para>
	Browse to Samba server.
	</para></step>

	<step><para>
	Open its <guiicon>Printers and Faxes</guiicon> folder.
	</para></step>

	<step><para>
	Highlight and right-click on the printer.
	</para></step>

	<step><para>
	Select <guimenuitem>Connect</guimenuitem> (for Windows NT4/200x
	it is possibly <guimenuitem>Install</guimenuitem>).
	</para></step>
</procedure>

<para>
A new printer (named <replaceable>printername</replaceable> on Samba server) should now have
appeared in your <emphasis>local</emphasis> Printer folder (check <guimenu>Start</guimenu> ->
<guimenuitem>Settings</guimenuitem> -> <guimenuitem>Control Panel</guimenuitem> -> <guiicon>Printers
and Faxes</guiicon>).
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>print test page</primary></indexterm>
Most likely you are tempted to try to print a test page. After all, you now can open the printer
properties, and on the <guimenu>General</guimenu> tab there is a button offering to do just that. But
chances are that you get an error message saying "<literal>Unable to print Test Page</literal>." The
reason might be that there is not yet a valid device mode set for the driver or that the <quote>printer
driver data</quote> set is still incomplete.
</para>

<para>
You must make sure that a valid <parameter>device mode</parameter> is set for the
driver. We now explain what that means.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="prt-modeset">
<title>Setting Device Modes on New Printers</title>

<para>
For a printer to be truly usable by a Windows NT/200x/XP client, it must possess:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
<indexterm><primary>device mode</primary></indexterm>
	A valid <emphasis>device mode</emphasis> generated by the driver for the printer (defining things
	like paper size, orientation and duplex settings).
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
<indexterm><primary>printer driver data</primary></indexterm>
	A complete set of <emphasis>printer driver data</emphasis> generated by the driver.
	</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>ntprinters.tdb</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ntdrivers.tdb</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>printing.tdb</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>ntforms.tdb</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>TDB database files</primary></indexterm>
If either of these is incomplete, the clients can produce less than optimal output at best. In the
worst cases, unreadable garbage or nothing at all comes from the printer, or it produces a harvest of
error messages when attempting to print. Samba stores the named values and all printing-related information in
its internal TDB database files <filename>(ntprinters.tdb</filename>, <filename>ntdrivers.tdb</filename>,
<filename>printing.tdb</filename>, and <filename>ntforms.tdb</filename>).
</para>

<para>
The device mode and the set of printer driver data are basically collections
of settings for all print queue properties, initialized in a sensible way. Device modes and
printer driver data should initially be set on the print server (the Samba host) to healthy
values so the clients can start to use them immediately. How do we set these initial healthy values?
This can be achieved by accessing the drivers remotely from an NT (or 200x/XP) client, as discussed
in the following paragraphs.
</para>

<para>
Be aware that a valid device mode can only be initiated by a <smbconfoption name="printer admin"/> or root
(the reason should be obvious). Device modes can be correctly set only by executing the printer driver program
itself. Since Samba cannot execute this Win32 platform driver code, it sets this field initially to NULL
(which is not a valid setting for clients to use). Fortunately, most drivers automatically generate the
printer driver data that is needed when they are uploaded to the <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> share with
the help of the APW or rpcclient.
</para>

<para>
The generation and setting of a first valid device mode, however, requires some tickling from a client
to set it on the Samba server. The easiest means of doing so is to simply change the page orientation on
the server's printer. This executes enough of the printer driver program on the client for the desired
effect to happen and feeds back the new device mode to our Samba server. You can use the native Windows
NT/200x/XP printer properties page from a Window client for this:
</para>

<procedure>
<title>Procedure to Initialize the Printer Driver Settings</title>
	<step><para>
	Browse the <guiicon>Network Neighborhood</guiicon>.
	</para></step>

	<step><para>
	Find the Samba server.
	</para></step>

	<step><para>
	Open the Samba server's <guiicon>Printers and Faxes</guiicon> folder.
	</para></step>

	<step><para>
	Highlight the shared printer in question.
	</para></step>

	<step><para>
	Right-click on the printer (you may already be here if you followed the last section's description).
	</para></step>

	<step><para>
	At the bottom of the context menu select <guimenu>Properties</guimenu> (if the menu still offers the 
	<guimenuitem>Connect</guimenuitem> entry further above, you
	need to click on that one first to achieve the driver
	installation, as shown in the last section).
	</para></step>

	<step><para>
	Go to the <guilabel>Advanced</guilabel> tab; click on <guibutton>Printing Defaults</guibutton>.
	</para></step>

	<step><para>
	Change the <guimenuitem>Portrait</guimenuitem> page setting to <guimenuitem>Landscape</guimenuitem> (and back).
	</para></step>

	<step><para>
	Make sure to apply changes between swapping the page orientation to cause the change to actually take effect.
	</para></step>

	<step><para>
	While you are at it, you may also want to set the desired printing defaults here, which then apply to all future
	client driver installations.
	</para></step>
</procedure>

<para>
This procedure executes the printer driver program on the client platform and feeds back the correct
device mode to Samba, which now stores it in its TDB files. Once the driver is installed on the client,
you can follow the analogous steps by accessing the <emphasis>local</emphasis> <guiicon>Printers</guiicon>
folder, too, if you are a Samba printer admin user. From now on, printing should work as expected.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>default devmode</primary></indexterm>
Samba includes a service-level parameter name <parameter>default devmode</parameter> for generating a default
device mode for a printer. Some drivers function well with Samba's default set of properties. Others
may crash the client's spooler service. So use this parameter with caution. It is always better to have
the client generate a valid device mode for the printer and store it on the server for you.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Additional Client Driver Installation</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>additional driver</primary></indexterm>
Every additional driver may be installed in the same way as just described.  Browse <command>Network
Neighborhood</command>, open the <guiicon>Printers</guiicon> folder on Samba server, right-click on
<guiicon>Printer</guiicon>, and choose <guimenuitem>Connect...</guimenuitem>. Once this completes (should be
not more than a few seconds, but could also take a minute, depending on network conditions), you should find
the new printer in your client workstation local <guiicon>Printers and Faxes</guiicon> folder.
</para>

<para>
You can also open your local <guiicon>Printers and Faxes</guiicon> folder by
using this command on Windows 200x/XP Professional workstations:
<screen>
<userinput>rundll32 shell32.dll,SHHelpShortcuts_RunDLL PrintersFolder</userinput>
</screen>
or this command on Windows NT 4.0 workstations:
<indexterm><primary>rundll32</primary></indexterm>
<screen>
<userinput>rundll32 shell32.dll,Control_RunDLL MAIN.CPL @2</userinput>
</screen>
</para>

<para>
You can enter the commands either inside a <guilabel>DOS box</guilabel> window or in the <guimenuitem>Run
command...</guimenuitem> field from the <guimenu>Start</guimenu> menu.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Always Make First Client Connection as root or <quote>printer admin</quote></title>

<para>
After you installed the driver on the Samba server (in its <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> share), you
should always make sure that your first client installation completes correctly. Make it a habit for yourself
to build the very first connection from a client as <smbconfoption name="printer admin"/>. This is to make
sure that:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	A first valid <emphasis>device mode</emphasis> is really initialized (see above <link
	linkend="prt-modeset">Setting Device Modes on New Printers</link>) for more explanation details).
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>	
	The default print settings of your printer for all further client installations are as you want them.
	</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
Do this by changing the orientation to landscape, click on <guiicon>Apply</guiicon>, and then change it
back again. Next, modify the other settings (for example, you do not want the default media size set to
<guiicon>Letter</guiicon> when you are all using <guiicon>A4</guiicon>, right? You may want to set the
printer for <guiicon>duplex</guiicon> as the default, and so on).
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>runas</primary></indexterm>
To connect as root to a Samba printer, try this command from a Windows 200x/XP DOS box command prompt:
<screen>
&dosprompt;<userinput>runas /netonly /user:root "rundll32 printui.dll,PrintUIEntry /p /t3 /n 
	\\<replaceable>SAMBA-SERVER</replaceable>\<replaceable>printername</replaceable>"</userinput>
</screen>
</para>

<para>
You will be prompted for <constant>root</constant>'s Samba password; type it, wait a few seconds, click on
<guibutton>Printing Defaults</guibutton>, and proceed to set the job options that should be used as defaults
by all clients. Alternatively, instead of root you can name one other member of the <smbconfoption
name="printer admin"/> from the setting.
</para>

<para>
Now all the other users downloading and installing the driver the same way (using
<literal>Point'n'Print</literal>) will have the same defaults set for them. If you miss this step, you'll get a
lot of help desk calls from your users, but maybe you like to talk to people.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Other Gotchas</title>

<para>
Your driver is installed. It is now ready for Point'n'Print installation by the clients. You may have tried to
download and use it on your first client machine, but wait. Let's make sure you are acquainted first with a
few tips and tricks you may find useful. For example, suppose you did not set the defaults on the printer, as
advised in the preceding paragraphs. Your users complain about various issues (such as, <quote>We need to set
the paper size for each job from Letter to A4 and it will not store it</quote>).
</para>

<sect2>
<title>Setting Default Print Options for Client Drivers</title>

<para>
The last sentence might be viewed with mixed feelings by some users and Admins. They have struggled for hours
and could not arrive at a point where their settings seemed to be saved. It is not their fault. The confusing
thing is that in the multitabbed dialog that pops up when you right-click on the printer name and select
<guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem>, you can arrive at two dialogs that appear identical, each claiming that
they help you to set printer options in three different ways. Here is the definitive answer to the Samba
default driver setting FAQ:
</para>

<formalpara><title><quote>I can not set and save default print options
for all users on Windows 200x/XP. Why not?</quote></title>

<para>
How are you doing it? I bet the wrong way. (It is not easy to find out, though.) There are three different
ways to bring you to a dialog that seems to set everything. All three dialogs look the same, but only one of
them does what you intend. You need to be Administrator or Print Administrator to do this for all users. Here
is how I reproduce it in an XP Professional:
</para>

<orderedlist numeration="upperalpha">
	<listitem><para>The first <quote>wrong</quote> way:
	<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
		<listitem><para>Open the <guiicon>Printers</guiicon> folder.</para></listitem>

		<listitem><para>Right-click on the printer (<emphasis>remoteprinter on cupshost</emphasis>) and
		select in context menu <guimenu>Printing Preferences...</guimenu>.</para></listitem>

		<listitem><para>Look at this dialog closely and remember what it looks like.</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist></para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>The second <quote>wrong</quote> way:
		<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
			<listitem><para>Open the <guimenu>Printers</guimenu> folder.</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>Right-click on the printer (<emphasis>remoteprinter on
			cupshost</emphasis>) and select in the context menu
			<guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem></para></listitem>.

			<listitem><para>Click on the <guilabel>General</guilabel>
			tab.</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>Click on the <guibutton>Printing
			Preferences...</guibutton> button.</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>A new dialog opens. Keep this dialog open and go back
			to the parent dialog.</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	The third and correct way (should you do this from the beginning, just carry out steps 1
	and 2 from the second method above):
	</para>

		<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
			<listitem><para>Click on the <guilabel>Advanced</guilabel>
			tab. (If everything is <quote>grayed out,</quote> then you are not logged
			in as a user with enough privileges.)</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>Click on the <guibutton>Printing
			Defaults</guibutton> button.</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>On any of the two new tabs,
			click on the
			<guilabel>Advanced</guilabel> button.</para></listitem>

			<listitem><para>A new dialog opens. Compare
			this one to the other. Are they
			identical when you compare one from
			<quote>B.5</quote> and one from A.3?</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>
Do you see any difference in the two settings dialogs? I do not either. However, only the last one, which you
arrived at with steps C.1 through C.6 will permanently save any settings which will then become the defaults
for new users. If you want all clients to have the same defaults, you need to conduct these steps as
administrator (<smbconfoption name="printer admin"/>) before a client downloads the driver (the clients can
later set their own per-user defaults by following procedures A or B above). Windows 200x/XP allow per-user
default settings and the ones the administrator gives them before they set up their own. The parents of the
identical-looking dialogs have a slight difference in their window names; one is called
<computeroutput>Default Print Values for Printer Foo on Server Bar</computeroutput> (which is the one you
need) and the other is called <quote><computeroutput>Print Settings for Printer Foo on Server
Bar</computeroutput></quote>. The last one is the one you arrive at when you right-click on the printer and
select <guimenuitem>Print Settings...</guimenuitem>. This is the one that you were taught to use back in the
days of Windows NT, so it is only natural to try the same way with Windows 200x/XP. You would not dream that
there is now a different path to arrive at an identical-looking, but functionally different, dialog to set
defaults for all users.
</para></formalpara>

<tip><para>Try (on Windows 200x/XP) to run this command (as a user with the right privileges):
<indexterm><primary>rundll32</primary></indexterm>
</para>

<para><userinput>
rundll32 printui.dll,PrintUIEntry /p /t3 /n\\<replaceable>SAMBA-SERVER</replaceable>\<replaceable>printersharename</replaceable>
</userinput></para>

<para>
To see the tab with the <guilabel>Printing Defaults</guilabel> button (the one you need), also run this command:
</para>

<para><userinput>
rundll32 printui.dll,PrintUIEntry /p /t0 /n\\<replaceable>SAMBA-SERVER</replaceable>\<replaceable>printersharename</replaceable>
</userinput></para>

<para>
To see the tab with the <guilabel>Printing Preferences</guilabel>
button (the one that does not set systemwide defaults), you can
start the commands from inside a DOS box or from <guimenu>Start</guimenu> -> <guimenuitem>Run</guimenuitem>.
</para>
</tip>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Supporting Large Numbers of Printers</title>

<para>
One issue that has arisen during the recent development phase of Samba is the need to support driver
downloads for hundreds of printers. Using Windows NT APW for this task is somewhat awkward (to say the least). If
you do not want to acquire RSS pains from the printer installation clicking orgy alone, you need
to think about a non-interactive script.
</para>

<para>
If more than one printer is using the same driver, the <command>rpcclient setdriver</command>
command can be used to set the driver associated with an installed queue. If the driver is uploaded to
<smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> once and registered with the printing TDBs, it can be used by
multiple print queues. In this case, you just need to repeat the <command>setprinter</command> subcommand of
<command>rpcclient</command> for every queue (without the need to conduct the <command>adddriver</command>
repeatedly). The following is an example of how this can be accomplished:
</para>

<para><screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>rpcclient <replaceable>SAMBA-CUPS</replaceable> -U root%<replaceable>secret</replaceable> -c 'enumdrivers'</userinput>
 cmd = enumdrivers
 
 [Windows NT x86]
 Printer Driver Info 1:
   Driver Name: [infotec  IS 2075 PCL 6]
 
 Printer Driver Info 1:
   Driver Name: [DANKA InfoStream]
 
 Printer Driver Info 1:
   Driver Name: [Heidelberg Digimaster 9110 (PS)]
 
 Printer Driver Info 1:
   Driver Name: [dm9110]

 Printer Driver Info 1:
   Driver Name: [mydrivername]

 [....]
</screen>

<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>rpcclient <replaceable>SAMBA-CUPS</replaceable> -U root%<replaceable>secret</replaceable> -c 'enumprinters'</userinput>
 cmd = enumprinters
   flags:[0x800000]
   name:[\\SAMBA-CUPS\dm9110]
   description:[\\SAMBA-CUPS\dm9110,,110ppm HiVolume DANKA Stuttgart]
   comment:[110 ppm HiVolume DANKA Stuttgart]
 [....]
</screen>

<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>rpcclient <replaceable>SAMBA-CUPS</replaceable> -U root%<replaceable>secret</replaceable> -c \
  'setdriver <replaceable>dm9110</replaceable> "<replaceable>Heidelberg Digimaster 9110 (PS)</replaceable>"'</userinput>
 cmd = setdriver dm9110 Heidelberg Digimaster 9110 (PPD)
 Successfully set dm9110 to driver Heidelberg Digimaster 9110 (PS).
</screen>

<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>rpcclient <replaceable>SAMBA-CUPS</replaceable> -U root%<replaceable>secret</replaceable> -c 'enumprinters'</userinput>
 cmd = enumprinters
   flags:[0x800000]
   name:[\\SAMBA-CUPS\dm9110]
   description:[\\SAMBA-CUPS\dm9110,Heidelberg Digimaster 9110 (PS),\
     110ppm HiVolume DANKA Stuttgart]
   comment:[110ppm HiVolume DANKA Stuttgart]
 [....]
</screen>

<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>rpcclient <replaceable>SAMBA-CUPS</replaceable> -U root%<replaceable>secret</replaceable> -c 'setdriver <replaceable>dm9110</replaceable> <replaceable>mydrivername</replaceable>'</userinput>
 cmd = setdriver dm9110 mydrivername
 Successfully set dm9110 to mydrivername.
</screen>

<screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>rpcclient <replaceable>SAMBA-CUPS</replaceable> -U root%<replaceable>secret</replaceable> -c 'enumprinters'</userinput>
 cmd = enumprinters
   flags:[0x800000]
   name:[\\SAMBA-CUPS\dm9110]
   description:[\\SAMBA-CUPS\dm9110,mydrivername,\
     110ppm HiVolume DANKA Stuttgart]
   comment:[110ppm HiVolume DANKA Stuttgart]
 [....]
</screen></para>

<para>
It may not be easy to recognize that the first call to <command>enumprinters</command> showed the
<quote>dm9110</quote> printer with an empty string where the driver should have been listed (between
the two commas in the description field). After the <command>setdriver</command> command
succeeds, all is well.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Adding New Printers with the Windows NT APW</title>

<para>
By default, Samba exhibits all printer shares defined in &smb.conf; in the <guiicon>Printers</guiicon>
folder. Also located in this folder is the Windows NT Add Printer Wizard icon. The APW will be shown only if:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	The connected user is able to successfully execute an <command>OpenPrinterEx(\\server)</command> with
	administrative privileges (i.e., root or <smbconfoption name="printer admin"/>).
	</para>

	<tip><para> Try this from a Windows 200x/XP DOS box command prompt:
	</para>

	<para><userinput>
	runas /netonly /user:root rundll32 printui.dll,PrintUIEntry /p /t0 /n \\<replaceable>SAMBA-SERVER</replaceable>\<replaceable>printersharename</replaceable>
	</userinput></para>

	<para>
	Click on <guibutton>Printing Preferences</guibutton>.
	</para></tip></listitem>

	<listitem><para>... contains the setting
	<smbconfoption name="show add printer wizard">yes</smbconfoption> (the
	default).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
The APW can do various things:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	Upload a new driver to the Samba <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> share.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Associate an uploaded driver with an existing (but still driverless) print queue.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Exchange the currently used driver for an existing print queue with one that has been uploaded before.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Add an entirely new printer to the Samba host (only in conjunction with a working
	<smbconfoption name="add printer command"/>. A corresponding
	<smbconfoption name="delete printer command"/> for removing entries from the
	<guiicon>Printers</guiicon> folder may also be provided).
	</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
The last one (add a new printer) requires more effort than the previous ones. To use the APW to successfully
add a printer to a Samba server, the <smbconfoption name="add printer command"/> must have a defined value.
The program hook must successfully add the printer to the UNIX print system (i.e., to
<filename>/etc/printcap</filename>, <filename>/etc/cups/printers.conf</filename> or other appropriate files)
and to &smb.conf; if necessary.
</para>

<para>
When using the APW from a client, if the named printer share does not exist, smbd will execute the
<smbconfoption name="add printer command"/> and reparse to attempt to locate the new printer share. If the
share is still not defined, an error of "<errorname>Access Denied"</errorname> is returned to the client. The
<smbconfoption name="add printer command"/> is executed under the context of the connected user, not
necessarily a root account. A <smbconfoption name="map to guest">bad user</smbconfoption> may have connected
you unwittingly under the wrong privilege. You should check it by using the <command>smbstatus</command>
command.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Error Message: <quote>Cannot connect under a different Name</quote></title>

<para>
Once you are connected with the wrong credentials, there is no means to reverse the situation other than
to close all Explorer windows, and perhaps reboot.
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
<indexterm><primary>net use</primary></indexterm>
	The <command>net use \\SAMBA-SERVER\sharename /user:root</command> gives you an error message:
	<quote>Multiple connections to a server or a shared resource by the same user utilizing
	several user names are not allowed. Disconnect all previous connections to the server,
	esp. the shared resource, and try again.</quote>
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Every attempt to <quote>connect a network drive</quote> to <filename>\\SAMBASERVER\\print$</filename>
	to <constant>z:</constant> is countered by the pertinacious message: <quote>This
	network folder is currently connected under different credentials (username and password).
	Disconnect first any existing connection to this network share in order to connect again under
	a different username and password</quote>.
	</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
So you close all connections. You try again. You get the same message. You check from the Samba side, using
<command>smbstatus</command>. Yes, there are more connections. You kill them all. The client still gives you
the same error message. You watch the smbd.log file on a high debug level and try reconnect. Same error
message, but not a single line in the log. You start to wonder if there was a connection attempt at all. You
run ethereal and tcpdump while you try to connect. Result: not a single byte goes on the wire. Windows still
gives the error message. You close all Explorer windows and start it again. You try to connect &smbmdash; and
this times it works!  Windows seems to cache connection information somewhere and does not keep it up to date
(if you are unlucky, you might need to reboot to get rid of the error message).
</para>

<para>
The easiest way to forcefully terminate all connections from your client to a server is by executing:
<screen>
&dosprompt; net use * /delete
</screen>
This will also disconnect all mapped drives and will allow you create fresh connection as required.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Take Care When Assembling Driver Files</title>

<para>
You need to be extremely careful when you take notes about the files belonging to a particular
driver. Don't confuse the files for driver version <quote>0</quote> (for Windows 9x/Me, going into
<filename>[print$]/WIN/0/</filename>), driver version <filename>2</filename> (kernel mode driver for Windows NT,
going into <filename>[print$]/W32X86/2/</filename>; may be used on Windows 200x/XP also), and
driver version <quote>3</quote> (non-kernel mode driver going into <filename>[print$]/W32X86/3/</filename>;
cannot be used on Windows NT). Quite often these different driver versions contain
files that have the same name but actually are very different. If you look at them from
the Windows Explorer (they reside in <filename>%WINDOWS%\system32\spool\drivers\W32X86\</filename>),
you will probably see names in capital letters, while an <command>enumdrivers</command> command from Samba
would show mixed or lowercase letters, so it is easy to confuse them. If you install them manually using
<command>rpcclient</command> and subcommands, you may even succeed without an error message. Only later,
when you try install on a client, you will encounter error messages like <computeroutput>This server
has no appropriate driver for the printer</computeroutput>.
</para>

<para>
Here is an example. You are invited to look closely at the various files, compare their names and
their spelling, and discover the differences in the composition of the version 2 and 3 sets. Note: the
version 0 set contained 40 <parameter>Dependentfiles</parameter>, so I left it out for space reasons:
</para>

<para><screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>rpcclient -U 'Administrator%<replaceable>secret</replaceable>' -c 'enumdrivers 3' 10.160.50.8 </userinput>

 Printer Driver Info 3:
         Version: [3]
         Driver Name: [Canon iR8500 PS3]
         Architecture: [Windows NT x86]
         Driver Path: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\cns3g.dll]
         Datafile: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\iR8500sg.xpd]
         Configfile: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\cns3gui.dll]
         Helpfile: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\cns3g.hlp]
 
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\aucplmNT.dll]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\ucs32p.dll]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\tnl32.dll]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\aussdrv.dll]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\cnspdc.dll]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\aussapi.dat]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\cns3407.dll]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\CnS3G.cnt]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\NBAPI.DLL]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\NBIPC.DLL]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\cpcview.exe]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\cpcdspl.exe]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\cpcedit.dll]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\cpcqm.exe]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\cpcspl.dll]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\cfine32.dll]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\cpcr407.dll]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\Cpcqm407.hlp]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\cpcqm407.cnt]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\3\cns3ggr.dll]
 
         Monitorname: []
         Defaultdatatype: []

 Printer Driver Info 3:
         Version: [2]
         Driver Name: [Canon iR5000-6000 PS3]
         Architecture: [Windows NT x86]
         Driver Path: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\2\cns3g.dll]
         Datafile: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\2\IR5000sg.xpd]
         Configfile: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\2\cns3gui.dll]
         Helpfile: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\2\cns3g.hlp]
 
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\2\AUCPLMNT.DLL]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\2\aussdrv.dll]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\2\cnspdc.dll]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\2\aussapi.dat]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\2\cns3407.dll]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\2\CnS3G.cnt]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\2\NBAPI.DLL]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\2\NBIPC.DLL]
         Dependentfiles: [\\10.160.50.8\print$\W32X86\2\cns3gum.dll]
 
         Monitorname: [CPCA Language Monitor2]
         Defaultdatatype: []

</screen></para>

<para>
If we write the <quote>version 2</quote> files and the <quote>version 3</quote> files
into different text files and compare the result, we see this
picture:
</para>

<para><screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>sdiff 2-files 3-files</userinput>

<![CDATA[
 cns3g.dll                     cns3g.dll
 iR8500sg.xpd                  iR8500sg.xpd
 cns3gui.dll                   cns3gui.dll
 cns3g.hlp                     cns3g.hlp
 AUCPLMNT.DLL                | aucplmNT.dll
                             > ucs32p.dll
                             > tnl32.dll
 aussdrv.dll                   aussdrv.dll
 cnspdc.dll                    cnspdc.dll
 aussapi.dat                   aussapi.dat
 cns3407.dll                   cns3407.dll
 CnS3G.cnt                     CnS3G.cnt
 NBAPI.DLL                     NBAPI.DLL
 NBIPC.DLL                     NBIPC.DLL
 cns3gum.dll                 | cpcview.exe
                             > cpcdspl.exe 
                             > cpcqm.exe
                             > cpcspl.dll
                             > cfine32.dll
                             > cpcr407.dll
                             > Cpcqm407.hlp
                             > cpcqm407.cnt
                             > cns3ggr.dll
]]>
</screen>

Do not be fooled! Driver files for each version with identical
names may be different in their content, as you can see from this size
comparison:
</para>

<para><screen>
&rootprompt;<userinput>for i in cns3g.hlp cns3gui.dll cns3g.dll; do                  \
           smbclient //10.160.50.8/print\$ -U 'Administrator%xxxx' \
           -c "cd W32X86/3; dir $i; cd .. ; cd 2; dir $i";      \
		   done</userinput>

  CNS3G.HLP               A   122981  Thu May 30 02:31:00 2002
  CNS3G.HLP               A    99948  Thu May 30 02:31:00 2002

  CNS3GUI.DLL             A  1805824  Thu May 30 02:31:00 2002
  CNS3GUI.DLL             A  1785344  Thu May 30 02:31:00 2002

  CNS3G.DLL               A  1145088  Thu May 30 02:31:00 2002
  CNS3G.DLL               A    15872  Thu May 30 02:31:00 2002
</screen></para>

<para>
In my example were even more differences than shown here. Conclusion: you must be careful to select the
correct driver files for each driver version. Don't rely on the names alone, and don't interchange files
belonging to different driver versions.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Samba and Printer Ports</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>LPT1:</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>COM1:</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>FILE:</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>available port</primary></indexterm>
Windows NT/2000 print servers associate a port with each printer. These normally take the form of
<filename>LPT1:</filename>, <filename>COM1:</filename>, <filename>FILE:</filename>, and so on. Samba must also
support the concept of ports associated with a printer. By default, only one printer port, named <quote>Samba
Printer Port</quote>, exists on a system. Samba does not really need such a <quote>port</quote> in order to
print; rather it is a requirement of Windows clients. They insist on being told about an available port when
they request this information; otherwise, they throw an error message at you. So Samba fakes the port
information to keep the Windows clients happy.
</para>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>Printer Pooling</primary></indexterm>
Samba does not support the concept of <constant>Printer Pooling</constant> internally either. Printer
pooling assigns a logical printer to multiple ports as a form of load balancing or failover.
</para>

<para>
If you require multiple ports to be defined for some reason or another (my users and my boss should not know
that they are working with Samba), configure the <smbconfoption name="enumports command"/>,
which can be used to define an external program that generates a listing of ports on a system.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Avoiding Common Client Driver Misconfiguration</title>

<para>
So now the printing works, but there are still problems. Most jobs print well, some do not print at
all. Some jobs have problems with fonts, which do not look good. Some jobs print fast and some
are dead-slow. We cannot cover it all, but we want to encourage you to read the brief paragraph about
<quote>Avoiding the Wrong PostScript Driver Settings</quote> in <link linkend="CUPS-printing">CUPS Printing
Chapter</link>, <link linkend="cups-avoidps1">Avoiding Critical PostScript Driver Settings on the
Client</link>.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>The Imprints Toolset</title>

<para>
<indexterm><primary>Imprints</primary></indexterm>
The Imprints tool set provides a UNIX equivalent of the Windows NT APW.  For complete information, please
refer to the <ulink url="http://imprints.sourceforge.net/">Imprints</ulink> Web site as well as the
documentation included with the Imprints source distribution. This section provides only a brief introduction
to the features of Imprints.
</para>

<para>
Unfortunately, the Imprints toolset is no longer maintained. As of December 2000, the project is in
need of a new maintainer. The most important skill to have is Perl coding and an interest in MS-RPC-based
printing used in Samba. If you wish to volunteer, please coordinate your efforts on the Samba technical
mailing list. The toolset is still in usable form, but only for a series of older printer models where
there are prepared packages to use. Packages for more up-to-date print devices are needed if Imprints
should have a future. Information regarding the Imprints toolset can be obtained from the <ulink
url="http://imprints.sourceforge.net/">Imprints</ulink> home page.
</para>

<sect2>
<title>What Is Imprints?</title>

<para>
Imprints is a collection of tools for supporting these goals:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	Providing a central repository of information regarding Windows NT and 95/98 printer driver packages.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Providing the tools necessary for creating the Imprints printer driver packages.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Providing an installation client that will obtain printer drivers from a central Internet (or intranet) Imprints Server
	repository and install them on remote Samba and Windows NT4 print servers.
	</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Creating Printer Driver Packages</title>

<para>
The process of creating printer driver packages is beyond the scope of this document (refer to Imprints.txt,
included with the Samba distribution for more information). In short, an Imprints driver package
is a gzipped tarball containing the driver files, related INF files, and a control file needed by the
installation client.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>The Imprints Server</title>

<para>
The Imprints server is really a database server that may be queried via standard HTTP mechanisms. Each
printer entry in the database has an associated URL for the actual downloading of the package. Each
package is digitally signed via GnuPG, which can be used to verify that
the package downloaded is actually
the one referred in the Imprints database. It is strongly recommended that this security check
not be disabled.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>The Installation Client</title>

<para>
More information regarding the Imprints installation client is available from the documentation file
<filename>Imprints-Client-HOWTO.ps</filename> that is included with the Imprints source package. The Imprints
installation client comes in two forms:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>A set of command-line Perl scripts.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>A GTK+-based graphical interface to the command-line Perl scripts.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
The installation client (in both forms) provides a means of querying the Imprints database server for
a matching list of known printer model names as well as a means to download and install the drivers on
remote Samba and Windows NT print servers.
</para>

<para>
The basic installation process is in four steps, and Perl code is wrapped around smbclient and rpcclient.
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	For each supported architecture for a given driver:
	<orderedlist>
		<listitem><para>rpcclient: Get the appropriate upload directory on the remote server.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>smbclient: Upload the driver files.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>rpcclient: Issues an AddPrinterDriver() MS-RPC.</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>rpcclient: Issues an AddPrinterEx() MS-RPC to actually create the printer.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
One of the problems encountered when implementing the Imprints tool set was the namespace issues between
various supported client architectures. For example, Windows NT includes a driver named <quote>Apple LaserWriter
II NTX v51.8</quote>, and Windows 95 calls its version of this driver <quote>Apple LaserWriter II NTX</quote>.
</para>

<para>
The problem is how to know what client drivers have been uploaded for a printer. An astute reader will
remember that the Windows NT Printer Properties dialog only includes space for one printer driver name. A
quick look in the Windows NT 4.0 system registry at:
</para>

<para><filename>
 HKLM\System\CurrentControlSet\Control\Print\Environment
</filename></para>

<para>
will reveal that Windows NT always uses the NT driver name. This is okay because Windows NT always requires
that at least the Windows NT version of the printer driver is present. Samba does not have the
requirement internally; therefore, <quote>How can you use the NT driver name if it has not already been installed?</quote>
</para>

<para>
The way of sidestepping this limitation is to require that all Imprints printer driver packages include both the Intel Windows NT and
95/98 printer drivers and that the NT driver is installed first.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Adding Network Printers without User Interaction</title>

<para>
The following MS Knowledge Base article may be of some help if you need to handle Windows 2000 clients:
<emphasis>How to Add Printers with No User Interaction in Windows 2000,</emphasis> (<ulink
url="http://support.microsoft.com/default.aspx?scid=kb;en-us;189105">Microsoft KB 189105</ulink>).  It also
applies to Windows XP Professional clients.  The ideas sketched out in this section are inspired by this
article, which describes a command-line method that can be applied to install network and local printers and
their drivers. This is most useful if integrated in Logon Scripts. You can see what options are available by
typing in the command prompt (<command>DOS box</command>):
</para>

<para><userinput>rundll32 printui.dll,PrintUIEntry /?</userinput></para>

<para>
A window pops up that shows you all of the command-line switches available. An extensive list of examples
is also provided. This is only for Windows 200x/XP; it does not work on Windows NT. Windows NT probably has
some other tools in the respective Resource Kit. Here is a suggestion about what a client logon script
might contain, with a short explanation of what the lines actually do (it works if 200x/XP Windows
clients access printers via Samba, and works for Windows-based print servers too):
</para>

<para><screen>
<userinput>rundll32 printui.dll,PrintUIEntry /dn /n "\\cupsserver\infotec2105-IPDS" /q</userinput>
<userinput>rundll32 printui.dll,PrintUIEntry /in /n "\\cupsserver\infotec2105-PS"</userinput>
<userinput>rundll32 printui.dll,PrintUIEntry /y /n "\\cupsserver\infotec2105-PS"</userinput>
</screen></para>

<para>
Here is a list of the used command-line parameters: 
</para>

<variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term>/dn</term>
		<listitem><para>deletes a network printer.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry><term>/q</term>
		<listitem><para>quiet modus.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry><term>/n</term>
		<listitem><para>names a printer.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry><term>/in</term>
		<listitem><para>adds a network printer connection.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry><term>/y</term>
		<listitem><para>sets printer as default printer.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	Line 1 deletes a possibly existing previous network printer <emphasis>infotec2105-IPDS</emphasis>
	(which had used native Windows drivers with LPRng that were removed from the server that was
	converted to CUPS). The <command>/q</command> at the end prevents confirm
	or error dialog boxes from popping up. They should not be presented to the user logging on.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>	
	Line 2 adds the new printer
	<emphasis>infotec2105-PS</emphasis> (which actually is the same
	physical device but is now run by the new CUPS printing system and associated with the
	CUPS/Adobe PS drivers). The printer and its driver must have been added to Samba prior to
	the user logging in (e.g., by a procedure as discussed earlier in this chapter or by running
	<command>cupsaddsmb</command>). The driver is now autodownloaded to the client PC where the
	user is about to log in.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Line 3 sets the default printer to this new network printer (there might be several other
	printers installed with this same method, and some may be local as well, so we decide for a
	default printer). The default printer selection may, of course, be different for different users.
	</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
The second line only works if the printer <emphasis>infotec2105-PS</emphasis> has an already working
print queue on the <constant>cupsserver</constant> and if the
printer drivers have been successfully uploaded
(via the <command>APW</command>, <command>smbclient/rpcclient</command>, or <command>cupsaddsmb</command>)
into the <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> driver repository of Samba. Some Samba versions
prior to version 3.0 required a restart of smbd after the printer install and the driver upload;
otherwise the script (or any other client driver download) would fail.
</para>

<para>
Since there is no easy way to test for the existence of an installed network printer from the logon script,
do not bother checking. Just allow the de-installation/re-installation to occur every time a user logs in;
it's really quick anyway (1 to 2 seconds).
</para>

<para>
The additional benefits for this are:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	It puts in place any printer default setup changes automatically at every user logon.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	It allows for <quote>roaming</quote> users' login to the domain from different workstations.
	</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
Since network printers are installed per user, this much simplifies the process of keeping the installation
up to date. The few extra seconds at logon time will not really be noticeable. Printers can be centrally
added, changed, and deleted at will on the server with no user intervention required from the clients
(you just need to keep the logon scripts up to date).
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>The <command>addprinter</command> Command</title>

<para>
The <command>addprinter</command> command can be configured to be a shell script or program executed by
Samba. It is triggered by running the APW from a client against the Samba print server. The APW asks
the user to fill in several fields (such as printer name, driver to be used, comment, port monitor,
and so on). These parameters are passed on to Samba by the APW. If the addprinter command is designed in a
way that it can create a new printer (through writing correct printcap entries on legacy systems or
by executing the <command>lpadmin</command> command on more modern systems) and create the associated share,
then the APW will in effect really create a new printer on Samba and the UNIX print subsystem!
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Migration of Classical Printing to Samba</title>

<para>
The basic NT-style printer driver management has not changed considerably in 3.0 over the 2.2.x releases
(apart from many small improvements). Here migration should be quite easy, especially if you followed
previous advice to stop using deprecated parameters in your setup. For migrations from an existing 2.0.x
setup, or if you continued Windows 9x/Me-style printing in your Samba 2.2 installations, it is more of
an effort. Please read the appropriate release notes and the HOWTO Collection for Samba-2.2.x. You can
follow several paths. Here are possible scenarios for migration:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	You need to study and apply the new Windows NT printer and driver support. Previously used
	parameters <parameter>printer driver file</parameter>, <parameter>printer driver</parameter>,
	and <parameter>printer driver location</parameter> are no longer supported.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	If you want to take advantage of Windows NT printer driver support, you also need to migrate the
	Windows 9x/Me drivers to the new setup.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	An existing <filename>printers.def</filename> file (the one specified in the now removed parameter
	<parameter>printer driver file</parameter>) will no longer work with Samba-3. In 3.0, smbd attempts
	to locate Windows 9x/Me driver files for the printer in <smbconfsection name="[print$]"/>
	and additional settings in the TDB and only there; if it fails, it will <emphasis>not</emphasis>
	(as 2.2.x used to do) drop down to using a <filename>printers.def</filename> (and all associated
	parameters). The make_printerdef tool is removed and there is no backward compatibility for this.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>You need to install a Windows 9x/Me driver into the
	<smbconfsection name="[print$]"/> share for a printer on your Samba
	host. The driver files will be stored in the <quote>WIN40/0</quote> subdirectory of
	<smbconfsection name="[print$]"/>, and some other settings and information go
	into the printing-related TDBs.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	If you want to migrate an existing <filename>printers.def</filename> file into the new setup, the only current
	solution is to use the Windows NT APW to install the NT drivers and the 9x/Me drivers. This can be scripted
	using smbclient and rpcclient. See the Imprints installation client on the <ulink noescape="1"
	url="http://imprints.sourceforge.net/">Imprints</ulink> web site for example. See also the discussion of
	rpcclient usage in <link linkend="CUPS-printing">CUPS Printing</link>.
	</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Publishing Printer Information in Active Directory or LDAP</title>

<para>
This topic has also been addressed in <link linkend="NetCommand">Remote and Local Management &smbmdash; The
Net Command</link>. If you wish to volunteer your services to help document this further, please contact 
<ulink url="mail://jht@samba.org">John H. Terpstra</ulink>.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Common Errors</title>

<sect2>
<title>I Give My Root Password but I Do Not Get Access</title>

<para>
Do not confuse the root password, which is valid for the UNIX system (and in most cases stored in the
form of a one-way hash in a file named <filename>/etc/shadow</filename>), with the password used to
authenticate against Samba. Samba does not know the UNIX password. Root access to Samba resources
requires that a Samba account for root must first be created. This is done with the <command>smbpasswd</command>
command as follows:
<screen>
&rootprompt; smbpasswd -a root
New SMB password: secret
Retype new SMB password: secret
</screen>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>My Print Jobs Get Spooled into the Spooling Directory, but Then Get Lost</title>

<para>
Do not use the existing UNIX print system spool directory for the Samba spool directory. It may seem
convenient and a savings of space, but it only leads to problems. The two must be separate. The UNIX/Linux
system print spool directory (e.g., <filename>/var/spool/cups</filename>) is typically owned by a
non-privileged user such as <literal>cups</literal> or <literal>lp</literal>. Additionally. the permissions on
the spool directory are typically restrictive to the owner and/or group. On the other hand, the Samba
spool directory must be world writable, and should have the 't' bit set to ensure that only a temporary
spool file owner can change or delete the file.
</para>

<para>
Depending on the type of print spooling system in use on the UNIX/Linux host, files that the spool
management application finds and that are not currently part of job queue that it is managing can be deleted.
This may explain the observation that jobs are spooled (by Samba) into this directory and just disappear.
</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>

</chapter>
