<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//Samba-Team//DTD DocBook V4.2-Based Variant V1.0//EN" "http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<refentry id="idmap_adex.8">

<refmeta>
	<refentrytitle>idmap_adex</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
	<refmiscinfo class="source">Samba</refmiscinfo>
	<refmiscinfo class="manual">System Administration tools</refmiscinfo>
	<refmiscinfo class="version">3.6</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>


<refnamediv>
	<refname>idmap_adex</refname>
	<refpurpose>Samba's idmap_adex Backend for Winbind</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
	<title>DESCRIPTION</title>
	<para>
	  The idmap_adex plugin provides a way for Winbind to read
	  id mappings from an AD server that uses RFC2307 schema
	  extensions. This module implements both the idmap and nss_info
	  APIs and supports domain trustes as well as two-way cross
	  forest trusts.  It is a read-only plugin requiring that the
	  administrator provide mappings in advance by adding the
	  POSIX attribute information to the users and groups objects
	  in AD.  The most common means of doing this is using &quot;Identity
	  Services for Unix&quot; support on Windows 2003 R2 and later.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Note that you must add the uidNumber, gidNumber, and uid
	  attributes to the partial attribute set of the forest global
	  catalog servers.  This can be done using the Active Directory Schema
	  Management MMC plugin (schmmgmt.dll).
	</para>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
	<title>NSS_INFO</title>
	<para>
	  The nss_info plugin supports reading the unixHomeDirectory,
	  gidNumber, loginShell, and uidNumber attributes from the user
	  object and the gidNumber attribute from the group object to
	  fill in information required by the libc getpwnam() and
	  getgrnam() family of functions.  Group membership is filled in
	  according to the Windows group membership and not the
	  msSFU30PosixMember attribute.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Username aliases are implement by setting the uid attribute
	  on the user object.  While group name aliases are implemented
	  by reading the displayname attribute from the group object.
	</para>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsect1>
	<title>EXAMPLES</title>
	<para>
	  The following example shows how to retrieve idmappings and NSS data
	  from our principal and trusted AD domains.
	</para>

	<programlisting>
	[global]
	idmap config * : backend = adex
	idmap config * : range = 1000-4000000000

	winbind nss info = adex
	winbind normalize names = yes
	</programlisting>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>AUTHOR</title>

	<para>
	The original Samba software and related utilities
	were created by Andrew Tridgell. Samba is now developed
	by the Samba Team as an Open Source project similar
	to the way the Linux kernel is developed.
	</para>
</refsect1>

</refentry>
