<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//Samba-Team//DTD DocBook V4.2-Based Variant V1.0//EN" "http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<refentry id="pam_winbind.conf.5">

<refmeta>
	<refentrytitle>pam_winbind.conf</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
	<refmiscinfo class="source">Samba</refmiscinfo>
	<refmiscinfo class="manual">5</refmiscinfo>
	<refmiscinfo class="version">3.6</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>


<refnamediv>
	<refname>pam_winbind.conf</refname>
	<refpurpose>Configuration file of PAM module for Winbind</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsect1>
	<title>DESCRIPTION</title>

	<para>This configuration file is part of the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>samba</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>7</manvolnum></citerefentry> suite.</para>

	<para>
	pam_winbind.conf is the configuration file for the pam_winbind PAM
	module. See
	<citerefentry><refentrytitle>pam_winbind</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>
	for further details.
	</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>SYNOPSIS</title>

	<para>
		The pam_winbind.conf configuration file is a classic ini-style
		configuration file. There is only one section (global) where
		various options are defined.
	</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>OPTIONS</title>
	<para>

		pam_winbind supports several options which can either be set in
		the PAM configuration files or in the pam_winbind configuration
		file situated at
		<filename>/etc/security/pam_winbind.conf</filename>. Options
		from the PAM configuration file take precedence to those from
		the pam_winbind.conf configuration file.

		<variablelist>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>debug = yes|no</term>
		<listitem><para>Gives debugging output to syslog. Defaults to "no".</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>debug_state = yes|no</term>
		<listitem><para>Gives detailed PAM state debugging output to syslog. Defaults to "no".</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>require_membership_of = [SID or NAME]</term>
		<listitem><para>
		If this option is set, pam_winbind will only succeed if the user is a member of the given SID or NAME. A SID
		can be either a group-SID, an alias-SID or even an user-SID. It is also possible to give a NAME instead of the
		SID. That name must have the form: <parameter>MYDOMAIN\\mygroup</parameter> or
		<parameter>MYDOMAIN\\myuser</parameter>.  pam_winbind will, in that case, lookup the SID internally. Note that
		NAME may not contain any spaces. It is thus recommended to only use SIDs. You can verify the list of SIDs a
		user is a member of with <command>wbinfo --user-sids=SID</command>. This setting is empty by default.
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>try_first_pass = yes|no</term>
		<listitem><para>
		By default, pam_winbind tries to get the authentication token from a previous module. If no token is available
		it asks the user for the old password. With this option, pam_winbind aborts with an error if no authentication
		token from a previous module is available. If a primary password is not valid, PAM will prompt for a password.
		Default to "no".
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>krb5_auth = yes|no</term>
		<listitem><para>

		pam_winbind can authenticate using Kerberos when winbindd is
		talking to an Active Directory domain controller. Kerberos
		authentication must be enabled with this parameter. When
		Kerberos authentication can not succeed (e.g. due to clock
		skew), winbindd will fallback to samlogon authentication over
		MSRPC. When this parameter is used in conjunction with
		<parameter>winbind refresh tickets</parameter>, winbind will
		keep your Ticket Granting Ticket (TGT) uptodate by refreshing
		it whenever necessary. Defaults to "no".

		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>krb5_ccache_type = [type]</term>
		<listitem><para>

		When pam_winbind is configured to try kerberos authentication
		by enabling the <parameter>krb5_auth</parameter> option, it can
		store the retrieved Ticket Granting Ticket (TGT) in a
		credential cache. The type of credential cache can be set with
		this option. Currently the only supported value is:
		<parameter>FILE</parameter>. In that case a credential cache in
		the form of /tmp/krb5cc_UID will be created, where UID is
		replaced with the numeric user id.  Leave empty to just do
		kerberos authentication without having a ticket cache after the
		logon has succeeded. This setting is empty by default.

		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>cached_login = yes|no</term>
		<listitem><para>
		Winbind allows to logon using cached credentials when <parameter>winbind offline logon</parameter> is enabled. To use this feature from the PAM module this option must be set. Defaults to "no".
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>silent = yes|no</term>
		<listitem><para>
		Do not emit any messages. Defaults to "no".
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>mkhomedir = yes|no</term>
		<listitem><para>
		Create homedirectory for a user on-the-fly, option is valid in
		PAM session block. Defaults to "no".
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>warn_pwd_expire = days</term>
		<listitem><para>
		Defines number of days before pam_winbind starts to warn about passwords that are
		going to expire. Defaults to 14 days.
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		</variablelist>

	</para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>SEE ALSO</title>
	<para><citerefentry>
	<refentrytitle>pam_winbind</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>, <citerefentry>
	<refentrytitle>wbinfo</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>, <citerefentry>
	<refentrytitle>winbindd</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>, <citerefentry>
	<refentrytitle>smb.conf</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry></para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>VERSION</title>

	<para>This man page is correct for version 3 of Samba.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>AUTHOR</title>

	<para>
	The original Samba software and related utilities were created by Andrew Tridgell. Samba is now developed by
	the Samba Team as an Open Source project similar to the way the Linux kernel is developed.
	</para>

	<para>This manpage was written by Jelmer Vernooij and Guenther Deschner.</para>

</refsect1>

</refentry>
