<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//Samba-Team//DTD DocBook V4.2-Based Variant V1.0//EN" "http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">

<preface lang="en-US">
<title>Acknowledgments</title>

	<para>
	<emphasis>Samba-3 by Example</emphasis> would not have been written except
	as a result of feedback provided by reviewers and readers of the book <emphasis>The
	Official Samba-3 HOWTO and Reference Guide.</emphasis> This second edition
	was made possible by generous feedback from Samba users. I hope this book
	more than answers the challenge and needs of many more networks that are
	languishing for a better networking solution.
	</para>

	<para>
	I am deeply indebted to a large group of diligent people. Space prevents 
	me from listing all of them, but a few stand out as worthy of mention.
	Jelmer Vernooij made the notable contribution of building the XML production
	environment and thereby made possible the typesetting of this book.
	</para>

	<para>
	Samba would not have come into existence if Andrew Tridgell had not taken
	the first steps. He continues to lead the project. Under the shadow of his
	mantle are some great folks who never give up and are always ready to help.
	Thank you to: Jeremy Allison, Jerry Carter, Andrew Bartlett, Jelmer Vernooij,
	Alexander Bokovoy, Volker Lendecke, and other team members who answered my 
	continuous stream of questions &smbmdash; all of which resulted in improved content 
	in this book.
	</para>

	<para>
	My heartfelt thanks go out also to a small set of reviewers (alphabetically 
	listed) who gave substantial feedback and significant suggestions for improvement:
	Tony Earnshaw, William Enestvedt, Eric Hines, Roland Gruber, Gavin Henry, 
	Steven Henry, Luke Howard, Tarjei Huse, Jon Johnston, Alan Munter, Mike MacIsaac,
	Scott Mann, Ed Riddle, Geoff Scott, Santos Soler, Misty Stanley-Jones, Mark Taylor,
	and Jérôme Tournier.
	</para>

	<para>
	My appreciation is extended to a team of more than 30 additional reviewers who
	helped me to find my way around dark corners.
	</para>

	<para>
	Particular mention is due to Lyndell, Amos, and Melissa who gave me the 
	latitude necessary to spend nearly an entire year writing Samba documentation,
	and then gave more so this second edition could be created.
	</para>

</preface>
