<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//Samba-Team//DTD DocBook V4.2-Based Variant V1.0//EN" "http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<refentry id="idmap_tdb2.8">

<refmeta>
	<refentrytitle>idmap_tdb2</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
	<refmiscinfo class="source">Samba</refmiscinfo>
	<refmiscinfo class="manual">System Administration tools</refmiscinfo>
	<refmiscinfo class="version">3.5</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>


<refnamediv>
	<refname>idmap_tdb2</refname>
	<refpurpose>Samba's idmap_tdb2 Backend for Winbind</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
	<title>DESCRIPTION</title>

	<para>
	The idmap_tdb2 plugin is a substitute for the default idmap_tdb
	backend used by winbindd for storing SID/uid/gid mapping tables
	in clustered environments with Samba and CTDB.
	</para>

	<para>
	In contrast to read only backends like idmap_rid, it is an allocating
	backend: This means that it needs to allocate new user and group IDs in
	order to create new mappings. The allocator can be provided by the
	idmap_tdb2 backend itself or by any other allocating backend like
	idmap_tdb or idmap_ldap. This is configured with the
	parameter <parameter>idmap alloc backend</parameter>.
	</para>

	<para>
	Note that in order for this (or any other allocating) backend to
	function at all, the default backend needs to be writeable.
	The ranges used for uid and gid allocation are the default ranges
	configured by &quot;idmap uid&quot; and &quot;idmap gid&quot;.
	</para>

	<para>
	Furthermore, since there is only one global allocating backend
	responsible for all domains using writeable idmap backends,
	any explicitly configured domain with idmap backend tdb2
	should have the same range as the default range, since it needs
	to use the global uid / gid allocator. See the example below.
	</para>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsect1>
	<title>IDMAP OPTIONS</title>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
		<term>range = low - high</term>
		<listitem><para>
			Defines the available matching uid and gid range for which the
			backend is authoritative.
			If the parameter is absent, Winbind fails over to use
			the &quot;idmap uid&quot; and &quot;idmap gid&quot; options
			from smb.conf.
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>IDMAP SCRIPT</title>

	<para>
	The tdb2 idmap backend supports a script for performing id mappings
	through the smb.conf option <parameter>idmap : script</parameter>.
	The script should accept the following command line options.
	</para>

	<programlisting>
	SIDTOID S-1-xxxx
	IDTOSID UID xxxx
	IDTOSID GID xxxx
	</programlisting>

	<para>
	And it should return one of the following responses as a single line of
	text.
	</para>

	<programlisting>
	UID:yyyy
	GID:yyyy
	SID:yyyy
	ERR:yyyy
	</programlisting>

	<para>
	Note that the script should cover the complete range of SIDs
	that can be passed in for SID to Unix ID mapping, since otherwise
	SIDs unmapped by the script might get mapped to IDs that had
	previously been mapped by the script.
	</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>EXAMPLES</title>

	<para>
	This example shows how tdb2 is used as a the default idmap backend.
	It configures the idmap range through the global options for all
	domains encountered. This same range is used for uid/gid allocation.
	</para>

	<programlisting>
	[global]
	idmap backend = tdb2
	idmap uid = 1000000-2000000
	idmap gid = 1000000-2000000
	</programlisting>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>AUTHOR</title>

	<para>
	The original Samba software and related utilities
	were created by Andrew Tridgell. Samba is now developed
	by the Samba Team as an Open Source project similar
	to the way the Linux kernel is developed.
	</para>
</refsect1>

</refentry>
