<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE glossary PUBLIC "-//Samba-Team//DTD DocBook V4.2-Based Variant V1.0//EN" "http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<glossary>
	<title>Glossary</title>

	<glossentry>
		<glossterm>Access Control List</glossterm>
		<acronym>ACL</acronym>
		<glossdef><para>
		A detailed list of permissions granted to users or groups with respect to file and network
		resource access.
		</para></glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry>
                <glossterm>Active Directory Service</glossterm>
		<acronym>ADS</acronym>
		<glossdef><para>
		A service unique to Microsoft Windows 200x servers that provides a centrally managed
		directory for management of user identities and computer objects, as well as the
		permissions each user or computer may be granted to access distributed network resources.
		ADS uses Kerberos-based authentication and LDAP over Kerberos for directory access.
		</para></glossdef>
        </glossentry>

	<glossentry>
		<glossterm>Common Internet File System</glossterm>
		<acronym>CIFS</acronym>
		<glossdef><para>
		The new name for SMB. Microsoft renamed the SMB protocol to CIFS during
		the Internet hype in the 1990s. At about the time that the SMB protocol was renamed
		to CIFS, an additional dialect of the SMB protocol was in development. The need for the
		deployment of the NetBIOS layer was also removed, thus paving the way for use of the SMB
		protocol natively over TCP/IP (known as NetBIOS-less SMB or <quote>naked</quote> TCP
		transport).
		</para></glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry>
		<glossterm>Common UNIX Printing System</glossterm>
		<acronym>CUPS</acronym>
		<glossdef><para>
		A recent implementation of a high-capability printing system for UNIX developed by
		<ulink url="http://www.easysw.com/">Easy Software Inc.</ulink>. The design objective
		of CUPS was to provide a rich print processing system that has built-in intelligence
		that is capable of correctly rendering (processing) a file that is submitted for
		printing even if it was formatted for an entirely different printer.
		</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry>
		<glossterm>Domain Master Browser</glossterm>
		<acronym>DMB</acronym>
		<glossdef><para>
		The Domain Master Browser maintains a list of all the servers that
		have announced their services within a given workgroup or NT domain.
		</para></glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry>
                <glossterm>Domain Name Service</glossterm>
		<acronym>DNS</acronym>
		<glossdef><para>
		A protocol by which computer hostnames may be resolved to the matching IP address/es.
		DNS is implemented by the Berkeley Internet Name Daemon. There exists a recent version
		of DNS that allows dynamic name registration by network clients or by a DHCP server.
		This recent protocol is known as dynamic DNS (DDNS).
		</para></glossdef>
        </glossentry>

	<glossentry>
                <glossterm>Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol</glossterm>
		<acronym>DHCP</acronym>
		<glossdef><para>
		A protocol that was based on the BOOTP protocol that may be used to dynamically assign
		an IP address, from a reserved pool of addresses, to a network client or device.
		Additionally, DHCP may assign all network configuration settings and may be used to
		register a computer name and its address with a dynamic DNS server.
		</para></glossdef>
        </glossentry>

	<glossentry>
		<glossterm>Group IDentifier</glossterm>
		<acronym>GID</acronym>
		<glossdef><para>
		The UNIX system group identifier; on older systems, a 32-bit unsigned integer, and on
		newer systems, an unsigned 64-bit integer. The GID is used in UNIX-like operating systems
		for all group-level access control.
		</para></glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry>
		<glossterm>Key Distribution Center</glossterm>
		<acronym>KDC</acronym>
		<glossdef><para>
		The Kerberos authentication protocol makes use of security keys (also called a ticket)
		by which access to network resources is controlled. The issuing of Kerberos tickets
		is effected by a KDC.
		</para></glossdef>
	</glossentry>

    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Lightweight Directory Access Protocol</glossterm>
      <acronym>LDAP</acronym>
      <glossdef>
	<para>
	The Lightweight Directory Access Protocol is a technology that
	  originated from the development of X.500 protocol specifications and
	  implementations. LDAP was designed as a means of rapidly searching
	  through X.500 information. Later LDAP was adapted as an engine that
	  could drive its own directory database. LDAP is not a database per
	  se; rather it is a technology that enables high-volume search and
	  locate activity from clients that wish to obtain simply defined
	  information about a subset of records that are stored in a
	  database. LDAP does not have a particularly efficient mechanism for
	  storing records in the database, and it has no concept of transaction
	  processing nor of mechanisms for preserving data consistency. LDAP is
	  premised around the notion that the search and read activity far
	  outweigh any need to add, delete, or modify records. LDAP does
	  provide a means for replication of the database to keep slave
	  servers up to date with a master. It also has built-in capability to
	  handle external references and deferral.
	</para></glossdef>
    </glossentry>

	<glossentry>
		<glossterm>Local Master Browser</glossterm>
		<acronym>LMB</acronym>
		<glossdef><para>
		The Local Master Browser maintains a list of all servers that have announced themselves
		within a given workgroup or NT domain on a particular broadcast isolated subnet.
		</para></glossdef>
	</glossentry>

        <glossentry>
                <glossterm>Media Access Control</glossterm>
		<acronym>MAC</acronym>
                <glossdef><para>
		The hard-coded address of the physical-layer device that is attached to the network.
		All network interface controllers must have a hard-coded and unique MAC address. The
		MAC address is 48 bits long.
                </para></glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry>
		<glossterm>NetBIOS Extended User Interface</glossterm>
		<acronym>NetBEUI</acronym>
		<glossdef><para>
		Very simple network protocol invented by IBM and Microsoft. It is used to do NetBIOS
		over Ethernet with low overhead. NetBEUI is a non-routable protocol.
		</para></glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry>
		<glossterm>Network Address Translation</glossterm>
                <acronym>NAT</acronym>
                <glossdef><para>
		Network address translation is a form of IP address masquerading. It ensures that internal
		private (RFC1918) network addresses from packets inside the network are rewritten so
		that TCP/IP packets that leave the server over a public connection are seen to come only
		from the external network address.
		</para></glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry>
		<glossterm>Network Basic Input/Output System</glossterm>
		<acronym>NetBIOS</acronym>
		<glossdef><para>
		NetBIOS is a simple application programming interface (API) invented in the 1980s
		that allows programs to send data to certain network names. NetBIOS is always run over
		another network protocol such as IPX/SPX, TCP/IP, or Logical Link Control (LLC).
		NetBIOS run over LLC is best known as NetBEUI (the NetBIOS Extended User Interface
		&smbmdash; a complete misnomer!).
		</para></glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry>
		<glossterm>NetBT</glossterm>
		<acronym>NBT</acronym>
		<glossdef><para>
		Protocol for transporting NetBIOS frames over TCP/IP. Uses ports 137, 138, and 139.
		NetBT is a fully routable protocol.
		</para></glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry>
		<glossterm>NT/LanManager Security Support Provider</glossterm>
		<acronym>NTLMSSP</acronym>
		<glossdef><para>
		The NTLM Security Support Provider (NTLMSSP) service in Windows NT4/200x/XP is responsible for
		handling all NTLM authentication requests. It is the front end for protocols such as SPNEGO,
		Schannel, and other technologies. The generic protocol family supported by NTLMSSP is known as
		GSSAPI, the Generic Security Service Application Program Interface specified in RFC2078.
		</para></glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry>
		<glossterm>Server Message Block</glossterm>
		<acronym>SMB</acronym>
		<glossdef><para>
		SMB was the original name of the protocol spoken by Samba. It was invented in the 1980s
		by IBM and adopted and extended further by Microsoft. Microsoft renamed the protocol to
		CIFS during the Internet hype in the 1990s.
		</para></glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry>
		<glossterm>The Simple and Protected GSS-API Negotiation</glossterm>
                <acronym>SPNEGO</acronym>
                <glossdef><para>
		The purpose of SPNEGO is to allow a client and server to negotiate a security mechanism for
		authentication. The protocol is specified in RFC2478 and uses tokens as built via ASN.1 DER.
		DER refers to Distinguished Encoding Rules. These are a set of common rules for creating
		binary encodings in a platform-independent manner. Samba has support for SPNEGO.
                </para></glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry>
		<glossterm>The Official Samba-3 HOWTO and Reference Guide, Second Edition</glossterm>
		<acronym>TOSHARG2</acronym>
		<glossdef><para>
		This book makes repeated reference to <quote>The Official Samba-3 HOWTO and Reference Guide, Second
		Edition</quote> by John H. Terpstra and Jelmer R. Vernooij. This publication is available from
		Amazon.com. Publisher: Prentice Hall PTR (August 2005),
		ISBN: 013122282.
		</para></glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry>
		<glossterm>User IDentifier</glossterm>
		<acronym>UID</acronym>
		<glossdef><para>
		The UNIX system user identifier; on older systems, a 32-bit unsigned integer, and on newer systems,
		an unsigned 64-bit integer. The UID is used in UNIX-like operating systems for all user-level access
		control.
		</para></glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry>
		<glossterm>Universal Naming Convention</glossterm>
		<acronym>UNC</acronym>
		<glossdef><para>A syntax for specifying the location of network resources (such as file shares).
		The UNC syntax was developed in the early days of MS DOS 3.x and is used internally by the SMB protocol.
		</para></glossdef>
	</glossentry>

	<glossentry>
		<glossterm>Wireshark</glossterm>
		<acronym>wireshark</acronym>
		<glossdef><para>
		A network analyzer, also known as a network sniffer or a protocol analyzer. Formerly known as Ethereal, Wireshark is
		freely available for UNIX/Linux and Microsoft Windows systems from
		<ulink url="http://www.wireshark.org">the Wireshark Web site</ulink>.
		</para></glossdef>
	</glossentry>

</glossary>
