<samba:parameter name="acl group control"
                 context="S"
		 type="boolean"
                 xmlns:samba="http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<description>
	<para>
	In a POSIX filesystem, only the owner of a file or directory and the superuser can modify the permissions
	and ACLs on a file. If this parameter is set, then Samba overrides this restriction, and also allows the
 	 <emphasis>primary group owner</emphasis> of a file or directory to modify the permissions and ACLs
	on that file.
	</para>
	<para>
	On a Windows server, groups may be the owner of a file or directory - thus allowing anyone in
	that group to modify the permissions on it. This allows the delegation of security controls
	on a point in the filesystem to the group owner of a directory and anything below it also owned
	by that group. This means there are multiple people with permissions to modify ACLs on a file
	or directory, easing managability.
	</para>
	<para>
	This parameter allows Samba to also permit delegation of the control over a point in the exported
	directory hierarchy in much the same way as Windows. This allows all members of a UNIX group to
	control the permissions on a file or directory they have group ownership on.
	</para>

	<para>
	This parameter is best used with the <smbconfoption name="inherit owner"/> option and also
	on on a share containing directories with the UNIX <emphasis>setgid bit</emphasis> set
	on them, which causes new files and directories created within it to inherit the group
	ownership from the containing directory. 
	</para>

	<para>
	This is parameter has been was deprecated in Samba 3.0.23, but re-activated in
	Samba 3.0.31 and above, as it now only controls permission changes if the user
	is in the owning primary group. It is now no longer equivalent to the
	<parameter moreinfo="none">dos filemode</parameter> option.
	</para>

</description>

<related>inherit owner</related>
<related>inherit permissions</related>

<value type="default">no</value>
</samba:parameter>
