<samba:parameter name="passwd chat"
                 context="G"
		 type="string"
                 advanced="1" developer="1"
                 xmlns:samba="http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<description>
    <para>This string controls the <emphasis>&quot;chat&quot;</emphasis> 
    conversation that takes places between <citerefentry><refentrytitle>smbd</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry> and the local password changing
    program to change the user's password. The string describes a 
    sequence of response-receive pairs that <citerefentry><refentrytitle>smbd</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry> uses to determine what to send to the 
    <smbconfoption name="passwd program"/> and what to expect back. If the expected output is not 
    received then the password is not changed.</para>

    <para>This chat sequence is often quite site specific, depending 
    on what local methods are used for password control (such as NIS 
    etc).</para>

    <para>Note that this parameter only is used if the <smbconfoption
    name="unix password sync"/> parameter is set  to <constant>yes</constant>. This sequence is 
    then called <emphasis>AS ROOT</emphasis> when the SMB password  in the 
    smbpasswd file is being changed, without access to the old password
    cleartext. This means that root must be able to reset the user's password without
    knowing the text of the previous password. In the presence of
    NIS/YP,  this means that the <smbconfoption name="passwd program"/> must
    be executed on the NIS master.
    </para>

    <para>The string can contain the macro <parameter
    moreinfo="none">%n</parameter> which is substituted 
    for the new password.  The old passsword (<parameter 
    moreinfo="none">%o</parameter>) is only available when
    <smbconfoption name="encrypt passwords"/> has been disabled.
    The chat sequence can also contain the standard macros 
    \n, \r, \t and \s to give line-feed, carriage-return, tab 
    and space.  The chat sequence string can also contain 
    a '*' which matches any sequence of characters. Double quotes can 
    be used to collect strings with spaces in them into a single 
    string.</para>

    <para>If the send string in any part of the chat sequence  is a full
    stop &quot;.&quot;,  then no string is sent. Similarly,  if the
    expect string is a full stop then no string is expected.</para>

    <para>If the <smbconfoption name="pam password change"/> parameter is set to <constant>yes</constant>, the
	chat pairs may be matched in any order, and success is determined by the PAM result, not any particular
	output. The \n macro is ignored for PAM conversions.
    </para>

</description>

<related>unix password sync</related>
<related>passwd program</related>
<related>passwd chat debug</related>
<related>pam password change</related>

<value type="default">*new*password* %n\n*new*password* %n\n *changed*</value>
<value type="example">&quot;*Enter NEW password*&quot; %n\n &quot;*Reenter NEW password*&quot; %n\n &quot;*Password changed*&quot;</value>
</samba:parameter>
