<appendix label="E" id="SAMBA-AP-E">
<title>Downloading Samba with CVS</title>




<para>
<indexterm id="appe-idx-992918-0"><primary>downloads</primary><secondary>Samba</secondary><tertiary sortas="obtainedusing CVS">obtained using CVS</tertiary></indexterm>
<indexterm id="appe-idx-992918-1"><primary>Samba</primary><secondary>downloading</secondary><tertiary>with CVS</tertiary></indexterm>This appendix contains information on how to download the latest source version of Samba using the C<indexterm id="appe-idx-992919-0"><primary>Concurrent Versions System (CVS)</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm id="appe-idx-992919-1"><primary>CVS (Concurrent Versions Systems)</primary></indexterm>oncurrent Versions System (CVS). CVS is a freely available configuration management tool available from <indexterm id="appe-idx-992920-0"><primary>Cyclic Software</primary></indexterm>Cyclic Software and is distributed under the<indexterm id="appe-idx-992921-0"><primary>GNU General Public License (GPL)</primary></indexterm> GNU General Public License. You can download the latest copy from <systemitem role="url">http://www.cyclic.com/</systemitem>.<indexterm id="appe-idx-992922-0"><primary>URLs (uniform resource locators)</primary><secondary>Cyclic Software</secondary></indexterm></para>


<para>CVS works on top of the GNU <indexterm id="appe-idx-992923-0"><primary>Revision Control System
(RCS)</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm id="appe-idx-992923-1"><primary>RCS (Revision Control
System)</primary></indexterm>Revision Control System (RCS). Many Unix
systems come preinstalled with RCS. However, if you want to download
the latest version of RCS, you can find it at <indexterm id="appe-idx-992936-0"><primary>URLs (uniform resource
locators)</primary><secondary>RCS (Revision Control
System)</secondary></indexterm><systemitem role="url">http://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/rcs/</systemitem>.</para>


<para>One of the nicest things about CVS is its ability to handle remote logins. This means that people across the globe on the Internet can download and update various source files for any project that uses a CVS repository. Such is the case with Samba. Once you have RCS and CVS installed on your system, you must first log in to the Samba source server with the following command:</para>


<programlisting>cvs -d :pserver:cvs@cvs.samba.org:/cvsroot login</programlisting>


<para>This tells CVS to connect to the CVS server at <filename>cvs.samba.org</filename>. Once you are connected, you can download the latest source tree with the following command:</para>


<programlisting>cvs -d :pserver:cvs@cvs.samba.org:/cvsroot co samba</programlisting>


<para>This will download the entire Samba distribution (file by file) into a directory entitled <filename>/samba</filename>, which it will create on your hard drive. This directory will have the same structure as the Samba source distribution described in <link linkend="SAMBA-CH-2">Chapter 2</link>. It includes source and header files, documentation, and sample configuration files to help get you started. After that is completed, you can follow the instructions in <link linkend="SAMBA-CH-2">Chapter 2</link> to configure and compile Samba on your server.</para>










</appendix>
