<samba:parameter name="ldapsam:editposix"
	context="G"
	type="string"
		 advanced="1" developer="0"
                 xmlns:samba="http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<description>

	<para>
	Editposix is an option that leverages ldapsam:trusted to make it simpler to manage a domain controller
	eliminating the need to set up custom scripts to add and manage the posix users and groups. This option
	will instead directly manipulate the ldap tree to create, remove and modify user and group entries.
	This option also requires a running winbindd as it is used to allocate new uids/gids on user/group
	creation. The allocation range must be therefore configured.
	</para>

	<para>
	To use this option, a basic ldap tree must be provided and the ldap suffix parameters must be properly
	configured. On virgin servers the default users and groups (Administrator, Guest, Domain Users,
	Domain Admins, Domain Guests) can be precreated with the command <command moreinfo="none">net sam
	provision</command>. To run this command the ldap server must be running, Winindd must be running and
	the smb.conf ldap options must be properly configured.

	The typical ldap setup used with the <smbconfoption name="ldapsam:trusted">yes</smbconfoption> option
	is usually sufficient to use <smbconfoption name="ldapsam:editposix">yes</smbconfoption> as well.
	</para>

	<para>
	An example configuration can be the following:

	<programlisting>
	encrypt passwords = true
	passdb backend = ldapsam

	ldapsam:trusted=yes
	ldapsam:editposix=yes

	ldap admin dn = cn=admin,dc=samba,dc=org
	ldap delete dn = yes
	ldap group suffix = ou=groups
	ldap idmap suffix = ou=idmap
	ldap machine suffix = ou=computers
	ldap user suffix = ou=users
	ldap suffix = dc=samba,dc=org

	idmap backend = ldap:"ldap://localhost"

	idmap uid = 5000-50000
	idmap gid = 5000-50000
	</programlisting>

	This configuration assumes a directory layout like described in the following ldif:

	<programlisting>
	dn: dc=samba,dc=org
	objectClass: top
	objectClass: dcObject
	objectClass: organization
	o: samba.org
	dc: samba

	dn: cn=admin,dc=samba,dc=org
	objectClass: simpleSecurityObject
	objectClass: organizationalRole
	cn: admin
	description: LDAP administrator
	userPassword: secret

	dn: ou=users,dc=samba,dc=org
	objectClass: top
	objectClass: organizationalUnit
	ou: users

	dn: ou=groups,dc=samba,dc=org
	objectClass: top
	objectClass: organizationalUnit
	ou: groups

	dn: ou=idmap,dc=samba,dc=org
	objectClass: top
	objectClass: organizationalUnit
	ou: idmap

	dn: ou=computers,dc=samba,dc=org
	objectClass: top
	objectClass: organizationalUnit
	ou: computers
	</programlisting>
	</para>

</description>
<value type="default">no</value>
</samba:parameter>
