<samba:parameter name="printcap name"
	context="G"
	type="string"
		 print="1" developer="1"
                 xmlns:samba="http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<synonym>printcap</synonym>
<description>
    <para>
	This parameter may be used to override the compiled-in default printcap name used by the server (usually
	<filename moreinfo="none"> /etc/printcap</filename>). See the discussion of the <link
	linkend="PRINTERSSECT">[printers]</link> section above for reasons why you might want to do this.
	</para>

    <para>
	To use the CUPS printing interface set <command moreinfo="none">printcap name = cups </command>. This should
	be supplemented by an addtional setting <smbconfoption name="printing">cups</smbconfoption> in the [global]
	section.  <command moreinfo="none">printcap name = cups</command> will use the  &quot;dummy&quot; printcap
	created by CUPS, as specified in your CUPS configuration file.
    </para>

    <para>
	On System V systems that use <command moreinfo="none">lpstat</command> to 
    list available printers you can use <command moreinfo="none">printcap name = lpstat
    </command> to automatically obtain lists of available printers. This 
    is the default for systems that define SYSV at configure time in 
    Samba (this includes most System V based systems). If <parameter moreinfo="none">
    printcap name</parameter> is set to <command moreinfo="none">lpstat</command> on 
    these systems then Samba will launch <command moreinfo="none">lpstat -v</command> and 
    attempt to parse the output to obtain a printer list.
	</para>

    <para>
	A minimal printcap file would look something like this:
<programlisting format="linespecific">
print1|My Printer 1
print2|My Printer 2
print3|My Printer 3
print4|My Printer 4
print5|My Printer 5
</programlisting>
    where the '|' separates aliases of a printer. The fact that the second alias has a space in
	it gives a hint to Samba that it's a comment.
	</para>

    <note><para>
	Under AIX the default printcap name is <filename moreinfo="none">/etc/qconfig</filename>. Samba will
	assume the file is in AIX <filename moreinfo="none">qconfig</filename> format if the string <filename
	moreinfo="none">qconfig</filename> appears in the printcap filename.
	</para></note>

</description>
	
<value type="default">/etc/printcap</value>
<value type="example">/etc/myprintcap</value>
</samba:parameter>
