<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//Samba-Team//DTD DocBook V4.2-Based Variant V1.0//EN" "http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">

<preface id="TOSHpreface">
<title>Preface</title>

<para>
The editors wish to thank you for your decision to purchase this book.
The Official Samba-3 HOWTO and Reference Guide is the result of many years
of accumulation of information, feedback, tips, hints, and happy solutions.
</para>

<para>
Please note that this book is a living document, the contents of which are
constantly being updated. We encourage you to contribute your tips, techniques,
helpful hints, and your special insight into the Windows networking world to
help make the next generation of this book even more valuable to Samba users.
</para>

<para>
We have made a concerted effort to document more comprehensively than has been
done previously the information that may help you to better deploy Samba and to
gain more contented network users.
</para>

<para>
This book provides example configurations, it documents key aspects of Microsoft
Windows networking, provides in-depth insight into the important configuration of
Samba-3, and helps to put all of these into a useful framework.
</para>

<para>
The most recent electronic versions of this document can be found at
<ulink noescape="1" url="http://www.samba.org/">http://www.samba.org/</ulink>
on the <quote>Documentation</quote> page.
</para>

<para>
Updates, patches and corrections are most welcome. Please email your contributions
to any one of the following:
</para>

<para>
<simplelist>
<member><ulink noescape="1" url="mailto:jelmer@samba.org">Jelmer Vernooij (jelmer@samba.org)</ulink></member>
<member><ulink noescape="1" url="mailto:jht@samba.org">John H. Terpstra (jht@samba.org)</ulink></member>
<member><ulink noescape="1" url="mailto:jerry@samba.org">Gerald (Jerry) Carter (jerry@samba.org)</ulink></member>
</simplelist>
</para>

<para>
We wish to advise that only original and unencumbered material can be published. Please do not submit
content that is not your own work unless proof of consent from the copyright holder accompanies your
submission.
</para>

  <!-- the conventions used in this book -->
  <xi:include href="conventions.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" />


</preface>
