<samba:parameter name="idmap config"
                 context="G"
		 type="string"
                 advanced="1" developer="1" hide="1"
                 xmlns:samba="http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<description>

	<para>
	ID mapping in Samba is the mapping between Windows SIDs and Unix user
	and group IDs. This is performed by Winbindd with a configurable plugin
	interface. Samba's ID mapping is configured by options starting with the
	<smbconfoption name="idmap config"/> prefix.
	An idmap option consists of the <smbconfoption name="idmap config"/>
	prefix, followed by a domain name or the asterisk character (*),
	a colon, and the name of an idmap setting for the chosen domain.
	</para>

	<para>
	The idmap configuration is hence divided into groups, one group
	for each domain to be configured, and one group with the the
	asterisk instead of a proper domain name, which speifies the
	default configuration that is used to catch all domains that do
	not have an explicit idmap configuration of their own.
	</para>

	<para>
	There are three general options available:
	</para>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
		<term>backend = backend_name</term>
		<listitem><para>
		This specifies the name of the idmap plugin to use as the
		SID/uid/gid backend for this domain. The standard backends are
		tdb
		(<citerefentry><refentrytitle>idmap_tdb</refentrytitle> <manvolnum>8</manvolnum> </citerefentry>),
		tdb2
		(<citerefentry><refentrytitle>idmap_tdb2</refentrytitle> <manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>),
		ldap
		(<citerefentry><refentrytitle>idmap_ldap</refentrytitle> <manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>),
		,
		rid
		(<citerefentry><refentrytitle>idmap_rid</refentrytitle> <manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>),
		,
		hash
		(<citerefentry><refentrytitle>idmap_hash</refentrytitle> <manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>),
		,
		autorid
		(<citerefentry><refentrytitle>idmap_autorid</refentrytitle> <manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>),
		,
		ad
		(<citerefentry><refentrytitle>idmap_ad</refentrytitle> <manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>),
		,
		adex
		(<citerefentry><refentrytitle>idmap_adex</refentrytitle> <manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>),
		,
		and nss.
		(<citerefentry><refentrytitle>idmap_nss</refentrytitle> <manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>),
		The corresponding manual pages contain the details, but
		here is a summary.
		</para>
		<para>
		The first three of these create mappings of their own using
		internal unixid counters and store the mappings in a database.
		These are suitable for use in the default idmap configuration.
		The rid and hash backends use a pure algorithmic calculation
		to determine the unixid for a SID. The autorid module is a
		mixture of the tdb and rid backend. It creates ranges for
		each domain encountered and then uses the rid algorithm for each
		of these automatically configured domains individually.
		The ad and adex
		backends both use unix IDs stored in Active Directory via
		the standard schema extensions. The nss backend reverses
		the standard winbindd setup and gets the unixids via names
		from nsswitch which can be useful in an ldap setup.
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>range = low - high</term>
		<listitem><para>
		Defines the available matching uid and gid range for which the
		backend is authoritative. For allocating backends, this also
		defines the start and the end of the range for allocating
		new unid IDs.
		</para>
		<para>
		winbind uses this parameter to find the backend that is
		authoritative for a unix ID to SID mapping, so it must be set
		for each individually configured domain and for the default
		configuration. The configured ranges must be mutually disjoint.
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>read only = yes|no</term>
		<listitem><para>
		This option can be used to turn the writing backends
		tdb, tdb2, and ldap into read only mode. This can be useful
		e.g. in cases where a pre-filled database exists that should
		not be extended automatically.
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<para>
	The following example illustrates how to configure the <citerefentry>
	<refentrytitle>idmap_ad</refentrytitle> <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
	</citerefentry> backend for the CORP domain and the
	<citerefentry><refentrytitle>idmap_tdb</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry> backend for all other
	domains. This configuration assumes that the admin of CORP assigns
	unix ids below 1000000 via the SFU extensions, and winbind is supposed
	to use the next million entries for its own mappings from trusted
	domains and for local groups for example.
	</para>

	<programlisting>
	idmap config * : backend = tdb
	idmap config * : range = 1000000-1999999

	idmap config CORP : backend  = ad
	idmap config CORP : range = 1000-999999
	</programlisting>
	
</description>
</samba:parameter>
