<colophon id="colophon">
<title>Colophon</title>




<para>Our look is the result of reader comments, our own
experimentation, and feedback from distribution channels. Distinctive
covers complement our distinctive approach to technical topics,
breathing personality and life into potentially dry subjects.</para>


<para>The animal on the cover of <citetitle>Using Samba</citetitle> is
a African ground hornbill (<foreignphrase>Bucorvus
cafer</foreignphrase>). This type of bird is one of fifty hornbill
species. The African ground hornbill is a medium to large sized bird
characterized by a bright red waddle under a very long beak,
dark-colored body and wings, long eyelashes, and short legs. Like all
hornbills, it has a casque, a large but lightweight growth on the top
of its beak, which grows more folds as the bird ages. It is the only
ground-dwelling species of hornbill, though it is able to fly when
necessary. It lives in the grasslands of southern and eastern Africa,
and nests in the foliage of dense trees, not in nest holes in the
ground as other hornbills do. Its diet includes mostly fruit, as well
as large insects and small mammals. The African ground hornbill is
considered to be sacred by many Africans, and as such this bird is
part of many legends and superstitions.</para>


<para>Sarah Jane Shangraw was the production editor and proofreader
for <citetitle>Using Samba</citetitle>. Sarah Lemaire copyedited the
text. Maureen Dempsey and Claire Cloutier LeBlanc provided quality
control. Brenda Miller wrote the index.</para>


<para>Edie Freedman designed the cover of this book based on her own
series design. The cover image of an African ground hornbill is a
19th-century engraving from the Dover Pictorial Archive. Kathleen
Wilson produced the cover layout with QuarkXPress 3.32 using Adobe's
ITC Garamond font. Kathleen Wilson also created the CD design.</para>


<para>Alicia Cech designed the interior layout based on a series
design by Nancy Priest. Mike Sierra implemented the design in
FrameMaker 5.5. The text and heading fonts are ITC Garamond Light and
Garamond Book. The illustrations that appear in the book were produced
by Robert Romano and Rhon Porter using Macromedia FreeHand 8 and Adobe
Photoshop 5. Interior composition was done by Sarah Jane Shangraw,
Sebastian Banker, Jeff Holcolmb, and Abigail Myers. This colophon was
written by Nicole Arigo.</para>











<para>The online edition of this book was created by the Safari
production group (John Chodacki, Becki Maisch, and Madeleine Newell)
using a set of Frame-to-XML conversion and cleanup tools written and
maintained by Erik Ray, Benn Salter, John Chodacki, and Jeff
Liggett.</para>
</colophon>
